<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 2><4%>
	Cæsar, my lord.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 2><4%>
	I shall remember:
	When Cæsar says 'Do this,' it is perform'd.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	Cæsar.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	Fear him not, Cæsar, he's not dangerous;
	He is a noble Roman, and well given.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 2><SCENE 2><40%>
	So to most noble Cæsar.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 3><SCENE 1><50%>
	O mighty Cæsar! dost thou lie so low?
	Are all thy conquests, glories, triumphs, spoils,
	Shrunk to this little measure? Fare thee well.
	I know not, gentlemen, what you intend,
	Who else must be let blood, who else is rank:
	If I myself, there is no hour so fit
	As Cæsar's death's hour, nor no instrument
	Of half that worth as those your swords, made rich
	With the most noble blood of all this world.
	I do beseech ye, if ye bear me hard,
	Now, whilst your purpled hands do reek and smoke,
	Fulfil your pleasure. Live a thousand years,
	I shall not find myself so apt to die:
	No place will please me so, no mean of death,
	As here by Cæsar, and by you cut off,
	The choice and master spirits of this age.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 3><SCENE 1><51%>
	I doubt not of your wisdom.
	Let each man render me his bloody hand:
	First, Marcus Brutus, will I shake with you;
	Next, Caius Cassius, do I take your hand;
	Now, Decius Brutus, yours; now yours, Metellus;
	Yours, Cinna; and, my valiant Casca, yours;
	Though last, not least in love, yours, good Trebonius.
	Gentlemen all,—alas! what shall I say?
	My credit now stands on such slippery ground,
	That one of two bad ways you must conceit me,
	Either a coward or a flatterer.
	That I did love thee, Cæsar, O! 'tis true:
	If then thy spirit look upon us now,
	Shall it not grieve thee dearer than thy death,
	To see thy Antony making his peace,
	Shaking the bloody fingers of thy foes,
	Most noble! in the presence of thy corse?
	Had I as many eyes as thou hast wounds,
	Weeping as fast as they com.linkedin.dagli.util.stream forth thy blood,
	It would become me better than to close
	In terms of friendship with thine enemies.
	Pardon me, Julius! Here wast thou bay'd, brave hart;
	Here didst thou fall; and here thy hunters stand,
	Sign'd in thy spoil, and crimson'd in thy leth
	O world! thou wast the forest to this hart;
	And this, indeed, O world! the heart of thee.
	How like a deer, strucken by many princes,
	Dost thou here lie!
<SPEECH 8><ACT 3><SCENE 1><52%>
	Pardon me, Caius Cassius:
	The enemies of Cæsar shall say this;
	Then, in a friend, it is cold modesty.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 3><SCENE 1><52%>
	Therefore I took your hands, but was indeed
	Sway'd from the point by looking down on Cæsar.
	Friends am I with you all, and love you all,
	Upon this hope, that you shall give me reasons
	Why and wherein Cæsar was dangerous.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 3><SCENE 1><52%>
	That's all I seek:
	And am moreover suitor that I may
	Produce his body to the market place;
	And in the pulpit, as becomes a friend,
	Speak in the order of his funeral.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 3><SCENE 1><53%>
	Be it so;
	I do desire no more.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 3><SCENE 1><54%>
	O! pardon me, thou bleeding piece of earth,
	That I am meek and gentle with these butchers;
	Thou art the ruins of the noblest man
	That ever lived in the tide of times.
	Woe to the hand that shed this costly blood!
	Over thy wounds now do I prophesy,
	Which like dumb mouths do ope their ruby lips,
	To beg the voice and utterance of my tongue,
	A curse shall light upon the limbs of men;
	Domestic fury and fierce civil strife
	Shall cumber all the parts of Italy;
	Blood and destruction shall be so in use,
	And dreadful objects so familiar,
	That mothers shall but smile when they behold
	Their infants quarter'd with the hands of war;
	All pity chok'd with custom of fell deeds:
	And Cæsar's spirit, ranging for revenge,
	With Ate by his side come hot from hell,
	Shall in these confines with a monarch's voice
	Cry 'Havoc!' and let slip the dogs of war;
	That this foul deed shall smell above the earth
	With carrion men, groaning for burial.
	You serve Octavius Cæsar, do you not?
<SPEECH 13><ACT 3><SCENE 1><54%>
	Cæsar did write for him to come to Rome.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 3><SCENE 1><55%>
	Thy heart is big, get thee apart and weep.
	Passion, I see, is catching; for mine eyes,
	Seeing those beads of sorrow stand in thine,
	Began to water. Is thy master coming?
<SPEECH 15><ACT 3><SCENE 1><55%>
	Post back with speed, and tell him what hath chanc'd:
	Hare is a mourning Rome, a dangerous Rome,
	No Rome of safety for Octavius yet;
	Hie hence and tell him so. Yet, stay awhile;
	Thou shalt not back till I have borne this corpse
	Into the market-place; there shall I try,
	In my oration, how the people take
	The cruel issue of these bloody men;
	According to the which thou shalt discourse
	To young Octavius of the state of things.
	Lead me your hand.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 3><SCENE 2><58%>
	For Brutus' sake, I am beholding to you.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 3><SCENE 2><59%>
	You gentle Romans,—
<SPEECH 18><ACT 3><SCENE 2><59%>
	Friends, Romans, countrymen, lend me your ears;
	I come to bury Cæsar, not to praise him.
	The evil that men do lives after them,
	The good is oft interred with their bones;
	So let it be with Cæsar. The noble Brutus
	Hath told you Cæsar was ambitious;
	If it were so, it was a grievous fault,
	And grievously hath Cæsar answer'd it.
	Here, under leave of Brutus and the rest,—
	For Brutus is an honourable man;
	So are they all, all honourable men,—
	Come I to speak in Cæsar's funeral.
	He was my friend, faithful and just to me:
	But Brutus says he was ambitious;
	And Brutus is an honourable man.
	He hath brought many captives home to Rome,
	Whose ransoms did the general coffers fill:
	Did this in Cæsar seem ambitious?
	When that the poor have cried, Cæsar hath wept;
	Ambition should be made of sterner stuff:
	Yet Brutus says he was ambitious;
	And Brutus is an honourable man.
	You all did see that on the Lupercal
	I thrice presented him a kingly crown,
	Which he did thrice refuse: was this ambition?
	Yet Brutus says he was ambitious;
	And, sure, he is an honourable man.
	I speak not to disprove what Brutus spoke,
	But here I am to speak what I do know,
	You all did love him once, not without cause:
	What cause withholds you then to mourn for him?
	O judgment! thou art fled to brutish beasts,
	And men have lost their reason. Bear with me;
	My heart is in the coffin there with Cæsar,
	And I must pause till it come back to me.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 3><SCENE 2><60%>
	But yesterday the word of Cæsar might
	Have stood against the world; now lies he there,
	And none so poor to do him reverence.
	O masters! if I were dispos'd to stir
	Your hearts and minds to mutiny and rage,
	I should do Brutus wrong, and Cassius wrong,
	Who, you all know, are honourable men.
	I will not do them wrong; I rather choose
	To wrong the dead, to wrong myself, and you,
	Than I will wrong such honourable men
	But here's a parchment with the seal of Cæsar;
	I found it in his closet, 'tis his will.
	Let but the commons hear this testament—
	Which, pardon me, I do not mean to read—
	And they would go and kiss dead Cæsar's wounds,
	And dip their napkins in his sacred blood,
	Yea, beg a hair of him for memory,
	And, dying, mention it within their wills,
	Bequeathing it as a rich legacy
	Unto their issue.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 3><SCENE 2><61%>
	Have patience, gentle friends; I must not read it:
	It is not meet you know how Cæsar lov'd you.
	You are not wood, you are not stones, but men;
	And, being men, hearing the will of Cæsar,
	It will inflame you, it will make you mad.
	'Tis good you know not that you are his heirs;
	For if you should, O! what would come of it.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 3><SCENE 2><61%>
	Will you be patient? Will you stay awhile?
	I have o'ershot myself to tell you of it.
	I fear I wrong the honourable men
	Whose daggers have stabb'd Cæsar; I do fear it.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 3><SCENE 2><62%>
	You will compel me then to read the will?
	Then make a ring about the corpse of Cæsar,
	And let me show you him that made the will.
	Shall I descend? and will you give me leave?
<SPEECH 23><ACT 3><SCENE 2><62%>
	Nay, press not so upon me; stand far off.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 3><SCENE 2><62%>
	If you have tears, prepare to shed them now.
	You all do know this mantle: I remember
	The first time ever Cæsar put it on;
	'Twas on a summer's evening, in his tent,
	That day he overcame the Nervii.
	Look! in this place ran Cassius' dagger through:
	See what a rent the envious Casca made:
	Through this the well-beloved Brutus stabb'd;
	And, as he pluck'd his cursed steel away,
	Mark how the blood of Cæsar follow'd it,
	As rushing out of doors, to be resolv'd
	If Brutus so unkindly knock'd or no;
	For Brutus, as you know, was Cæsar's angel:
	Judge, O you gods! how dearly Cæsar lov'd him.
	This was the most unkindest cut of all;
	For when the noble Cæsar saw him stab,
	Ingratitude, more strong than traitors' arms,
	Quite vanquish'd him: then burst his mighty heart;
	And, in his mantle muffling up his face,
	Even at the base of Pompey's status,
	Which all the while ran blood, great Cæsar fell.
	O! what a fall was there, my countrymen;
	Then I, and you, and all of us fell down,
	Whilst bloody treason flourish'd over us.
	O! now you weep, and I perceive you feel
	The dint of pity; these are gracious drops.
	Kind souls, what! weep you when you but behold
	Our Cæsar's vesture wounded? Look you here,
	Here is himself, marr'd, as you see, with traitors.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 3><SCENE 2><63%>
	Stay, countrymen!
<SPEECH 26><ACT 3><SCENE 2><64%>
	Good friends, sweet friends, let me not stir you up
	To such a sudden flood of mutiny.
	They that have done this deed are honourable:
	What private griefs they have, alas! I know not,
	That made them do it; they are wise and honourable,
	And will, no doubt, with reasons answer you.
	I come not, friends, to steal away your hearts:
	I am no orator, as Brutus is;
	But, as you know me all, a plain blunt man,
	That love my friend; and that they know full well
	That gave me public leave to speak of him.
	For I have neither wit, nor words, nor worth,
	Action, nor utterance, nor the power of speech,
	To stir men's blood: I only speak right on;
	I tell you that which you yourselves do know,
	Show you sweet Cæsar's wounds, poor poor dumb mouths,
	And bid them speak for me: but were I Brutus,
	And Brutus Antony, there were an Antony
	Would ruffle up your spirits, and put a tongue
	In every wound of Cæsar, that should move
	The stones of Rome to rise and mutiny.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 3><SCENE 2><64%>
	Yet hear me, countrymen; yet hear me speak.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 3><SCENE 2><65%>
	Why, friends, you go to do you know not what.
	Wherein hath Cæsar thus deserv'd your loves?
	Alas! you know not: I must tell you then.
	You have forgot the will I told you of.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 3><SCENE 2><65%>
	Here is the will, and under Cæsar's seal.
	To every Roman citizen he gives,
	To every several man, seventy-five drachmas.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 3><SCENE 2><65%>
	Hear me with patience.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 3><SCENE 2><65%>
	Moreover, he hath left you all his walks,
	His private arbours, and new-planted orchards,
	On this side Tiber; he hath left them you,
	And to your heirs for ever; common pleasures,
	To walk abroad, and recreate yourselves.
	Here was a Cæsar! when comes such another?
<SPEECH 32><ACT 3><SCENE 2><66%>
	Now let it work: mischief, thou art afoot,
	Take thou what course thou wilt!
	How now, fellow!
<SPEECH 33><ACT 3><SCENE 2><66%>
	Where is he?
<SPEECH 34><ACT 3><SCENE 2><66%>
	And thither will I straight to visit him.
	He comes upon a wish. Fortune is merry,
	And in this mood will give us any thing.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 3><SCENE 2><66%>
	Belike they had some notice of the people,
	How I had mov'd them. Bring me to Octavius.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 4><SCENE 1><68%>
	These many then shall die; their names are prick'd.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 4><SCENE 1><68%>
	He shall not live; look, with a spot I damn him.
	But, Lepidus, go you to Cæsar's house;
	Fetch the will hither, and we shall determine
	How to cut off some charge in legacies.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 4><SCENE 1><68%>
	This is a slight unmeritable man,
	Meet to be sent on errands: is it fit,
	The three-fold world divided, he should stand
	One of the three to share it?
<SPEECH 39><ACT 4><SCENE 1><68%>
	Octavius, I have seen more days than you:
	And though we lay these honours on this man,
	To ease ourselves of divers slanderous loads,
	He shall but bear them as the ass bears gold,
	To groan and sweat under the business,
	Either led or driven, as we point the way;
	And having brought our treasure where we will,
	Then take we down his load, and turn him off,
	Like to the empty ass, to shake his ears,
	And graze in commons.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 4><SCENE 1><69%>
	So is my horse, Octavius; and for that
	I do appoint him store of provender.
	It is a creature that I teach to fight,
	To wind, to stop, to run directly on,
	His corporal motion govern'd by my spirit.
	And, in some taste, is Lepidus but so;
	He must be taught, and train'd, and bid go forth;
	A barren-spirited fellow; one that feeds
	On abject orts, and imitations,
	Which, out of use and stal'd by other men,
	Begin his fashion: do not talk of him
	But as a property. And now, Octavius,
	Listen great things: Brutus and Cassius
	Are levying powers; we must straight make head;
	Therefore let our alliance be combin'd,
	Our best friends made, and our best means stretch'd out;
	And let us presently go sit in council,
	How covert matters may be best disclos'd,
	And open perils surest answered.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 5><SCENE 1><85%>
	Tut! I am in their bosoms, and I know
	Wherefore they do it: they could be content
	To visit other places; and come down
	With fearful bravery, thinking by this face
	To fasten in our thoughts that they have courage;
	But 'tis not so.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 5><SCENE 1><85%>
	Octavius, lead your battle softly on,
	Upon the left hand of the even field.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 5><SCENE 1><85%>
	Why do you cross me in this exigent?
<SPEECH 44><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	No, Cæsar, we will answer on their charge.
	Make forth; the generals would have some words.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	In your bad strokes, Brutus, you give good words:
	Witness the hole you made in Cæsar's heart,
	Crying, 'Long live! hail, Cæsar!'
<SPEECH 46><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	Not stingless too.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	Villains! you did not so when your vile daggers
	Hack'd one another in the sides of Cæsar:
	How show'd your teeth like apes, and fawn'd like hounds,
	And bow'd like bondmen, kissing Cæsar's feet;
	Whilst damned Casca, like a cur, behind
	Struck Cæsar on the neck. O you flatterers!
<SPEECH 48><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Old Cassius still!
<SPEECH 49><ACT 5><SCENE 4><96%>
	Where is he?
<SPEECH 50><ACT 5><SCENE 4><96%>
	This is not Brutus, friend; but, I assure you,
	A prize no less in worth. Keep this man safe,
	Give him all kindness: I had rather have
	Such men my friends than enemies. Go on,
	And see whe'r Brutus be alive or dead;
	And bring us word unto Octavius' tent,
	How every thing is chanc'd.
<SPEECH 51><ACT 5><SCENE 5><99%>
	This was the noblest Roman of them all;
	All the conspirators save only he
	Did that they did in envy of great Cæsar;
	He only, in a general honest thought
	And common good to all, made one of them.
	His life was gentle, and the elements
	So mix'd in him that Nature might stand up
	And say to all the world, 'This was a man!'
