<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 3><5%>
	How far is 't call'd to Forres? What are these,
	So wither'd and so wild in their attire,
	That look not like th' inhabitants o' the earth,
	And yet are on 't? Live you? or are you aught
	That man may question? You seem to understand me,
	By each at once her choppy finger laying
	Upon her skinny lips: you should be women,
	And yet your beards forbid me to interpret
	That you are so.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 3><6%>
	Good sir, why do you start, and seem to fear
	Things that do sound so fair? I' the name of truth,
	Are ye fantastical, or that indeed
	Which outwardly ye show? My noble partner
	You greet with present grace and great prediction
	Of noble having and of royal hope,
	That he seems rapt withal: to me you speak not.
	If you can look into the seeds of time,
	And say which grain will grow and which will not,
	Speak then to me, who neither beg nor fear
	Your favours nor your hate.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 3><7%>
	The earth hath bubbles, as the water has,
	And these are of them. Whither are they vanish'd?
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 3><7%>
	Were such things here as we do speak about?
	Or have we eaten on the insane root
	That takes the reason prisoner?
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 3><8%>
	You shall be king.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 3><8%>
	To the self-same tune and words. Who's here?
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 3><8%>
	What! can the devil speak true?
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 3><9%>
	That, trusted home,
	Might yet enkindle you unto the crown,
	Besides the Thane of Cawdor. But 'tis strange:
	And oftentimes, to win us to our harm,
	The instruments of darkness tell us truths,
	Win us with honest trifles, to betray's
	In deepest consequence.
	Cousins, a word, I pray you.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 3><10%>
	Look, how our partner's rapt.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 3><10%>
	New honours come upon him,
	Like our strange garments, cleave not to their mould
	But with the aid of use.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 3><10%>
	Worthy Macbeth, we stay upon your leisure.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 3><11%>
	Very gladly.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 1><SCENE 4><12%>
	There if I grow,
	The harvest is your own.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 1><SCENE 6><17%>
	This guest of summer,
	The temple-haunting martlet, does approve
	By his lov'd mansionry that the heaven's breath
	Smells wooingly here: no jutty, frieze,
	Buttress, nor coign of vantage, but this bird
	Hath made his pendent bed and procreant cradle:
	Where they most breed and haunt, I have observ'd
	The air is delicate.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	How goes the night, boy?
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	And she goes down at twelve.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	Hold, take my sword. There's husbandry in heaven;
	Their candles are all out. Take thee that too.
	A heavy summons lies like lead upon me,
	And yet I would not sleep: merciful powers!
	Restrain in me the cursed thoughts that nature
	Gives way to in repose.
	Give me my sword.—
	Who's there?
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	What, sir! not yet at rest? The king's a-bed:
	He hath been in unusual pleasure, and
	Sent forth great largess to your offices.
	This diamond he greets your wife withal,
	By the name of most kind hostess; and shut up
	In measureless content.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	All's well.
	I dreamt last night of the three weird sisters:
	To you they have show'd some truth.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	At your kind'st leisure.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	So I lose none
	In seeking to augment it, but still keep
	My bosom franchis'd and allegiance clear,
	I shall be counsell'd.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	Thanks, sir: the like to you.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 3><34%>
	Too cruel any where.
	Dear Duff, I prithee, contradict thyself,
	And say it is not so.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 2><SCENE 3><36%>
	Look to the lady:
	And when we have our naked frailties hid,
	That suffer in exposure, let us meet,
	And question this most bloody piece of work,
	To know it further. Fears and scruples shake us:
	In the great hand of God I stand, and thence
	Against the undivulg'd pretence I fight
	Of treasonous malice.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 3><SCENE 1><39%>
	Thou hast it now: King, Cawdor, Glamis, all,
	As the weird women promis'd; and, I fear,
	Thou play'dst most foully for 't; yet it was said
	It should not stand in thy posterity,
	But that myself should be the root and father
	Of many kings. If there come truth from them,—
	As upon thee, Macbeth, their speeches shine,—
	Why, by the verities on thee made good,
	May they not be my oracles as well,
	And set me up in hope? But, hush! no more.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 3><SCENE 1><40%>
	Let your highness
	Command upon me; to the which my duties
	Are with a most indissoluble tie
	For ever knit.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 3><SCENE 1><40%>
	Ay, my good lord.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 3><SCENE 1><40%>
	As far, my lord, as will fill up the time
	'Twixt this and supper; go not my horse the better,
	I must become a borrower of the night
	For a dark hour or twain.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 3><SCENE 1><40%>
	My lord, I will not.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 3><SCENE 1><41%>
	Ay, my good lord: our time does call upon 's.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 3><SCENE 3><49%>
	</STAGE DIR> Give us a light there, ho!
<SPEECH 32><ACT 3><SCENE 3><49%>
	It will be rain to-night.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 3><SCENE 3><49%>
	O, treachery! Fly, good Fleance, fly, fly, fly!
	Thou mayst revenge. O slave!
