<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 2><4%>
	A soothsayer bids you beware the ides of March.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 2><5%>
	Not I.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 2><5%>
	I am not gamesome: I do lack some part
	Of that quick spirit that is in Antony.
	Let me not hinder, Cassius, your desires;
	I'll leave you.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 2><5%>
	Cassius,
	Be not deceiv'd: if I have veil'd my look,
	I turn the trouble of my countenance
	Merely upon myself. Vexed I am
	Of late with passions of some difference,
	Conceptions only proper to myself,
	Which give some soil perhaps to my behaviours;
	But let not therefore my good friends be griev'd,—
	Among which number, Cassius, be you one,—
	Nor construe any further my neglect,
	Than that poor Brutus, with himself at war,
	Forgets the shows of love to other men.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 2><6%>
	No, Cassius; for the eye sees not itself,
	But by reflection, by some other things.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 2><6%>
	Into what dangers would you lead me, Cassius,
	That you would have me seek into myself
	For that which is not in me?
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	What means this shouting? I do fear the people
	Choose Cæsar for their king.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	I would not, Cassius; yet I love him well.
	But wherefore do you hold me here so long?
	What is it that you would impart to me?
	If it be aught toward the general good,
	Set honour in one eye and death i' the other,
	And I will look on both indifferently;
	For let the gods so speed me as I love
	The name of honour more than I fear death.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 2><8%>
	Another general shout!
	I do believe that these applauses are
	For some new honours that are heaped on Cæsar.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 2><10%>
	That you do love me, I am nothing jealous;
	What you would work me to, I have some aim:
	How I have thought of this and of these times,
	I shall recount hereafter; for this present,
	I would not, so with love I might entreat you,
	Be any further mov'd. What you have said
	I will consider; what you have to say
	I will with patience hear, and find a time
	Both meet to hear and answer such high things.
	Till then, my noble friend, chew upon this:
	Brutus had rather be a villager
	Than to repute himself a son of Rome
	Under these hard conditions as this time
	Is like to lay upon us.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 2><10%>
	The games are done and Cæsar is returning.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 2><10%>
	I will do so. But, look you, Cassius,
	The angry spot doth glow on Cæsar's brow,
	And all the rest look like a chidden train:
	Calphurnia's cheek is pale, and Cicero
	Looks with such ferret and such fiery eyes
	As we have seen him in the Capitol,
	Being cross'd in conference by some senators.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 1><SCENE 2><12%>
	Ay, Casca; tell us what hath chanc'd to-day,
	That Cæsar looks so sad.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 1><SCENE 2><12%>
	I should not then ask Casca what had chanc'd.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 1><SCENE 2><12%>
	What was the second noise for?
<SPEECH 16><ACT 1><SCENE 2><12%>
	Was the crown offered him thrice?
<SPEECH 17><ACT 1><SCENE 2><12%>
	Tell us the manner of it, gentle Casca.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 1><SCENE 2><13%>
	'Tis very like: he hath the falling-sickness.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 1><SCENE 2><13%>
	What said he, when he came unto himself?
<SPEECH 20><ACT 1><SCENE 2><14%>
	And after that he came, thus sad, away?
<SPEECH 21><ACT 1><SCENE 2><15%>
	What a blunt fellow is this grown to be!
	He was quick mettle when he went to school.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 1><SCENE 2><15%>
	And so it is. For this time I will leave you:
	To-morrow, if you please to speak with me,
	I will come home to you; or, if you will,
	Come home to me, and I will wait for you.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 1><22%>
	What, Lucius! ho!
	I cannot, by the progress of the stars,
	Give guess how near to day. Lucius, I say!
	I would it were my fault to sleep so soundly.
	When, Lucius, when! Awake, I say! what, Lucius!
<SPEECH 24><ACT 2><SCENE 1><22%>
	Get me a taper in my study, Lucius:
	When it is lighted, come and call me here.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	It must be by his death: and, for my part,
	I know no personal cause to spurn at him,
	But for the general. He would be crown'd:
	How that might change his nature, there's the question:
	It is the bright day that brings forth the adder;
	And that craves wary walking. Crown him?—that!
	And then, I grant, we put a sting in him,
	That at his will he may do danger with.
	The abuse of greatness is when it disjoins
	Remorse from power; and, to speak truth of Cæsar,
	I have not known when his affections sway'd
	More than his reason. But 'tis a common proof,
	That lowliness is young ambition's ladder,
	Whereto the climber-upward turns his face;
	But when he once attains the upmost round,
	He then unto the ladder turns his back,
	Looks in the clouds, scorning the base degrees
	By which he did ascend. So Cæsar may:
	Then, lest he may, prevent. And, since the quarrel
	Will bear no colour for the thing he is,
	Fashion it thus; that what he is, augmented,
	Would run to these and these extremities;
	And therefore think him as a serpent's egg
	Which, hatch'd, would, as his kind, grow mischievous,
	And kill him in the shell.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	Get you to bed again; it is not day.
	Is not to-morrow, boy, the ides of March?
<SPEECH 27><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	Look in the calendar, and bring me word.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	The exhalations whizzing in the air
	Give so much light that I may read by them.
	Brutus, thou sleep'st: awake and see thyself.
	Shall Rome, &c. Speak, strike, redress!
	Brutus, thou sleep'st: awake!
	Such instigations have been often dropp'd
	Where I have took them up.
	'Shall Rome, &c.' Thus must I piece it out:
	Shall Rome stand under one man's awe? What, Rome?
	My ancestors did from the streets of Rome
	The Tarquin drive, when he was call'd a king.
	'Speak, strike, redress!' Am I entreated
	To speak, and strike? O Rome! I make thee promise;
	If the redress will follow, thou receiv'st
	Thy full petition at the hand of Brutus!
<SPEECH 29><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	'Tis good. Go to the gate: somebody knocks.
	Since Cassius first did whet me against Cæsar,
	I have not slept.
	Between the acting of a dreadful thing
	And the first motion, all the interim is
	Like a phantasma, or a hideous dream:
	The genius and the mortal instruments
	Are then in council; and the state of man,
	Like to a little kingdom, suffers then
	The nature of an insurrection.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	Is he alone?
<SPEECH 31><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	Do you know them?
<SPEECH 32><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	Let 'em enter.
	They are the faction. O conspiracy!
	Sham'st thou to show thy dangerous brow by night,
	When evils are most free? O! then by day
	Where wilt thou find a cavern dark enough
	To mask thy monstrous visage? Seek none, conspiracy;
	Hide it in smiles and affability:
	For if thou path, thy native semblance on,
	Not Erebus itself were dim enough
	To hide thee from prevention.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	I have been up this hour, awake all night.
	Know I these men that come along with you?
<SPEECH 34><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	He is welcome hither.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	He is welcome too.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	They are all welcome.
	What watchful cares do interpose themselves
	Betwixt your eyes and night?
<SPEECH 37><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	Here lies the east: doth not the day break here?
<SPEECH 38><ACT 2><SCENE 1><27%>
	Give me your hands all over, one by one.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 2><SCENE 1><27%>
	No, not an oath: if not the face of men,
	The sufferance of our souls, the time's abuse,
	If these be motives weak, break off betimes,
	And every man hence to his idle bed;
	So let high-sighted tyranny range on,
	Till each man-drop by lottery. But if these,
	As I am sure they do, bear fire enough
	To kindle cowards and to steel with valour
	The melting spirits of women, then, countrymen,
	What need we any spur but our own cause
	To prick us to redress? what other bond
	Than secret Romans, that have spoke the word
	And will not palter? and what other oath
	Than honesty to honesty engag'd,
	That this shall be, or we will fall for it?
	Swear priests and cowards and men cautelous,
	Old feeble carrions and such suffering souls
	That welcome wrongs; unto bad causes swear
	Such creatures as men doubt; but do not stain
	The even virtue of our enterprise,
	Nor th' insuppressive mettle of our spirits,
	To think that or our cause or our performance
	Did need an oath; when every drop of blood
	That every Roman bears, and nobly bears,
	Is guilty of a several bastardy,
	If he do break the smallest particle
	Of any promise that hath pass'd from him.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 2><SCENE 1><28%>
	O! name him not: let us not break with him;
	For he will never follow any thing
	That other men begin.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 2><SCENE 1><28%>
	Shall no man else be touch'd but only Cæsar?
<SPEECH 42><ACT 2><SCENE 1><29%>
	Our course will seem too bloody, Caius Cassius,
	To cut the head off and then hack the limbs,
	Like wrath in death and envy afterwards;
	For Antony is but a limb of Cæsar.
	Let us be sacrificers, but not butchers, Caius.
	We all stand up against the spirit of Cæsar;
	And in the spirit of men there is no blood:
	O! then that we could come by Cæsar's spirit,
	And not dismember Cæsar. But, alas!
	Cæsar must bleed for it. And, gentle friends,
	Let's kill him boldly, but not wrathfully;
	Let's carve him as a dish fit for the gods,
	Not hew him as a carcass fit for hounds:
	And let our hearts, as subtle masters do,
	Stir up their servants to an act of rage,
	And after seem to chide 'em. This shall make
	Our purpose necessary and not envious;
	Which so appearing to the common eyes,
	We shall be call'd purgers, not murderers.
	And, for Mark Antony, think not of him;
	For he can do no more than Cæsar's arm
	When Cæsar's head is off.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 2><SCENE 1><29%>
	Alas! good Cassius, do not think of him:
	If he love Cæsar, all that he can do
	Is to himself, take thought and die for Cæsar:
	And that were much he should; for he is given
	To sports, to wildness, and much company.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 2><SCENE 1><30%>
	Peace! count the clock.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 2><SCENE 1><30%>
	Never fear that: if he be so resolv'd,
	I can o'ersway him; for he loves to hear
	That unicorns may be betray'd with trees,
	And bears with glasses, elephants with holes,
	Lions with toils, and men with flatterers;
	But when I tell him he hates flatterers,
	He says he does, being then most flattered.
	Let me work;
	For I can give his humour the true bent,
	And I will bring him to the Capitol.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 2><SCENE 1><30%>
	By the eighth hour: is that the uttermost?
<SPEECH 47><ACT 2><SCENE 1><31%>
	Now, good Metellus, go along by him:
	He loves me well, and I have given him reasons;
	Send him but hither, and I'll fashion him.
<SPEECH 48><ACT 2><SCENE 1><31%>
	Good gentlemen, look fresh and merrily;
	Let not our looks put on our purposes,
	But bear it as our Roman actors do,
	With untir'd spirits and formal constancy:
	And so good morrow to you every one.
	Boy! Lucius! Fast asleep? It is no matter;
	Enjoy the honey-heavy dew of slumber:
	Thou hast no figures nor no fantasies
	Which busy care draws in the brains of men;
	Therefore thou sleep'st so sound.
<SPEECH 49><ACT 2><SCENE 1><31%>
	Portia, what mean you? Wherefore rise you now?
	It is not for your health thus to commit
	Your weak condition to the raw cold morning.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 2><SCENE 1><32%>
	I am not well in health, and that is all.
<SPEECH 51><ACT 2><SCENE 1><32%>
	Why, so I do. Good Portia, go to bed.
<SPEECH 52><ACT 2><SCENE 1><33%>
	Kneel not, gentle Portia.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 2><SCENE 1><33%>
	You are my true and honourable wife,
	As dear to me as are the ruddy drops
	That visit my sad heart.
<SPEECH 54><ACT 2><SCENE 1><34%>
	O ye gods!
	Render me worthy of this noble wife.
	Hark, hark! one knocks. Portia, go in awhile;
	And by and by thy bosom shall partake
	The secrets of my heart.
	All my engagements I will construe to thee,
	All the charactery of my sad brows.
	Leave me with haste.
	Lucius, who's that knocks?
<SPEECH 55><ACT 2><SCENE 1><34%>
	Caius Ligarius, that Metellus spoke of.
	Boy, stand aside. Caius Ligarius! how?
<SPEECH 56><ACT 2><SCENE 1><34%>
	O! what a time have you chose out, brave Caius,
	To wear a kerchief. Would you were not sick.
<SPEECH 57><ACT 2><SCENE 1><35%>
	Such an exploit have I in hand, Ligarius,
	Had you a healthful ear to hear of it.
<SPEECH 58><ACT 2><SCENE 1><35%>
	A piece of work that will make sick men whole.
<SPEECH 59><ACT 2><SCENE 1><35%>
	That must we also. What it is, my Caius,
	I shall unfold to thee as we are going
	To whom it must be done.
<SPEECH 60><ACT 2><SCENE 1><35%>
	Follow me then.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 2><SCENE 2><38%>
	Cæsar, all hail! Good morrow, worthy Cæsar:
	I come to fetch you to the senate-house.
<SPEECH 62><ACT 2><SCENE 2><38%>
	Most mighty Cæsar, let me know some cause,
	Lest I be laugh'd at when I tell them so.
<SPEECH 63><ACT 2><SCENE 2><39%>
	This dream is all amiss interpreted;
	It was a vision fair and fortunate:
	Your statue spouting blood in many pipes,
	In which so many smiling Romans bath'd,
	Signifies that from you great Rome shall suck
	Reviving blood, and that great men shall press
	For tinctures, stains, relics, and cognizance.
	This by Calphurnia's dream is signified.
<SPEECH 64><ACT 2><SCENE 2><39%>
	I have, when you have heard what I can say:
	And know it now: the senate have concluded
	To give this day a crown to mighty Cæsar.
	If you shall send them word you will not come,
	Their minds may change. Besides, it were a mock
	Apt to be render'd, for some one to say
	'Break up the senate till another time,
	When Cæsar's wife shall meet with better dreams.'
	If Cæsar hide himself, shall they not whisper
	'Lo! Cæsar is afraid?'
	Pardon me, Cæsar; for my dear dear love
	To your proceeding bids me tell you this,
	And reason to my love is liable.
<SPEECH 65><ACT 2><SCENE 2><40%>
	Cæsar, 'tis strucken eight.
<SPEECH 66><ACT 2><SCENE 2><40%>
	</STAGE DIR> That every like is not the same, O Cæsar!
	The heart of Brutus yearns to think upon.
<SPEECH 67><ACT 3><SCENE 1><44%>
	Trebonius doth desire you to o'er-read,
	At your best leisure, this his humble suit.
<SPEECH 68><ACT 3><SCENE 1><44%>
	What said Popilius Lena?
<SPEECH 69><ACT 3><SCENE 1><44%>
	Look, how he makes to Cæsar: mark him.
<SPEECH 70><ACT 3><SCENE 1><45%>
	Cassius, be constant:
	Popilius Lena speaks not of our purposes;
	For, look, he smiles, and Cæsar doth not change.
<SPEECH 71><ACT 3><SCENE 1><45%>
	Where is Metellus Cimber? Let him go,
	And presently prefer his suit to Cæsar.
<SPEECH 72><ACT 3><SCENE 1><45%>
	He is address'd; press near and second him.
<SPEECH 73><ACT 3><SCENE 1><46%>
	I kiss thy hand, but not in flattery, Cæsar;
	Desiring thee, that Publius Cimber may
	Have an immediate freedom of repeal.
<SPEECH 74><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	Great Cæsar,—
<SPEECH 75><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	People and senators be not affrighted;
	Fly not; stand still; ambition's debt is paid.
<SPEECH 76><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	And Cassius too.
<SPEECH 77><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	Where's Publius?
<SPEECH 78><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	Talk not of standing. Publius, good cheer;
	There is no harm intended to your person,
	Nor to no Roman else; so tell them, Publius.
<SPEECH 79><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	Do so; and let no man abide this deed
	But we the doers.
<SPEECH 80><ACT 3><SCENE 1><48%>
	Fates, we will know your pleasures.
	That we shall die, we know; 'tis but the time
	And drawing days out, that men stand upon.
<SPEECH 81><ACT 3><SCENE 1><48%>
	Grant that, and then is death a benefit:
	So are we Cæsar's friends, that have abridg'd
	His time of fearing death. Stoop, Romans, stoop,
	And let us bathe our hands in Cæsar's blood
	Up to the elbows, and besmear our swords:
	Then walk we forth, even to the market-place;
	And waving our red weapons o'er our heads,
	Let's all cry, 'Peace, freedom, and liberty!'
<SPEECH 82><ACT 3><SCENE 1><48%>
	How many times shall Cæsar bleed in sport,
	That now on Pompey's basis lies along
	No worthier than the dust!
<SPEECH 83><ACT 3><SCENE 1><48%>
	What! shall we forth?
<SPEECH 84><ACT 3><SCENE 1><49%>
	Soft! who comes here? A friend of Antony's.
<SPEECH 85><ACT 3><SCENE 1><49%>
	Thy master is a wise and valiant Roman;
	I never thought him worse.
	Tell him, so please him come unto this place,
	He shall be satisfied; and, by my honour,
	Depart untouch'd.
<SPEECH 86><ACT 3><SCENE 1><49%>
	I know that we shall have him well to friend.
<SPEECH 87><ACT 3><SCENE 1><50%>
	But here comes Antony. Welcome, Mark Antony.
<SPEECH 88><ACT 3><SCENE 1><50%>
	O Antony! beg not your death of us.
	Though now we must appear bloody and cruel,
	As, by our hands and this our present act,
	You see we do, yet see you but our hands
	And this the bleeding business they have done:
	Our hearts you see not; they are pitiful;
	And pity to the general wrong of Rome—
	As fire drives out fire, so pity pity—
	Hath done this deed on Cæsar. For your part,
	To you our swords have leaden points, Mark Antony;
	Our arms, in strength of malice, and our hearts
	Of brothers' temper, do receive you in
	With all kind love, good thoughts, and reverence.
<SPEECH 89><ACT 3><SCENE 1><51%>
	Only be patient till we have appeas'd
	The multitude, beside themselves with fear,
	And then we will deliver you the cause
	Why I, that did love Cæsar when I struck him,
	Have thus proceeded.
<SPEECH 90><ACT 3><SCENE 1><52%>
	Or else were this a savage spectacle.
	Our reasons are so full of good regard
	That were you, Antony, the son of Cæsar,
	You should be satisfied.
<SPEECH 91><ACT 3><SCENE 1><53%>
	You shall, Mark Antony.
<SPEECH 92><ACT 3><SCENE 1><53%>
	By your pardon;
	I will myself into the pulpit first,
	And show the reason of our Cæsar's death:
	What Antony shall speak, I will protest
	He speaks by leave and by permission,
	And that we are contented Cæsar shall
	Have all true rites and lawful ceremonies.
	It shall advantage more than do us wrong.
<SPEECH 93><ACT 3><SCENE 1><53%>
	Mark Antony, here, take you Cæsar's body.
	You shall not in your funeral speech blame us,
	But speak all good you can devise of Cæsar,
	And say you do 't by our permission;
	Else shall you not have any hand at all
	About his funeral; and you shall speak
	In the same pulpit whereto I am going,
	After my speech is ended.
<SPEECH 94><ACT 3><SCENE 1><53%>
	Prepare the body then, and follow us.
<SPEECH 95><ACT 3><SCENE 2><55%>
	Then follow me, and give me audience, friends.
	Cassius, go you into the other street,
	And part the numbers.
	Those that will hear me speak, let 'em stay here;
	Those that will follow Cassius, go with him;
	And public reasons shall be rendered
	Of Cæsar's death.
<SPEECH 96><ACT 3><SCENE 2><56%>
	Be patient till the last.
	Romans, countrymen, and lovers! hear me for my cause; and be silent, that you may hear: believe me for mine honour, and have respect to mine honour, that you may believe: censure me in your wisdom, and awake your senses, that you may the better judge. If there be any in this assembly, any dear friend of Cæsar's, to him I say, that Brutus' love to Cæsar was no less than his. If then that friend demand why Brutus rose against Cæsar, this is my answer: Not that I loved Cæsar less, but that I loved Rome more. Had you rather Cæsar were living, and die all slaves, than that Cæsar were dead, to live all free men? As Cæsar loved me, I weep for him; as he was fortunate, I rejoice at it; as he was valiant, I honour him; but, as he was ambitious, I slew him. There is tears for his love; joy for his fortune; honour for his valour; and death for his ambition. Who is here so base that would be a bondman? If any, speak; for him have I offended. Who is here so rude that would not be a Roman? If any, speak; for him have I offended. Who is here so vile that will not love his country? If any, speak; for him have I offended. I pause for a reply.
<SPEECH 97><ACT 3><SCENE 2><57%>
	Then none have I offended. I have done no more to Cæsar, than you shall do to Brutus. The question of his death is enrolled in the Capitol; his glory not extenuated, wherein he was worthy, nor his offences enforced, for which he suffered death.
	Here comes his body, mourned by Mark Antony: who, though he had no hand in his death, shall receive the benefit of his dying, a place in the commonwealth; as which of you shall not? With this I depart: that, as I slew my best lover for the good of Rome, I have the same dagger for myself, when it shall please my country to need my death.
<SPEECH 98><ACT 3><SCENE 2><58%>
	My countrymen,—
<SPEECH 99><ACT 3><SCENE 2><58%>
	Good countrymen, let me depart alone,
	And, for my sake, stay here with Antony.
	Do grace to Cæsar's corpse, and grace his speech
	Tending to Cæsar's glories, which Mark Antony,
	By our permission, is allow'd to make.
	I do entreat you, not a man depart,
	Save I alone, till Antony have spoke.
<SPEECH 100><ACT 4><SCENE 2><70%>
	Stand, ho!
<SPEECH 101><ACT 4><SCENE 2><70%>
	What now, Lucilius! is Cassius near?
<SPEECH 102><ACT 4><SCENE 2><70%>
	He greets me well. Your master, Pindarus,
	In his own change, or by ill officers,
	Hath given me some worthy cause to wish
	Things done, undone; but, if he be at hand,
	I shall be satisfied.
<SPEECH 103><ACT 4><SCENE 2><70%>
	He is not doubted. A word, Lucilius;
	How he receiv'd you, let me be resolv'd.
<SPEECH 104><ACT 4><SCENE 2><70%>
	Thou hast describ'd
	A hot friend cooling. Ever note, Lucilius,
	When love begins to sicken and decay,
	It useth an enforced ceremony.
	There are no tricks in plain and simple faith;
	But hollow men, like horses hot at hand,
	Make gallant show and promise of their mettle;
	But when they should endure the bloody spur,
	They fall their crests, and, like deceitful jades,
	Sink in the trial. Comes his army on?
<SPEECH 105><ACT 4><SCENE 2><71%>
	Hark! he is arriv'd.
	March gently on to meet him.
<SPEECH 106><ACT 4><SCENE 2><71%>
	Stand, ho! Speak the word along.
<SPEECH 107><ACT 4><SCENE 2><71%>
	Judge me, you gods! Wrong I mine enemies?
	And, if not so, how should I wrong a brother?
<SPEECH 108><ACT 4><SCENE 2><71%>
	Cassius, be content;
	Speak your griefs softly: I do know you well.
	Before the eyes of both our armies here,
	Which should perceive nothing but love from us,
	Let us not wrangle: bid them move away;
	Then in my tent, Cassius, enlarge your griefs,
	And I will give you audience.
<SPEECH 109><ACT 4><SCENE 2><72%>
	Lucilius, do you the like; and let no man
	Come to our tent till we have done our conference.
	Let Lucius and Titinius guard our door.
<SPEECH 110><ACT 4><SCENE 3><72%>
	You wrong'd yourself to write in such a case.
<SPEECH 111><ACT 4><SCENE 3><72%>
	Let me tell you, Cassius, you yourself
	Are much condemn'd to have an itching palm;
	To sell and mart your offices for gold
	To undeservera.
<SPEECH 112><ACT 4><SCENE 3><72%>
	The name of Cassius honours this corruption,
	And chastisement doth therefore hide his head.
<SPEECH 113><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	Remember March, the ides of March remember:
	Did not great Julius bleed for justice' sake?
	What villain touch'd his body, that did stab,
	And not for justice? What! shall one of us,
	That struck the foremost man of all this world
	But for supporting robbers, shall we now
	Contaminate our fingers with base bribes,
	And sell the mighty space of our large honours
	For so much trash as may be grasped thus?
	I had rather be a dog, and bay the moon,
	Than such a Roman.
<SPEECH 114><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	Go to; you are not, Cassius.
<SPEECH 115><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	I say you are not.
<SPEECH 116><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	Away, slight man!
<SPEECH 117><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	Hear me, for I will speak.
	Must I give way and room to your rash choler?
	Shall I be frighted when a madman stares?
<SPEECH 118><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	All this! ay, more: fret till your proud heart break;
	Go show your slaves how choleric you are,
	And make your bondmen tremble. Must I budge?
	Must I observe you? Must I stand and crouch
	Under your testy humour? By the gods,
	You shall digest the venom of your spleen,
	Though it do split you; for, from this day forth,
	I'll use you for my mirth, yea, for my laughter,
	When you are waspish.
<SPEECH 119><ACT 4><SCENE 3><74%>
	You say you are a better soldier:
	Let it appear so; make your vaunting true,
	And it shall please me well. For mine own part,
	I shall be glad to learn of noble men.
<SPEECH 120><ACT 4><SCENE 3><74%>
	If you did, I care not.
<SPEECH 121><ACT 4><SCENE 3><74%>
	Peace, peace! you durst not so have tempted him.
<SPEECH 122><ACT 4><SCENE 3><74%>
	No.
<SPEECH 123><ACT 4><SCENE 3><74%>
	For your life you durst not.
<SPEECH 124><ACT 4><SCENE 3><74%>
	You have done that you should be sorry for.
	There is no terror, Cassius, in your threats;
	For I am arm'd so strong in honesty
	That they pass by me as the idle wind,
	Which I respect not. I did send to you
	For certain sums of gold, which you denied me;
	For I can raise no money by vile means:
	By heaven, I had rather coin my heart,
	And drop my blood for drachmas, than to wring
	From the hard hands of peasants their vile trash
	By any indirection. I did send
	To you for gold to pay my legions,
	Which you denied me: was that done like Cassius?
	Should I have answer'd Caius Cassius so?
	When Marcus Brutus grows so covetous,
	To lock such rascal counters from his friends,
	Be ready, gods, with all your thunderbolts;
	Dash him to pieces!
<SPEECH 125><ACT 4><SCENE 3><75%>
	You did.
<SPEECH 126><ACT 4><SCENE 3><75%>
	I do not, till you practise them on me.
<SPEECH 127><ACT 4><SCENE 3><75%>
	I do not like your faults.
<SPEECH 128><ACT 4><SCENE 3><75%>
	A flatterer's would not, though they do appear
	As huge as high Olympus.
<SPEECH 129><ACT 4><SCENE 3><76%>
	Sheathe your dagger:
	Be angry when you will, it shall have scope;
	Do what you will, dishonour shall be humour.
	O Cassius! you are yoked with a lamb
	That carries anger as the flint bears fire,
	Who, much enforced, shows a hasty spark,
	And straight is cold again.
<SPEECH 130><ACT 4><SCENE 3><76%>
	When I spoke that I was ill-temper'd too.
<SPEECH 131><ACT 4><SCENE 3><76%>
	And my heart too.
<SPEECH 132><ACT 4><SCENE 3><76%>
	What's the matter?
<SPEECH 133><ACT 4><SCENE 3><76%>
	Yes, Cassius; and from henceforth
	When you are over-earnest with your Brutus,
	He'll think your mother chides, and leave you so.
<SPEECH 134><ACT 4><SCENE 3><77%>
	Get you hence, sirrah; saucy fellow, hence!
<SPEECH 135><ACT 4><SCENE 3><77%>
	I'll know his humour, when he knows his time:
	What should the wars do with these jigging fools?
	Companion, hence!
<SPEECH 136><ACT 4><SCENE 3><77%>
	Lucilius and Titinius, bid the commanders
	Prepare to lodge their companies to-night.
<SPEECH 137><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	Lucius, a bowl of wine!
<SPEECH 138><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	O Cassius! I am sick of many griefs.
<SPEECH 139><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	No man bears sorrow better: Portia is dead.
<SPEECH 140><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	She is dead.
<SPEECH 141><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	Impatient of my absence,
	And grief that young Octavius with Mark Antony
	Have made themselves so strong;—for with her death
	That tidings came:—with this she fell distract,
	And, her attendants absent, swallow'd fire.
<SPEECH 142><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	Even so.
<SPEECH 143><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	Speak no more of her. Give me a bowl of wine.
	In this I bury all unkindness, Cassius.
<SPEECH 144><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	Come in, Titinius.
	Welcome, good Messala.
	Now sit we close about this taper here,
	And call in question our necessities.
<SPEECH 145><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	No more, I pray you.
	Messala, I have here received letters,
	That young Octavius and Mark Antony
	Come down upon us with a mighty power,
	Bending their expedition towards Philippi.
<SPEECH 146><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	With what addition?
<SPEECH 147><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	Therein our letters do not well agree;
	Mine speak of seventy senators that died
	By their proscriptions, Cicero being one.
<SPEECH 148><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	No, Messala.
<SPEECH 149><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	Nothing, Messala.
<SPEECH 150><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	Why ask you? Hear you aught of her in yours?
<SPEECH 151><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	Now, as you are a Roman, tell me true.
<SPEECH 152><ACT 4><SCENE 3><80%>
	Why, farewell, Portia. We must die, Messala:
	With meditating that she must die once,
	I have the patience to endure it now.
<SPEECH 153><ACT 4><SCENE 3><80%>
	Well, to our work alive. What do you think
	Of marching to Philippi presently?
<SPEECH 154><ACT 4><SCENE 3><80%>
	Your reason?
<SPEECH 155><ACT 4><SCENE 3><80%>
	Good reasons must, of force, give place to better,
	The people 'twixt Philippi and this ground
	Do stand but in a forc'd affection;
	For they have grudg'd us contribution:
	The enemy, marching along by them,
	By them shall make a fuller number up,
	Come on refresh'd, new-added, and encourag'd;
	From which advantage shall we cut him off,
	If at Philippi we do face him there,
	These people at our back.
<SPEECH 156><ACT 4><SCENE 3><81%>
	Under your pardon. You must note beside,
	That we have tried the utmost of our friends,
	Our legions are brim-full, our cause is ripe:
	The enemy increaseth every day;
	We, at the height, are ready to decline.
	There is a tide in the affairs of men,
	Which, taken at the flood, leads on to fortune;
	Omitted, all the voyage of their life
	Is bound in shallows and in miseries.
	On such a full sea are we now afloat;
	And we must take the current when it serves,
	Or lose our ventures.
<SPEECH 157><ACT 4><SCENE 3><81%>
	The deep of night is crept upon our talk,
	And nature must obey necessity,
	Which we will niggard with a little rest.
	There is no more to say?
<SPEECH 158><ACT 4><SCENE 3><81%>
	Lucius!
	My gown.
	Farewell, good Messala:
	Good-night, Titinius. Noble, noble Cassius,
	Good-night, and good repose.
<SPEECH 159><ACT 4><SCENE 3><81%>
	Every thing is well.
<SPEECH 160><ACT 4><SCENE 3><82%>
	Good-night, good brother.
<SPEECH 161><ACT 4><SCENE 3><82%>
	Farewell, every one.
	Give me the gown. Where is thy instrument?
<SPEECH 162><ACT 4><SCENE 3><82%>
	What! thou speak'st drowsily?
	Poor knave, I blame thee not; thou art o'erwatch'd.
	Call Claudius and some other of my men;
	I'll have them sleep on cushions in my tent.
<SPEECH 163><ACT 4><SCENE 3><82%>
	I pray you, sirs, lie in my tent and sleep:
	It may be I shall raise you by and by
	On business to my brother Cassius.
<SPEECH 164><ACT 4><SCENE 3><82%>
	I will not have it so; lie down, good sirs;
	It may be I shall otherwise bethink me.
	Look, Lucius, here's the book I sought for so;
	I put it in the pocket of my gown.
<SPEECH 165><ACT 4><SCENE 3><82%>
	Bear with me, good boy, I am much forgetful.
	Canst thou hold up thy heavy eyes awhile,
	And touch thy instrument a strain or two?
<SPEECH 166><ACT 4><SCENE 3><83%>
	It does, my boy:
	I trouble thee too much, but thou art willing.
<SPEECH 167><ACT 4><SCENE 3><83%>
	I should not urge thy duty past thy might;
	I know young bloods look for a time of rest.
<SPEECH 168><ACT 4><SCENE 3><83%>
	It was well done, and thou shalt sleep again;
	I will not hold thee long: if I do live,
	I will be good to thee.
	This is a sleepy tune: O murderous slumber!
	Lay'st thou thy leaden mace upon my boy,
	That plays thee music? Gentle knave, good-night;
	I will not do thee so much wrong to wake thee.
	If thou dost nod, thou break'st thy instrument;
	I'll take it from thee; and, good boy, good-night.
	Let me see, let me see; is not the leaf turn'd down
	Where I left reading? Here it is, I think.
	How ill this taper burns! Ha! who comes here?
	I think it is the weakness of mine eyes
	That shapes this monstrous apparition.
	It comes upon me. Art thou any thing?
	Art thou some god, some angel, or some devil,
	That mak'st my blood cold and my hair to stare?
	Speak to me what thou art.
<SPEECH 169><ACT 4><SCENE 3><84%>
	Why com'st thou?
<SPEECH 170><ACT 4><SCENE 3><84%>
	Well; then I shall see thee again?
<SPEECH 171><ACT 4><SCENE 3><84%>
	Why, I will see thee at Philippi then.
	Now I have taken heart thou vanishest:
	Ill spirit, I would hold more talk with thee.
	Boy, Lucius! Varro! Claudius! Sirs, awake!
	Claudius!
<SPEECH 172><ACT 4><SCENE 3><84%>
	He thinks he still is at his instrument.
	Lucius, awake!
<SPEECH 173><ACT 4><SCENE 3><84%>
	Didst thou dream, Lucius, that thou so criedst out?
<SPEECH 174><ACT 4><SCENE 3><84%>
	Yes, that thou didst. Didst thou see any thing?
<SPEECH 175><ACT 4><SCENE 3><84%>
	Sleep again, Lucius. Sirrah, Claudius!
	Fellow thou! awake!
<SPEECH 176><ACT 4><SCENE 3><84%>
	Why did you so cry out, sirs, in your sleep?
<SPEECH 177><ACT 4><SCENE 3><84%>
	Ay: saw you any thing?
<SPEECH 178><ACT 4><SCENE 3><84%>
	Go, and commend me to my brother Cassius.
	Bid him set on his powers betimes before,
	And we will follow.
<SPEECH 179><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	They stand, and would have parley.
<SPEECH 180><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	Words before blows: is it so, countrymen?
<SPEECH 181><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	Good words are better than bad strokes, Octavius.
<SPEECH 182><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	O! yes, and soundless too;
	For you have stol'n their buzzing, Antony,
	And very wisely threat before you sting.
<SPEECH 183><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Cæsar, thou canst not die by traitors' hands,
	Unless thou bring'st them with thee.
<SPEECH 184><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	O! if thou wert the noblest of thy strain,
	Young man, thou couldst not die more honourable.
<SPEECH 185><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	Ho!
	Lucilius! hark, a word with you.
<SPEECH 186><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	Even so, Lucilius.
<SPEECH 187><ACT 5><SCENE 1><89%>
	Even by the rule of that philosophy
	By which I did blame Cato for the death
	Which he did give himself; I know not how,
	But I do find it cowardly and vile,
	For fear of what might fall, so to prevent
	The time of life: arming myself with patience,
	To stay the providence of some high powers
	That govern us below.
<SPEECH 188><ACT 5><SCENE 1><89%>
	No, Cassius, no: think not, thou noble Roman,
	That ever Brutus will go bound to Rome;
	He bears too great a mind: but this same day
	Must end that work the ides of March begun;
	And whether we shall meet again I know not.
	Therefore our everlasting farewell take:
	For ever, and for ever, farewell, Cassius!
	If we do meet again, why, we shall smile;
	If not, why then, this parting was well made.
<SPEECH 189><ACT 5><SCENE 1><90%>
	Why, then, lead on. O! that a man might know
	The end of this day's business, ere it come;
	But it sufficeth that the day will end,
	And then the end is known. Come, ho! away!
<SPEECH 190><ACT 5><SCENE 2><90%>
	Ride, ride, Messala, ride, and give these bills
	Unto the legions on the other side.
	Let them set on at once, for I perceive
	But cold demeanour in Octavius' wing,
	And sudden push gives them the overthrow.
	Ride, ride, Messala: let them all come down.
<SPEECH 191><ACT 5><SCENE 3><94%>
	Where, where, Messala, doth his body lie?
<SPEECH 192><ACT 5><SCENE 3><94%>
	Titinius' face is upward.
<SPEECH 193><ACT 5><SCENE 3><94%>
	O Julius Cæsar! thou art mighty yet!
	Thy spirit walks abroad, and turns our swords
	In our own proper entrails.
<SPEECH 194><ACT 5><SCENE 3><94%>
	Are yet two Romans living such as these?
	The last of all the Romans, fare thee well!
	It is impossible that ever Rome
	Should breed thy fellow. Friends, I owe more tears
	To this dead man than you shall see me pay.—
	I shall find time, Cassius, I shall find time.—
	Come therefore, and to Thassos send his body:
	His funerals shall not be in our camp,
	Lest it discomfort us. Lucilius, come;
	And come, young Cato;—let us to the field.
	Labeo and Flavius, set our battles on:—
	'Tis three o'clock; and, Romans, yet ere night
	We shall try fortune in a second fight.
<SPEECH 195><ACT 5><SCENE 4><95%>
	Yet, countrymen, O! yet hold up your heads!
<SPEECH 196><ACT 5><SCENE 4><95%>
	And I am Brutus, Marcus Brutus, I;
	Brutus, my country's friend; know me for Brutus!
<SPEECH 197><ACT 5><SCENE 5><97%>
	Come, poor remains of friends, rest on this rock.
<SPEECH 198><ACT 5><SCENE 5><97%>
	Sit thee down, Clitus: slaying is the word;
	It is a deed in fashion. Hark thee, Clitus.
<SPEECH 199><ACT 5><SCENE 5><97%>
	Peace, then! no words.
<SPEECH 200><ACT 5><SCENE 5><97%>
	Hark thee, Dardanius.
<SPEECH 201><ACT 5><SCENE 5><97%>
	Come hither, good Volumnius: list a word.
<SPEECH 202><ACT 5><SCENE 5><97%>
	Why this, Volumnius:
	The ghost of Cæsar hath appear'd to me
	Two several times by night; at Sardis once,
	And this last night here in Philippi fields.
	I know my hour is come.
<SPEECH 203><ACT 5><SCENE 5><97%>
	Nay, I am sure it is, Volumnius.
	Thou seest the world, Volumnius, how it goes;
	Our enemies have beat us to the pit:
	It is more worthy to leap in ourselves,
	Than tarry till they push us. Good Volumnius,
	Thou know'st that we two went to school together:
	Even for that our love of old, I prithee,
	Hold thou my sword-hilts, whilst I run on it.
<SPEECH 204><ACT 5><SCENE 5><98%>
	Farewell to you; and you; and you, Volumnius.
	Strato, thou hast been all this while asleep;
	Farewell to thee too, Strato. Countrymen,
	My heart doth joy that yet, in all my life,
	I found no man but he was true to me.
	I shall have glory by this losing day,
	More than Octavius and Mark Antony
	By this vile conquest shall attain unto.
	So fare you well at once; for Brutus' tongue
	Hath almost ended his life's history:
	Night hangs upon mine eyes; my bones would rest,
	That have but labour'd to attain this hour.
<SPEECH 205><ACT 5><SCENE 5><98%>
	Hence! I will follow.
	I prithee, Strato, stay thou by thy lord:
	Thou art a fellow of a good respect;
	Thy life hath had some smatch of honour in it:
	Hold then my sword, and turn away thy face,
	While I do run upon it. Wilt thou, Strato?
<SPEECH 206><ACT 5><SCENE 5><99%>
	Farewell, good Strato.—<STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> Cæsar, now be still;
	I kill'd not thee with half so good a will.
