<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 2><4%>
	Calphurnia!
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 2><4%>
	Calphurnia!
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 2><4%>
	Stand you directly in Antonius' way
	When he doth run his course. Antonius!
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 2><4%>
	Forget not, in your speed, Antonius,
	To touch Calphurnia; for our elders say,
	The barren, touched in this holy chase,
	Shake off their sterile curse.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 2><4%>
	Set on; and leave no ceremony out.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 2><4%>
	Ha! Who calls?
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 2><4%>
	Who is it in the press that calls on me?
	I hear a tongue, shriller than all the music,
	Cry 'Cæsar.' Speak; Cæsar is turn'd to hear.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 2><4%>
	What man is that?
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 2><4%>
	Set him before me; let me see his face.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 2><4%>
	What sayst thou to me now? Speak once again.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 2><5%>
	He is a dreamer; let us leave him: pass.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	Antonius!
<SPEECH 13><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	Let me have men about me that are fat;
	Sleek-headed men and such as sleep o' nights.
	Yond Cassius has a lean and hungry look;
	He thinks too much: such men are dangerous:
<SPEECH 14><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	Would he were fatter! but I fear him not:
	Yet if my name were liable to fear,
	I do not know the man I should avoid
	So soon as that spare Cassius. He reads much;
	He is a great observer, and he looks
	Quite through the deeds of men; he loves no plays,
	As thou dost, Antony; he hears no music;
	Seldom he smiles, and smiles in such a sort
	As if he mock'd himself, and scorn'd his spirit
	That could be mov'd to smile at any thing.
	Such men as he be never at heart's ease
	Whiles they behold a greater than themselves,
	And therefore are they very dangerous.
	I rather tell thee what is to be fear'd
	Than what I fear, for always I am Cæsar.
	Come on my right hand, for this ear is deaf,
	And tell me truly what thou think'st of him.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 2><35%>
	Nor heaven nor earth have been at peace to-night:
	Thrice hath Calphurnia in her sleep cried out,
	'Help, ho! They murder Cæsar!' Who's within?
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 2><36%>
	Go bid the priests do present sacrifice,
	And bring me their opinions of success.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 2><36%>
	Cæsar shall forth: the things that threaten'd me
	Ne'er look'd but on my back; when they shall see
	The face of Cæsar, they are vanished.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 2><36%>
	What can be avoided
	Whose end is purpos'd by the mighty gods?
	Yet Cæsar shall go forth; for these predictions
	Are to the world in general as to Cæsar.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 2><37%>
	Cowards die many times before their deaths;
	The valiant never taste of death but once.
	Of all the wonders that I yet have heard,
	It seems to me most strange that men should fear;
	Seeing that death, a necessary end,
	Will come when it will come.
	What say the augurers?
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 2><37%>
	The gods do this in shame of cowardice:
	Cæsar should be a beast without a heart
	If he should stay at home to-day for fear.
	No, Cæsar shall not; danger knows full well
	That Cæsar is more dangerous than he:
	We are two lions litter'd in one day,
	And I the elder and more terrible:
	And Cæsar shall go forth.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 2><37%>
	Mark Antony shall say I am not well;
	And, for thy humour, I will stay at home.
	Here's Decius Brutus, he shall tell them so.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 2><38%>
	And you are come in very happy time
	To bear my greeting to the senators,
	And tell them that I will not come to-day:
	Cannot, is false, and that I dare not, falser;
	I will not come to-day: tell them so, Decius.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 2><38%>
	Shall Cæsar send a lie?
	Have I in conquest stretch'd mine arm so far
	To be afeard to tell greybeards the truth?
	Decius, go tell them Cæsar will not come.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 2><SCENE 2><38%>
	The cause is in my will: I will not come;
	That is enough to satisfy the senate:
	But for your private satisfaction,
	Because I love you, I will let you know:
	Calphurnia here, my wife, stays me at home:
	She dreamt to-night she saw my statua,
	Which, like a fountain with a hundred spouts,
	Did run pure blood; and many lusty Romans
	Came smiling, and did bathe their hands in it:
	And these does she apply for warnings and portents,
	And evils imminent; and on her knee
	Hath begg'd that I will stay at home to-day.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 2><SCENE 2><39%>
	And this way have you well expounded it.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 2><SCENE 2><39%>
	How foolish do your fears seem now, Calphurnia!
	I am ashamed I did yield to them.
	Give me my robe, for I will go:
	And look where Publius is come to fetch me.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 2><SCENE 2><40%>
	Welcome, Publius.
	What! Brutus, are you stirr'd so early too?
	Good morrow, Casca. Caius Ligarius,
	Cæsar was ne'er so much your enemy
	As that same ague which hath made you lean.
	What is't o'clock?
<SPEECH 28><ACT 2><SCENE 2><40%>
	I thank you for your pains and courtesy.
	See! Antony, that revels long o' nights,
	Is notwithstanding up. Good morrow, Antony.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 2><SCENE 2><40%>
	Bid them prepare within:
	I am to blame to be thus waited for.
	Now, Cinna; now, Metellus; what, Trebonius!
	I have an hour's talk in store for you;
	Remember that you call on me to-day:
	Be near me, that I may remember you.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 2><SCENE 2><40%>
	Good friends, go in, and taste some wine with me;
	And we, like friends, will straightway go together.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 3><SCENE 1><44%>
	</STAGE DIR> The idea of March are come.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 3><SCENE 1><44%>
	What touches us ourself shall be last serv'd
<SPEECH 33><ACT 3><SCENE 1><44%>
	What! is the fellow mad?
<SPEECH 34><ACT 3><SCENE 1><44%>
	What! urge you your petitions in the street?
	Come to the Capitol.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 3><SCENE 1><45%>
	I must prevent thee, Cimber.
	These couchings and these lowly courtesies,
	Might fire the blood of ordinary men,
	And turn pre-ordinance and first decree
	Into the law of children. Be not fond,
	To think that Cæsar bears such rebel blood
	That will be thaw'd from the true quality
	With that which melteth fools; I mean sweet words,
	Low-crooked curtsies, and base spaniel fawning.
	Thy brother by decree is banished:
	If thou dost bend and pray and fawn for him,
	I spurn thee like a cur out of my way.
	Know, Cæsar doth not wrong, nor without cause
	Will he be satisfied.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 3><SCENE 1><46%>
	What, Brutus!
<SPEECH 37><ACT 3><SCENE 1><46%>
	I could be well mov'd if I were as you;
	If I could pray to move, prayers would move me;
	But I am constant as the northern star,
	Of whose true-fix'd and resting quality
	There is no fellow in the firmament.
	The skies are painted with unnumber'd sparks,
	They are all fire and every one doth shine,
	But there's but one in all doth hold his place:
	So, in the world; 'tis furnish'd well with men,
	And men are flesh and blood, and apprehensive;
	Yet in the number I do know but one
	That unassailable holds on his rank,
	Unshak'd of motion: and that I am he,
	Let me a little show it, even in this,
	That I was constant Cimber should be banish'd,
	And constant do remain to keep him so.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	Hence! Wilt thou lift up Olympus!
<SPEECH 39><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	Doth not Brutus bootless kneel?
<SPEECH 40><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	Et tu, Brute? Then fall, Cæsar!
