<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 2><1%>
	What bloody man is that? He can report,
	As seemeth by his plight, of the revolt
	The newest state.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 2><2%>
	O valiant cousin! worthy gentleman!
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 2><2%>
	Dismay'd not this
	Our captains, Macbeth and Banquo?
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 2><3%>
	So well thy words become thee as thy wounds;
	They smack of honour both. Go, get him surgeons.
	Who comes here?
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 2><3%>
	Whence cam'st thou, worthy thane?
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 2><4%>
	Great happiness!
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 2><4%>
	No more that Thane of Cawdor shall deceive
	Our bosom interest. Go pronounce his present death,
	And with his former title greet Macbeth.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 2><4%>
	What he hath lost noble Macbeth hath won.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 4><11%>
	Is execution done on Cawdor? Are not
	Those in commission yet return'd?
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 4><11%>
	There's no art
	To find the mind's construction in the face:
	He was a gentleman on whom I built
	An absolute trust.
	O worthiest cousin!
	The sin of my ingratitude even now
	Was heavy on me. Thou art so far before
	That swiftest wing of recompense is slow
	To overtake thee; would thou hadst less deserv'd,
	That the proportion both of thanks and payment
	Might have been mine! only I have left to say,
	More is thy due than more than all can pay.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 4><12%>
	Welcome hither:
	I have begun to plant thee, and will labour
	To make thee full of growing. Noble Banquo,
	That hast no less deserv'd, nor must be known
	No less to have done so, let me infold thee
	And hold thee to my heart.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 4><12%>
	My plenteous joys
	Wanton in fulness, seek to hide themselves
	In drops of sorrow. Sons, kinsmen, thanes,
	And you whose places are the nearest, know
	We will establish our estate upon
	Our eldest, Malcolm, whom we name hereafter
	The Prince of Cumberland; which honour must
	Not unaccompanied invest him only,
	But signs of nobleness, like stars, shall shine
	On all deservers. From hence to Inverness,
	And bind us further to you.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 1><SCENE 4><13%>
	My worthy Cawdor!
<SPEECH 14><ACT 1><SCENE 4><13%>
	True, worthy Banquo; he is full so valiant,
	And in his commendations I am fed;
	It is a banquet to me. Let's after him,
	Whose care is gone before to bid us welcome:
	It is a peerless kinsman.
	They met me in the day of success; and I have learned by the perfectest report, they have more in them than mortal knowledge. When I burned in desire to question them further, they made themselves air, into which they vanished. Whiles I stood rapt in the wonder of it, came missives from the king, who all-hailed me, 'Thane of Cawdor;' by which title, before, these weird sisters saluted me, and referred me to the coming on of time, with, 'Hail, king that shall be!' This have I thought good to deliver thee, my dearest partner of greatness, that thou mightest not lose the dues of rejoicing, by being ignorant of what greatness is promised thee. Lay it to thy heart, and farewell.
	Glamis thou art, and Cawdor; and shalt be
	What thou art promis'd. Yet do I fear thy nature;
	It is too full o' the milk of human kindness
	To catch the nearest way; thou wouldst be great,
	Art not without ambition, but without
	The illness should attend it; what thou wouldst highly,
	That thou wouldst holily; wouldst not play false,
	And yet wouldst wrongly win; thou'dst have, great Glamis,
	That which cries, 'Thus thou must do, if thou have it;'
	And that which rather thou dost fear to do
	Than wishest should be undone. Hie thee hither,
	That I may pour my spirits in thine ear,
	And chastise with the valour of my tongue
	All that impedes thee from the golden round,
	Which fate and metaphysical aid doth seem
	To have thee crown'd withal.
	What is your tidings?
<SPEECH 15><ACT 1><SCENE 6><17%>
	This castle hath a pleasant seat; the air
	Nimbly and sweetly recommends itself
	Unto our gentle senses.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 1><SCENE 6><18%>
	See, see, our honour'd hostess!
	The love that follows us sometime is our trouble,
	Which still we thank as love. Herein I teach you
	How you shall bid God 'eyld us for your pains,
	And thank us for your trouble.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 1><SCENE 6><18%>
	Where's the Thane of Cawdor?
	We cours'd him at the heels, and had a purpose
	To be his purveyor; but he rides well,
	And his great love, sharp as his spur, hath holp him
	To his home before us. Fair and noble hostess,
	We are your guest to-night.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 1><SCENE 6><19%>
	Give me your hand;
	Conduct me to mine host: we love him highly,
	And shall continue our graces towards him.
	By your leave, hostess.
