<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><1%>
	Friends to this ground.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><1%>
	A piece of him.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 1><1%>
	Tush, tush! 'twill not appear.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 1><1%>
	Well, sit we down,
	And let us hear Bernardo speak of this.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 1><1%>
	Most like: it harrows me with fear and wonder.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 1><2%>
	What art thou that usurp'st this time of night,
	Together with that fair and war-like form
	In which the majesty of buried Denmark
	Did sometimes march? by heaven I charge thee, speak!
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 1><2%>
	Stay! speak, speak! I charge thee, speak!
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 1><2%>
	Before my God, I might not this believe
	Without the sensible and true avouch
	Of mine own eyes.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 1><2%>
	As thou-art to thyself:
	Such was the very armour he had on
	When he the ambitious Norway combated;
	So frown'd he once, when, in an angry parle,
	He smote the sledded Polacks on the ice.
	'Tis strange.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 1><2%>
	In what particular thought to work I know not;
	But in the gross and scope of my opinion,
	This bodes some strange eruption to our state.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 1><2%>
	That can I;
	At least, the whisper goes so. Our last king,
	Whose image even but now appear'd to us,
	Was, as you know, by Fortinbras of Norway,
	Thereto prick'd on by a most emulate pride,
	Dar'd to the combat; in which our valiant Hamlet—
	For so this side of our known world esteem'd him—
	Did slay this Fortinbras; who, by a seal'd compact,
	Well ratified by law and heraldry,
	Did forfeit with his life all those his lands
	Which he stood seiz'd of, to the conqueror;
	Against the which, a moiety competent
	Was gaged by our king; which had return'd
	To the inheritance of Fortinbras,
	Had he been vanquisher; as, by the same covenant,
	And carriage of the article design'd,
	His fell to Hamlet. Now, sir, young Fortinbras,
	Of unimproved mettle hot and full,
	Hath in the skirts of Norway here and there
	Shark'd up a list of lawless resolutes,
	For food and diet, to some enterprise
	That hath a stomach in 't; which is no other—
	As it doth well appear unto our state—
	But to recover of us, by strong hand
	And terms compulsative, those foresaid lands
	So by his father lost. And this, I take it,
	Is the main motive of our preparations,
	The source of this our watch and the chief head
	Of this post-haste and romage in the land.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	A mote it is to trouble the mind's eye.
	In the most high and palmy state of Rome,
	A little ere the mightiest Julius fell,
	The graves stood tenantless and the sheeted dead
	Did squeak and gibber in the Roman streets;
	As stars with trains of fire and dews of blood,
	Disasters in the sun; and the moist star
	Upon whose influence Neptune's empire stands
	Was sick almost to doomsday with eclipse;
	And even the like precurse of fierce events,
	As harbingers preceding still the fates
	And prologue to the omen coming on,
	Have heaven and earth together demonstrated
	Unto our climatures and countrymen.
	But, soft! behold! lo! where it comes again.
	I'll cross it, though it blast me. Stay, illusion!
	If thou hast any sound, or use of voice,
	Speak to me:
	If there be any good thing to be done,
	That may to thee do ease and grace to me,
	Speak to me:
	If thou art privy to thy country's fate,
	Which happily foreknowing may avoid,
	O! speak;
	Or if thou hast uphoarded in thy life
	Extorted treasure in the womb of earth,
	For which, they say, you spirits oft walk in death,
	Speak of it: stay, and speak! Stop it, Marcellus.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	Do, if it will not stand.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	'Tis here!
<SPEECH 15><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	And then it started like a guilty thing
	Upon a fearful summons. I have heard,
	The cock, that is the trumpet to the morn,
	Doth with his lofty and shrill-sounding throat
	Awake the god of day; and at his warning,
	Whether in sea or fire, in earth or air,
	The extravagant and erring spirit hies
	To his confine; and of the truth herein
	This present object made probation.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	So have I heard and do in part believe it.
	But, look, the morn in russet mantle clad,
	Walks o'er the dew of yon high eastern hill;
	Break we our watch up; and by my advice
	Let us impart what we have seen to-night
	Unto young Hamlet; for, upon my life,
	This spirit, dumb to us, will speak to him.
	Do you consent we shall acquaint him with it,
	As needful in our loves, fitting our duty?
<SPEECH 17><ACT 1><SCENE 2><9%>
	Hail to your lordship!
<SPEECH 18><ACT 1><SCENE 2><9%>
	The same, my lord, and your poor servant ever.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 1><SCENE 2><9%>
	A truant disposition, good my lord.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 1><SCENE 2><9%>
	My lord, I came to see your father's funeral.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 1><SCENE 2><9%>
	Indeed, my lord, it follow'd hard upon.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 1><SCENE 2><9%>
	O! where, my lord?
<SPEECH 23><ACT 1><SCENE 2><9%>
	I saw him once; he was a goodly king.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 1><SCENE 2><10%>
	My lord, I think I saw him yesternight.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 1><SCENE 2><10%>
	My lord, the king your father.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 1><SCENE 2><10%>
	Season your admiration for a while
	With an attent ear, till I may deliver,
	Upon the witness of these gentlemen,
	This marvel to you.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 1><SCENE 2><10%>
	Two nights together had these gentlemen,
	Marcellus and Bernardo, on their watch,
	In the dead vast and middle of the night,
	Been thus encounter'd: a figure like your father,
	Armed at points exactly, cap-a-pe,
	Appears before them, and with solemn march
	Goes slow and stately by them: thrice he walk'd
	By their oppress'd and fear-surprised eyes,
	Within his truncheon's length; whilst they, distill'd
	Almost to jelly with the act of fear,
	Stand dumb and speak not to him. This to me
	In dreadful secrecy impart they did,
	And I with them the third night kept the watch;
	Where, as they had deliver'd, both in time,
	Form of the thing, each word made true and good,
	The apparition comes. I knew your father;
	These hands are not more like.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 1><SCENE 2><10%>
	My lord, I did;
	But answer made it none; yet once methought
	It lifted up its head and did address
	Itself to motion, like as it would speak;
	But even then the morning cock crew loud,
	And at the sound it shrunk in haste away
	And vanish'd from our sight.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 1><SCENE 2><10%>
	As I do live, my honour'd lord, 'tis true;
	And we did think it writ down in our duty
	To let you know of it.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	O yes! my lord; he wore his beaver up.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	A countenance more in sorrow than in anger.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	Nay, very pale.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	Most constantly.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	It would have much amaz'd you.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	While one with moderate haste might tell a hundred.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	Not when I saw it.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	It was, as I have seen it in his life,
	A sable silver'd.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	I warrant it will.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 1><SCENE 4><15%>
	It is a nipping and an eager air.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 1><SCENE 4><15%>
	I think it lacks of twelve.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 1><SCENE 4><15%>
	Indeed? I heard it not: then it draws near the season
	Wherein the spirit held his wont to walk.
	What does this mean, my lord?
<SPEECH 42><ACT 1><SCENE 4><15%>
	Is it a custom?
<SPEECH 43><ACT 1><SCENE 4><16%>
	Look, my lord, it comes.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 1><SCENE 4><16%>
	It beckons you to go away with it,
	As if it some impartment did desire
	To you alone.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 1><SCENE 4><16%>
	No, by no means.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 1><SCENE 4><17%>
	Do not, my lord.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 1><SCENE 4><17%>
	What if it tempt you toward the flood, my lord,
	Or to the dreadful summit of the cliff
	That beetles o'er his base into the sea,
	And there assume some other horrible form,
	Which might deprive your sovereignty of reason
	And draw you into madness? think of it;
	The very place puts toys of desperation,
	Without more motive, into every brain
	That looks so many fathoms to the sea
	And hears it roar beneath.
<SPEECH 48><ACT 1><SCENE 4><17%>
	Be rul'd; you shall not go.
<SPEECH 49><ACT 1><SCENE 4><17%>
	He wares desperate with imagination.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 1><SCENE 4><17%>
	Have after. To what issue will this come?
<SPEECH 51><ACT 1><SCENE 4><17%>
	Heaven will direct it.
<SPEECH 52><ACT 1><SCENE 5><20%>
	</STAGE DIR> My lord! my lord!
<SPEECH 53><ACT 1><SCENE 5><20%>
	</STAGE DIR> Heaven secure him!
<SPEECH 54><ACT 1><SCENE 5><20%>
	</STAGE DIR> Hillo, ho, ho, my lord!
<SPEECH 55><ACT 1><SCENE 5><20%>
	What news, my lord?
<SPEECH 56><ACT 1><SCENE 5><20%>
	Good my lord, tell it.
<SPEECH 57><ACT 1><SCENE 5><20%>
	Not I, my lord, by heaven!
<SPEECH 58><ACT 1><SCENE 5><20%>
	Ay, by heaven, my lord.
<SPEECH 59><ACT 1><SCENE 5><20%>
	There needs no ghost, my lord, come from the grave,
	To tell us this.
<SPEECH 60><ACT 1><SCENE 5><21%>
	These are but wild and whirling words, my lord.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 1><SCENE 5><21%>
	There's no offence, my lord.
<SPEECH 62><ACT 1><SCENE 5><21%>
	What is't, my lord? we will.
<SPEECH 63><ACT 1><SCENE 5><21%>
	My lord, we will not.
<SPEECH 64><ACT 1><SCENE 5><21%>
	In faith,
	My lord, not I.
<SPEECH 65><ACT 1><SCENE 5><21%>
	Propose the oath, my lord.
<SPEECH 66><ACT 1><SCENE 5><22%>
	O day and night, but this is wondrous strange!
<SPEECH 67><ACT 3><SCENE 2><47%>
	Here, sweet lord, at your service.
<SPEECH 68><ACT 3><SCENE 2><47%>
	O! my dear lord,—
<SPEECH 69><ACT 3><SCENE 2><48%>
	Well, my lord:
	If he steal aught the whilst this play is playing,
	And 'scape detecting, I will pay the theft.
<SPEECH 70><ACT 3><SCENE 2><53%>
	Half a share.
<SPEECH 71><ACT 3><SCENE 2><53%>
	You might have rimed.
<SPEECH 72><ACT 3><SCENE 2><53%>
	Very well, my lord.
<SPEECH 73><ACT 3><SCENE 2><53%>
	I did very well note him.
<SPEECH 74><ACT 4><SCENE 5><70%>
	'Twere good she were spoken with, for she may strew
	Dangerous conjectures in ill-breeding minds.
<SPEECH 75><ACT 4><SCENE 6><76%>
	What are they that would speak with me?
<SPEECH 76><ACT 4><SCENE 6><76%>
	Let them come in.
	I do not know from what part of the world
	I should be greeted, if not from Lord Hamlet.
<SPEECH 77><ACT 4><SCENE 6><76%>
	Let him bless thee too.
<SPEECH 78><ACT 4><SCENE 6><76%>
	Horatio, when thou shalt have overlooked this, give these fellows some means to the king: they have letters for him. Ere we were two days old at sea, a pirate of very war-like appointment gave us chase. Finding ourselves too slow of sail, we put on a compelled valour; in the grapple I boarded them: on the instant they got clear of our ship, so I alone became their prisoner. They have dealt with me like thieves of mercy, but they knew what they did; I am to do a good turn for them. Let the king have the letters I have sent; and repair thou to me with as much haste as thou wouldst fly death. I have words to speak in thine ear will make thee dumb; yet are they much too light for the bore of the matter. These good fellows will bring thee where I am. Rosencrantz and Guildenstern hold their course for England: of them I have much to tell thee. Farewell.
	He that thou knowest thine,
	<HAMLET.>Come, I will give you way for these your letters;
	And do 't the speedier, that you may direct me
	To him from whom you brought them.
<SPEECH 79><ACT 5><SCENE 1><83%>
	Custom hath made it in him a property of easiness.
<SPEECH 80><ACT 5><SCENE 1><84%>
	It might, my lord.
<SPEECH 81><ACT 5><SCENE 1><84%>
	Ay, my lord.
<SPEECH 82><ACT 5><SCENE 1><84%>
	Not a jot more, my lord.
<SPEECH 83><ACT 5><SCENE 1><84%>
	Ay, my lord, and of calf-skins too.
<SPEECH 84><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	What's that, my lord?
<SPEECH 85><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	E'en so.
<SPEECH 86><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	E'en so, my lord.
<SPEECH 87><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	'Twere to consider too curiously, to consider so.
<SPEECH 88><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	Good my lord, be quiet.
<SPEECH 89><ACT 5><SCENE 2><89%>
	Remember it, my lord?
<SPEECH 90><ACT 5><SCENE 2><90%>
	That is most certain.
<SPEECH 91><ACT 5><SCENE 2><90%>
	Is 't possible?
<SPEECH 92><ACT 5><SCENE 2><90%>
	I beseech you.
<SPEECH 93><ACT 5><SCENE 2><90%>
	Ay, good my lord.
<SPEECH 94><ACT 5><SCENE 2><90%>
	How was this seal'd?
<SPEECH 95><ACT 5><SCENE 2><91%>
	So Guildenstern and Rosencrantz go to 't.
<SPEECH 96><ACT 5><SCENE 2><91%>
	Why, what a king is this!
<SPEECH 97><ACT 5><SCENE 2><91%>
	It must be shortly known to him from England
	What is the issue of the business there.
<SPEECH 98><ACT 5><SCENE 2><91%>
	Peace! who comes here?
<SPEECH 99><ACT 5><SCENE 2><91%>
	</STAGE DIR> No, my good lord.
<SPEECH 100><ACT 5><SCENE 2><92%>
	Is 't not possible to understand in another tongue? You will do 't, sir, really.
<SPEECH 101><ACT 5><SCENE 2><93%>
	His purse is empty already; all 's golden words are spent.
<SPEECH 102><ACT 5><SCENE 2><93%>
	I knew you must be edified by the margent, ere you had done.
<SPEECH 103><ACT 5><SCENE 2><94%>
	This lapwing runs away with the shell on his head.
<SPEECH 104><ACT 5><SCENE 2><94%>
	You will lose this wager, my lord.
<SPEECH 105><ACT 5><SCENE 2><95%>
	Nay, good my lord,—
<SPEECH 106><ACT 5><SCENE 2><95%>
	If your mind dislike any thing, obey it; I will forestal their repair hither, and say you are not fit.
<SPEECH 107><ACT 5><SCENE 2><97%>
	They bleed on both sides. How is it, my lord?
<SPEECH 108><ACT 5><SCENE 2><98%>
	Never believe it;
	I am more an antique Roman than a Dane:
	Here's yet some liquor left.
<SPEECH 109><ACT 5><SCENE 2><99%>
	Now cracks a noble heart. Good-night, sweet prince,
	And flights of angels sing thee to thy rest!
	Why does the drum come hither?
<SPEECH 110><ACT 5><SCENE 2><99%>
	What is it ye would see?
	If aught of woe or wonder, cease your search.
<SPEECH 111><ACT 5><SCENE 2><99%>
	Not from his mouth,
	Had it the ability of life to thank you:
	He never gave commandment for their death.
	But since, so jump upon this bloody question,
	You from the Polack wars, and you from England,
	Are here arriv'd, give order that these bodies
	High on a stage be placed to the view;
	And let me speak to the yet unknowing world
	How these things came about: so shall you hear
	Of carnal, bloody, and unnatural acts,
	Of accidental judgments, casual slaughters;
	Of deaths put on by cunning and forc'd cause,
	And, in this upshot, purposes mistook
	Fall'n on the inventors' heads; all this can I
	Truly deliver.
<SPEECH 112><ACT 5><SCENE 2><100%>
	Of that I shall have also cause to speak,
	And from his mouth whose voice will draw on more:
	But let this same be presently perform'd,
	Even while men's minds are wild, lest more mischance
	On plots and errors happen.
