<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 3><12%>
	How now! who calls?
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 3><12%>
	Madam, I am here.
	What is your will?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 3><14%>
	And stint thou too, I pray thee, nurse, say I.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 3><14%>
	It is an honour that I dream not of.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 3><15%>
	I'll look to like, if looking liking move;
	But no more deep will I endart mine eye
	Than your consent gives strength to make it fly.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 5><22%>
	Good pilgrim, you do wrong your hand too much,
	Which mannerly devotion shows in this;
	For saints have hands that pilgrims' hands do touch,
	And palm to palm is holy palmers' kiss.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 5><23%>
	Ay, pilgrim, lips that they must use in prayer.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 5><23%>
	Saints do not move, though grant for prayers' sake.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 5><23%>
	Then have my lips the sin that they have took.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 5><23%>
	You kiss by the book.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 5><23%>
	Come hither, nurse. What is yond gentleman?
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 5><24%>
	What's he that now is going out of door?
<SPEECH 13><ACT 1><SCENE 5><24%>
	What's he, that follows there, that would not dance?
<SPEECH 14><ACT 1><SCENE 5><24%>
	Go, ask his name.—If he be married,
	My grave is like to be my wedding bed.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 1><SCENE 5><24%>
	My only love sprung from my only hate!
	Too early seen unknown, and known too late!
	Prodigious birth of love it is to me,
	That I must love a loathed enemy.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 1><SCENE 5><24%>
	A rime I learn'd even now
	Of one I danc'd withal.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	Ay me!
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	O Romeo, Romeo! wherefore art thou Romeo?
	Deny thy father, and refuse thy name;
	Or, if thou wilt not, be but sworn my love,
	And I'll no longer be a Capulet.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	'Tis but thy name that is my enemy;
	Thou art thyself though, not a Montague.
	What's Montague? it is nor hand, nor foot,
	Nor arm, nor face, nor any other part
	Belonging to a man. O! be some other name:
	What's in a name? that which we call a rose
	By any other name would smell as sweet;
	So Romeo would, were he not Romeo call'd,
	Retain that dear perfection which he owes
	Without that title. Romeo, doff thy name;
	And for that name, which is no part of thee,
	Take all myself.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	What man art thou, that, thus bescreen'd in night,
	So stumblest on my counsel?
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	My ears have not yet drunk a hundred words
	Of that tongue's uttering, yet I know the sound:
	Art thou not Romeo, and a Montague?
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	How cam'st thou hither, tell me, and wherefore?
	The orchard walls are high and hard to climb,
	And the place death, considering who thou art,
	If any of my kinsmen find thee here.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	If they do see thee they will murder thee.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	I would not for the world they saw thee here.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	By whose direction found'st thou out this place?
<SPEECH 26><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	Thou know'st the mask of night is on my face,
	Else would a maiden blush bepaint my cheek
	For that which thou hast heard me speak to-night.
	Fain would I dwell on form, fain, fain deny
	What I have spoke: but farewell compliment!
	Dost thou love me? I know thou wilt say 'Ay;'
	And I will take thy word; yet, if thou swear'st,
	Thou mayst prove false; at lovers' perjuries,
	They say, Jove laughs. O gentle Romeo!
	If thou dost love, pronounce it faithfully:
	Or if thou think'st I am too quickly won,
	I'll frown and be perverse and say thee nay,
	So thou wilt woo; but else, not for the world.
	In truth, fair Montague, I am too fond,
	And therefore thou mayst think my haviour light:
	But trust me, gentleman, I'll prove more true
	Than those that have more cunning to be strange.
	I should have been more strange, I must confess,
	But that thou over-heard'st, ere I was 'ware,
	My true love's passion: therefore pardon me,
	And not impute this yielding to light love,
	Which the dark night hath so discovered.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	O! swear not by the moon, the inconstant moon,
	That monthly changes in her circled orb,
	Lest that thy love prove likewise variable.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	Do not swear at all;
	Or, if thou wilt, swear by thy gracious self,
	Which is the god of my idolatry,
	And I'll believe thee.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	Well, do not swear. Although I joy in thee,
	I have no joy of this contract to-night:
	It is too rash, too unadvis'd, too sudden;
	Too like the lightning, which doth cease to be
	Ere one can say it lightens. Sweet, good-night!
	This bud of love, by summer's ripening breath,
	May prove a beauteous flower when next we meet.
	Good-night, good-night! as sweet repose and rest
	Come to thy heart as that within my breast!
<SPEECH 30><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	What satisfaction canst thou have to-night?
<SPEECH 31><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	I gave thee mine before thou didst request it;
	And yet I would it were to give again.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	But to be frank, and give it thee again.
	And yet I wish but for the thing I have:
	My bounty is as boundless as the sea,
	My love as deep; the more I give to thee,
	The more I have, for both are infinite.
	I hear some noise within; dear love, adieu!
	Anon, good nurse! Sweet Montague, be true.
	Stay but a little, I will come again.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	Three words, dear Romeo, and good-night indeed.
	If that thy bent of love be honourable,
	Thy purpose marriage, send me word to-morrow,
	By one that I'll procure to come to thee,
	Where, and what time, thou wilt perform the rite;
	And all my fortunes at thy foot I'll lay,
	And follow thee my lord throughout the world.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	I come, anon.—But if thou mean'st not well,
	I do beseech thee,—
<SPEECH 35><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	By and by; I come:—
	To cease thy suit, and leave me to my grief:
	To-morrow will I send.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	A thousand times good-night!
<SPEECH 37><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	Hist! Romeo, hist! O! for a falconer's voice,
	To lure this tassel-gentle back again.
	Bondage is hoarse, and may not speak aloud,
	Else would I tear the cave where Echo lies,
	And make her airy tongue more hoarse than mine,
	With repetition of my Romeo's name.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	Romeo!
<SPEECH 39><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	At what o'clock to-morrow
	Shall I send to thee?
<SPEECH 40><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	I will not fail; 'tis twenty years till then.
	I have forgot why I did call thee back.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	I shall forget, to have thee still stand there,
	Remembering how I love thy company.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	'Tis almost morning; I would have thee gone;
	And yet no further than a wanton's bird,
	Who lets it hop a little from her hand,
	Like a poor prisoner in his twisted gyves,
	And with a silk thread plucks it back again,
	So loving-jealous of his liberty.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	Sweet, so would I:
	Yet I should kill thee with much cherishing.
	Good-night, good-night! parting is such sweet sorrow
	That I shall say good-night till it be morrow.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 2><SCENE 5><42%>
	The clock struck nine when I did send the nurse;
	In half an hour she promis'd to return.
	Perchance she cannot meet him: that's not so.
	O! she is lame: love's heralds should be thoughts,
	Which ten times faster glide than the sun's beams,
	Driving back shadows over lowering hills:
	Therefore do nimble-pinion'd doves draw Love,
	And therefore hath the wind-swift Cupid wings.
	Now is the sun upon the highmost hill
	Of this day's journey, and from nine till twelve
	Is three long hours, yet she is not come.
	Had she affections, and warm youthful blood,
	She'd be as swift in motion as a ball;
	My words would bandy her to my sweet love,
	And his to me:
	But old folks, many feign as they were dead;
	Unwieldy, slow, heavy and pale as lead.
	O God! she comes. O honey nurse! what news?
	Hast thou met with him? Send thy man away.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 2><SCENE 5><43%>
	Now, good sweet nurse; O Lord! why look'st thou sad?
	Though news be sad, yet tell them merrily;
	If good, thou sham'st the music of sweet news
	By playing it to me with so sour a face.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 2><SCENE 5><43%>
	I would thou hadst my bones, and I thy news.
	Nay, come, I pray thee, speak; good, good nurse, speak.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 2><SCENE 5><43%>
	How art thou out of breath when thou hast breath
	To say to me that thou art out of breath?
	The excuse that thou dost make in this delay
	Is longer than the tale thou dost excuse.
	Is thy news good, or bad? answer to that;
	Say either, and I'll stay the circumstance:
	Let me be satisfied, is 't good or bad?
<SPEECH 48><ACT 2><SCENE 5><43%>
	No, no: but all this did I know before.
	What says he of our marriage? what of that?
<SPEECH 49><ACT 2><SCENE 5><44%>
	I' faith, I am sorry that thou art not well.
	Sweet, sweet, sweet nurse, tell me, what says my love?
<SPEECH 50><ACT 2><SCENE 5><44%>
	Where is my mother! why, she is within;
	Where should she be? How oddly thou repliest:
	'Your love says, like an honest gentleman,
	Where is your mother?'
<SPEECH 51><ACT 2><SCENE 5><44%>
	Here's such a coil! come, what says Romeo?
<SPEECH 52><ACT 2><SCENE 5><44%>
	I have.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 2><SCENE 5><44%>
	Hie to high fortune! Honest nurse, farewell.
<SPEECH 54><ACT 2><SCENE 6><45%>
	Good even to my ghostly confessor.
<SPEECH 55><ACT 2><SCENE 6><45%>
	As much to him, else are his thanks too much.
<SPEECH 56><ACT 2><SCENE 6><45%>
	Conceit, more rich in matter than in words,
	Brags of his substance, not of ornament:
	They are but beggars that can count their worth;
	But my true love is grown to such excess
	I cannot sum up half my sum of wealth.
<SPEECH 57><ACT 3><SCENE 2><53%>
	Gallop apace, you fiery-footed steeds,
	Towards Phœbus' lodging; such a waggoner
	As Phæthon would whip you to the west,
	And bring in cloudy night immediately.
	Spread thy close curtain, love-performing night!
	That runaway's eyes may wink, and Romeo
	Leap to these arms, untalk'd of and unseen!
	Lovers can see to do their amorous rites
	By their own beauties; or, if love be blind,
	It best agrees with night. Come, civil night,
	Thou sober-suited matron, all in black,
	And learn me how to lose a winning match,
	Play'd for a pair of stainless maidenhoods:
	Hood my unmann'd blood, bating in my cheeks,
	With thy black mantle; till strange love, grown bold,
	Think true love acted simple modesty.
	Come, night! come, Romeo! come, thou day in night!
	For thou wilt lie upon the wings of night,
	Whiter than new snow on a raven's back.
	Come, gentle night; come, loving, black-brow'd night,
	Give me my Romeo: and, when he shall die,
	Take him and cut him out in little stars,
	And he will make the face of heaven so fine
	That all the world will be in love with night,
	And pay no worship to the garish sun.
	O! I have bought the mansion of a love,
	But not possess'd it, and, though I am sold,
	Not yet enjoy'd. So tedious is this day
	As is the night before some festival
	To an impatient child that hath new robes
	And may not wear them. O! here comes my nurse,
	And she brings news; and every tongue that speaks
	But Romeo's name speaks heavenly eloquence.
	Now nurse, what news? What hast thou there? the cords
	That Romeo bade thee fetch?
<SPEECH 58><ACT 3><SCENE 2><54%>
	Ah me! what news? why dost thou wring thy hands?
<SPEECH 59><ACT 3><SCENE 2><54%>
	Can heaven be so envious?
<SPEECH 60><ACT 3><SCENE 2><54%>
	What devil art thou that dost torment me thus?
	This torture should be roar'd in dismal hell.
	Hath Romeo slain himself? say thou but 'I,'
	And that bare vowel, 'I,' shall poison more
	Than the death-darting eye of cockatrice:
	I am not I, if there be such an 'I;'
	Or those eyes shut that make thee answer 'I.'
	If he be slain, say 'I;' or if not 'no:'
	Brief sounds determine of my weal or woe.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 3><SCENE 2><54%>
	O break, my heart!—poor bankrupt, break at once!
	To prison, eyes, ne'er look on liberty!
	Vile earth, to earth resign; end motion here;
	And thou and Romeo press one heavy bier!
<SPEECH 62><ACT 3><SCENE 2><55%>
	What storm is this that blows so contrary?
	Is Romeo slaughter'd, and is Tybalt dead?
	My dearest cousin, and my dearer lord?
	Then, dreadful trumpet, sound the general doom!
	For who is living if those two are gone?
<SPEECH 63><ACT 3><SCENE 2><55%>
	O God! did Romeo's hand shed Tybalt's blood?
<SPEECH 64><ACT 3><SCENE 2><55%>
	O serpent heart, hid with a flowering face!
	Did ever dragon keep so fair a cave?
	Beautiful tyrant! fiend angelical!
	Dove-feather'd raven! wolvish-ravening lamb!
	Despised substance of divinest show!
	Just opposite to what thou justly seem'st;
	A damned saint, an honourable villain!
	O, nature! what hadst thou to do in hell
	When thou didst bower the spirit of a fiend
	In mortal paradise of such sweet flesh?
	Was ever book containing such vile matter
	So fairly bound? O! that deceit should dwell
	In such a gorgeous palace.
<SPEECH 65><ACT 3><SCENE 2><55%>
	Blister'd be thy tongue
	For such a wish! he was not born to shame:
	Upon his brow shame is asham'd to sit;
	For 'tis a throne where honour may be crown'd
	Sole monarch of the universal earth.
	O! what a beast was I to chide at him.
<SPEECH 66><ACT 3><SCENE 2><56%>
	Shall I speak ill of him that is my husband?
	Ah! poor my lord, what tongue shall smooth thy name,
	When I, thy three-hours wife, have mangled it?
	But, wherefore, villain, didst thou kill my cousin?
	That villain cousin would have kill'd my husband:
	Back, foolish tears, back to your native spring;
	Your tributary drops belong to woe,
	Which you, mistaking, offer up to joy.
	My husband lives, that Tybalt would have slain;
	And Tybalt's dead, that would have slain my husband:
	All this is comfort; wherefore weep I then?
	Some word there was, worser than Tybalt's death,
	That murder'd me: I would forget it fain;
	But O! it presses to my memory,
	Like damned guilty deeds to sinners' minds.
	'Tybalt is dead, and Romeo banished!'
	That 'banished,' that one word 'banished,'
	Hath slain ten thousand Tybalts. Tybalt's death
	Was woe enough, if it had ended there:
	Or, if sour woe delights in fellowship,
	And needly will be rank'd with other griefs,
	Why follow'd not, when she said 'Tybalt's dead,'
	Thy father, or thy mother, nay, or both,
	Which modern lamentation might have mov'd?
	But with a rearward following Tybalt's death,
	'Romeo is banished!' to speak that word
	Is father, mother, Tybalt, Romeo, Juliet,
	All slain, all dead: 'Romeo is banished!'
	There is no end, no limit, measure, bound
	In that word's death; no words can that woe sound.—
	Where is my father and my mother, nurse?
<SPEECH 67><ACT 3><SCENE 2><57%>
	Wash they his wounds with tears: mine shall be spent,
	When theirs are dry, for Romeo's banishment.
	Take up those cords. Poor ropes, you are beguil'd,
	Both you and I, for Romeo is exil'd:
	He made you for a highway to my bed,
	But I, a maid, die maiden-widowed.
	Come, cords; come, nurse; I'll to my wedding bed;
	And death, not Romeo, take my maidenhead!
<SPEECH 68><ACT 3><SCENE 2><57%>
	O! find him; give this ring to my true knight,
	And bid him come to take his last farewell.
<SPEECH 69><ACT 3><SCENE 5><64%>
	Wilt thou be gone? it is not yet near day:
	It was the nightingale, and not the lark,
	That pierc'd the fearful hollow of thine ear;
	Nightly she sings on you pomegranate tree:
	Believe me, love, it was the nightingale.
<SPEECH 70><ACT 3><SCENE 5><64%>
	Yon light is not daylight, I know it, I:
	It is some meteor that the sun exhales,
	To be to thee this night a torch-bearer,
	And light thee on thy way to Mantua:
	Therefore stay yet; thou need'st not to be gone.
<SPEECH 71><ACT 3><SCENE 5><65%>
	It is, it is; hie hence, be gone, away!
	It is the lark that sings so out of tune,
	Straining harsh discords and unpleasing sharps.
	Some say the lark makes sweet division;
	This doth not so, for she divideth us:
	Some say the lark and loathed toad change eyes;
	O! now I would they had chang'd voices too,
	Since arm from arm that voice doth us affray,
	Hunting thee hence with hunts-up to the day.
	O! now be gone; more light and light it grows.
<SPEECH 72><ACT 3><SCENE 5><65%>
	Nurse!
<SPEECH 73><ACT 3><SCENE 5><65%>
	Then, window, let day in, and let life out.
<SPEECH 74><ACT 3><SCENE 5><65%>
	Art thou gone so? my lord, my love, my friend!
	I must hear from thee every day in the hour,
	For in a minute there are many days:
	O! by this count I shall be much in years
	Ere I again behold my Romeo.
<SPEECH 75><ACT 3><SCENE 5><65%>
	O! think'st thou we shall ever meet again?
<SPEECH 76><ACT 3><SCENE 5><66%>
	O God! I have an ill-divining soul:
	Methinks I see thee, now thou art so low,
	As one dead in the bottom of a tomb:
	Either my eyesight fails, or thou look'st pale.
<SPEECH 77><ACT 3><SCENE 5><66%>
	O fortune, fortune! all men call thee fickle:
	If thou art fickle, what dost thou with him
	That is renown'd for faith? Be fickle, fortune;
	For then, I hope, thou wilt not keep him long,
	But send him back.
<SPEECH 78><ACT 3><SCENE 5><66%>
	Who is't that calls? is it my lady mother?
	Is she not down so late, or up so early?
	What unaccustom'd cause procures her hither?
<SPEECH 79><ACT 3><SCENE 5><66%>
	Madam, I am not well.
<SPEECH 80><ACT 3><SCENE 5><66%>
	Yet let me weep for such a feeling loss.
<SPEECH 81><ACT 3><SCENE 5><66%>
	Feeling so the loss,
	I cannot choose but ever weep the friend.
<SPEECH 82><ACT 3><SCENE 5><67%>
	What villain, madam?
<SPEECH 83><ACT 3><SCENE 5><67%>
	</STAGE DIR> Villain and he be many miles asunder.
	God pardon him! I do, with all my heart;
	And yet no man like he doth grieve my heart.
<SPEECH 84><ACT 3><SCENE 5><67%>
	Ay, madam, from the reach of these my hands.
	Would none but I might venge my cousin's death!
<SPEECH 85><ACT 3><SCENE 5><67%>
	Indeed, I never shall be satisfied
	With Romeo, till I behold him—dead—
	Is my poor heart so for a kinsman vex'd:
	Madam, if you could find out but a man
	To bear a poison, I would temper it,
	That Romeo should, upon receipt thereof,
	Soon sleep in quiet. O! how my heart abhors
	To hear him nam'd, and cannot come to him,
	To wreak the love I bore my cousin Tybalt
	Upon his body that hath slaughter'd him.
<SPEECH 86><ACT 3><SCENE 5><67%>
	And joy comes well in such a needy time:
	What are they, I beseech your ladyship?
<SPEECH 87><ACT 3><SCENE 5><68%>
	Madam, in happy time, what day is that?
<SPEECH 88><ACT 3><SCENE 5><68%>
	Now, by Saint Peter's church, and Peter too,
	He shall not make me there a joyful bride.
	I wonder at this haste; that I must wed
	Ere he that should be husband comes to woo.
	I pray you, tell my lord and father, madam,
	I will not marry yet; and, when I do, I swear,
	It shall be Romeo, whom you know I hate,
	Rather than Paris. These are news indeed!
<SPEECH 89><ACT 3><SCENE 5><69%>
	Not proud, you have; but thankful, that you have:
	Proud can I never be of what I hate;
	But thankful even for hate, that is meant love.
<SPEECH 90><ACT 3><SCENE 5><69%>
	Good father, I beseech you on my knees,
	Hear me with patience but to speak a word.
<SPEECH 91><ACT 3><SCENE 5><70%>
	Is there no pity sitting in the clouds,
	That sees into the bottom of my grief?
	O! sweet my mother, cast me not away:
	Delay this marriage for a month, a week;
	Or, if you do not, make the bridal bed
	In that dim monument where Tybalt lies.
<SPEECH 92><ACT 3><SCENE 5><71%>
	O God! O nurse! how shall this be prevented?
	My husband is on earth, my faith in heaven;
	How shall that faith return again to earth,
	Unless that husband send it me from heaven
	By leaving earth? comfort me, counsel me.
	Alack, alack! that heaven should practise stratagems
	Upon so soft a subject as myself!
	What sayst thou? hast thou not a word of joy?
	Some comfort, nurse?
<SPEECH 93><ACT 3><SCENE 5><71%>
	Speakest thou from thy heart?
<SPEECH 94><ACT 3><SCENE 5><71%>
	Amen!
<SPEECH 95><ACT 3><SCENE 5><71%>
	Well, thou hast comforted me marvellous much.
	Go in; and tell my lady I am gone,
	Having displeas'd my father, to Laurence' cell,
	To make confession and to be absolv'd.
<SPEECH 96><ACT 3><SCENE 5><72%>
	Ancient damnation! O most wicked fiend!
	Is it more sin to wish me thus forsworn,
	Or to dispraise my lord with that same tongue
	Which she hath prais'd him with above compare
	So many thousand times? Go, counsellor;
	Thou and my bosom henceforth shall be twain.
	I'll to the friar, to know his remedy:
	If all else fail, myself have power to die.
<SPEECH 97><ACT 4><SCENE 1><72%>
	That may be, sir, when I may be a wife.
<SPEECH 98><ACT 4><SCENE 1><73%>
	What must be shall be.
<SPEECH 99><ACT 4><SCENE 1><73%>
	To answer that, I should confess to you.
<SPEECH 100><ACT 4><SCENE 1><73%>
	I will confess to you that I love him.
<SPEECH 101><ACT 4><SCENE 1><73%>
	If I do so, it will be of more price,
	Being spoke behind your back, than to your face.
<SPEECH 102><ACT 4><SCENE 1><73%>
	The tears have got small victory by that;
	For it was bad enough before their spite.
<SPEECH 103><ACT 4><SCENE 1><73%>
	That is no slander, sir, which is a truth;
	And what I spake, I spake it to my face.
<SPEECH 104><ACT 4><SCENE 1><73%>
	It may be so, for it is not mine own.
	Are you at leisure, holy father, now;
	Or shall I come to you at evening mass?
<SPEECH 105><ACT 4><SCENE 1><73%>
	O! shut the door! and when thou hast done so,
	Come weep with me; past hope, past cure, past help!
<SPEECH 106><ACT 4><SCENE 1><74%>
	Tell me not, friar, that thou hear'st of this,
	Unless thou tell me how I may prevent it:
	If, in thy wisdom, thou canst give no help,
	Do thou but call my resolution wise,
	And with this knife I'll help it presently,
	God join'd my heart and Romeo's, thou our hands;
	And ere this hand, by thee to Romeo seal'd,
	Shall be the label to another deed,
	Or my true heart with treacherous revolt
	Turn to another, this shall slay them both.
	Therefore, out of thy long-experienc'd time,
	Give me some present counsel; or behold,
	'Twixt my extremes and me this bloody knife
	Shall play the umpire, arbitrating that
	Which the commission of thy years and art
	Could to no issue of true honour bring.
	Be not so long to speak; I long to die,
	If what thou speak'st speak not of remedy.
<SPEECH 107><ACT 4><SCENE 1><74%>
	O! bid me leap, rather than marry Paris,
	From off the battlements of yonder tower;
	Or walk in thievish ways; or bid me lurk
	Where serpents are; chain me with roaring bears;
	Or shut me nightly in a charnel-house,
	O'er-cover'd quite with dead men's rattling bones,
	With reeky shanks, and yellow chapless skulls;
	Or bid me go into a new-made grave
	And hide me with a dead man in his shroud;
	Things that, to hear them told, have made me tremble;
	And I will do it without fear or doubt,
	To live an unstain'd wife to my sweet love.
<SPEECH 108><ACT 4><SCENE 1><76%>
	Give me, give me! O! tell me not of fear!
<SPEECH 109><ACT 4><SCENE 1><76%>
	Love, give me strength! and strength shall help afford.
	Farewell, dear father!
<SPEECH 110><ACT 4><SCENE 2><77%>
	Where I have learn'd me to repent the sin
	Of disobedient opposition
	To you and your behests; and am enjoin'd
	By holy Laurence to fall prostrate here,
	And beg your pardon. Pardon, I beseech you!
	Henceforward I am ever rul'd by you.
<SPEECH 111><ACT 4><SCENE 2><77%>
	I met the youthful lord at Laurence' cell;
	And gave him what becomed love I might,
	Not stepping o'er the bounds of modesty.
<SPEECH 112><ACT 4><SCENE 2><77%>
	Nurse, will you go with me into my closet,
	To help me sort such needful ornaments
	As you think fit to furnish me to-morrow?
<SPEECH 113><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	Ay, those attires are best; but, gentle nurse,
	I pray thee, leave me to myself to-night;
	For I have need of many orisons
	To move the heavens to smile upon my state,
	Which, well thou know'st, is cross and full of sin.
<SPEECH 114><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	No, madam; we have cull'd such necessaries
	As are behoveful for our state to-morrow:
	So please you, let me now be left alone,
	And let the nurse this night sit up with you;
	For, I am sure, you have your hands full all
	In this so sudden business.
<SPEECH 115><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	Farewell! God knows when we shall meet again.
	I have a faint cold fear thrills through my veins,
	That almost freezes up the heat of life:
	I'll call them back again to comfort me:
	Nurse! What should she do here?
	My dismal scene I needs must act alone.
	Come, vial.
	What if this mixture do not work at all?
	Shall I be married then to-morrow morning?
	No, no; this shall forbid it: lie thou there.
	What if it be a poison, which the friar
	Subtly hath minister'd to have me dead,
	Lest in this marriage he should be dishonour'd
	Because he married me before to Romeo?
	I fear it is: and yet, methinks, it should not,
	For he hath still been tried a holy man.
	I will not entertain so bad a thought.
	How if, when I am laid into the tomb,
	I wake before the time that Romeo
	Come to redeem me? there's a fearful point!
	Shall I not then be stifled in the vault,
	To whose foul mouth no healthsome air breathes in,
	And there die strangled ere my Romeo comes?
	Or, if I live, is it not very like,
	The horrible conceit of death and night,
	Together with the terror of the place,
	As in a vault, an ancient receptacle,
	Where, for these many hundred years, the bones
	Of all my buried ancestors are pack'd;
	Where bloody Tybalt, yet but green in earth,
	Lies festering in his shroud; where, as they say,
	At some hours in the night spirits resort:
	Alack, alack! is it not like that I,
	So early waking, what with loathsome smells,
	And shrieks like mandrakes' torn out of the earth,
	That living mortals, hearing them, run mad:
	O! if I wake, shall I not be distraught,
	Environed with all these hideous fears,
	And madly play with my forefathers' joints,
	And pluck the mangled Tybalt from his shroud?
	And, in this rage, with some great kinsman's bone,
	As with a club, dash out my desperate brains?
	O, look! methinks I see my cousin's ghost
	Seeking out Romeo, that did spit his body
	Upon a rapier's point. Stay, Tybalt, stay!
	Romeo, I come! this do I drink to thee.
<SPEECH 116><ACT 5><SCENE 3><94%>
	O, comfortable friar! where is my lord?
	I do remember well where I should be,
	And there I am. Where is my Romeo?
<SPEECH 117><ACT 5><SCENE 3><95%>
	Go, get thee hence, for I will not away.
	What's here? a cup, clos'd in my true love's hand?
	Poison, I see, hath been his timeless end.
	O churl! drunk all, and left no friendly drop
	To help me after! I will kiss thy lips;
	Haply, some poison yet doth hang on them,
	To make me die with a restorative.
	Thy lips are warm!
<SPEECH 118><ACT 5><SCENE 3><95%>
	Yea, noise? then I'll be brief. O happy dagger!
	This is thy sheath; <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> there rest, and let me die.
