<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 2><5%>
	Though yet of Hamlet our dear brother's death
	The memory be green, and that it us befitted
	To bear our hearts in grief and our whole kingdom
	To be contracted in one brow of woe,
	Yet so far hath discretion fought with nature
	That we with wisest sorrow think on him,
	Together with remembrance of ourselves.
	Therefore our sometime sister, now our queen,
	The imperial jointress of this war-like state,
	Have we, as 'twere with a defeated joy,
	With one auspicious and one dropping eye,
	With mirth in funeral and with dirge in marriage,
	In equal scale weighing delight and dole,
	Taken to wife: nor have we herein barr'd
	Your better wisdoms, which have freely gone
	With this affair along: for all, our thanks.
	Now follows, that you know, young Fortinbras,
	Holding a weak supposal of our worth,
	Or thinking by our late dear brother's death
	Our state to be disjoint and out of frame,
	Colleagued with the dream of his advantage,
	He hath not fail'd to pester us with message,
	Importing the surrender of those lands
	Lost by his father, with all bands of law,
	To our most valiant brother. So much for him.
	Now for ourself and for this time of meeting.
	Thus much the business is: we have here writ
	To Norway, uncle of young Fortinbras,
	Who, impotent and bed-rid, scarcely hears
	Of this his nephew's purpose, to suppress
	His further gait herein; in that the levies,
	The lists and full proportions, are all made
	Out of his subject; and we here dispatch
	You, good Cornelius, and you, Voltimand,
	For bearers of this greeting to old Norway,
	Giving to you no further personal power
	To business with the king more than the scope
	Of these delated articles allow.
	Farewell and let your haste commend your duty.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 2><6%>
	We doubt it nothing: heartily farewell.
	And now, Laertes, what's the news with you?
	You told us of some suit; what is't, Laertes?
	You cannot speak of reason to the Dane,
	And lose your voice; what wouldst thou beg, Laertes,
	That shall not be my offer, not thy asking?
	The head is not more native to the heart,
	The hand more instrumental to the mouth,
	Than is the throne of Denmark to thy father.
	What wouldst thou have, Laertes?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 2><6%>
	Have you your father's leave? What says Polonius?
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 2><6%>
	Take thy fair hour, Laertes; time be thine,
	And thy best graces spend it at thy will.
	But now, my cousin Hamlet, and my son,—
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 2><6%>
	How is it that the clouds still hang on you?
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	'Tis sweet and commendable in your nature, Hamlet,
	To give these mourning duties to your father:
	But, you must know, your father lost a father;
	That father lost, lost his; and the survivor bound
	In filial obligation for some term
	To do obsequious sorrow; but to persever
	In obstinate condolement is a course
	Of impious stubbornness; 'tis unmanly grief:
	It shows a will most incorrect to heaven,
	A heart unfortified, a mind impatient,
	An understanding simple and unschool'd:
	For what we know must be and is as common
	As any the most vulgar thing to sense,
	Why should we in our peevish opposition
	Take it to heart? Fie! 'tis a fault to heaven,
	A fault against the dead, a fault to nature,
	To reason most absurd, whose common theme
	Is death of fathers, and who still hath cried,
	From the first corse till he that died to-day,
	'This must be so.' We pray you, throw to earth
	This unprevailing woe, and think of us
	As of a father; for let the world take note,
	You are the most immediate to our throne;
	And with no less nobility of love
	Than that which dearest father bears his son
	Do I impart toward you. For your intent
	In going back to school in Wittenberg,
	It is most retrograde to our desire;
	And we beseech you, bend you to remain
	Here, in the cheer and comfort of our eye,
	Our chiefest courtier, cousin, and our son.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 2><8%>
	Why, 'tis a loving and a fair reply:
	Be as ourself in Denmark. Madam, come;
	This gentle and unforc'd accord of Hamlet
	Sits smiling to my heart; in grace whereof,
	No jocund health that Denmark drinks to-day,
	But the great cannon to the clouds shall tell,
	And the king's rouse the heavens shall bruit again,
	Re-speaking earthly thunder. Come away.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 2><25%>
	Welcome, dear Rosencrantz and Guildenstern!
	Moreover that we much did long to see you,
	The need we have to use you did provoke
	Our hasty sending. Something have you heard
	Of Hamlet's transformation; so I call it,
	Since nor the exterior nor the inward man
	Resembles that it was. What it should be
	More than his father's death, that thus hath put him
	So much from the understanding of himself,
	I cannot dream of: I entreat you both,
	That, being of so young days brought up with him,
	And since so neighbour'd to his youth and humour,
	That you vouchsafe your rest here in our court
	Some little time; so by your companies
	To draw him on to pleasures, and to gather,
	So much as from occasion you may glean,
	Whe'r aught to us unknown afflicts him thus,
	That, open'd, lies within our remedy.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 2><SCENE 2><26%>
	Thanks, Rosencrantz and gentle Guildenstern.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 2><26%>
	Thou still hast been the father of good news.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	O! speak of that; that do I long to hear.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	Thyself do grace to them, and bring them in.
	He tells me, my sweet queen, that he hath found
	The head and source of all your son's distemper.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	Well, we shall sift him.
	Welcome, my good friends!
	Say, Voltimand, what from our brother Norway?
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	It likes us well;
	And at our more consider'd time we'll read,
	Answer, and think upon this business:
	Meantime we thank you for your well-took labour.
	Go to your rest; at night we'll feast together:
	Most welcome home.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	But how hath she
	Receiv'd his love?
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	As of a man faithful and honourable.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	Do you think 'tis this?
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	Not that I know.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	How may we try it further?
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	We will try it.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 3><SCENE 1><41%>
	And can you, by no drift of circumstance,
	Get from him why he puts on this confusion,
	Grating so harshly all his days of quiet
	With turbulent and dangerous lunacy?
<SPEECH 22><ACT 3><SCENE 1><41%>
	With all my heart; and it doth much content me
	To hear him so inclin'd.
	Good gentlemen, give him a further edge,
	And drive his purpose on to these delights.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 3><SCENE 1><41%>
	Sweet Gertrude, leave us too;
	For we have closely sent for Hamlet hither,
	That he, as 'twere by accident, may here
	Affront Ophelia.
	Her father and myself, lawful espials,
	Will so bestow ourselves, that, seeing, unseen,
	We may of their encounter frankly judge,
	And gather by him, as he is behav'd,
	If 't be the affliction of his love or no
	That thus he suffers for.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 3><SCENE 1><42%>
	</STAGE DIR> O! 'tis too true;
	How smart a lash that speech doth give my conscience!
	The harlot's cheek, beautied with plastering art,
	Is not more ugly to the thing that helps it
	Than is my deed to my most painted word:
	O heavy burden!
<SPEECH 25><ACT 3><SCENE 1><45%>
	Love! his affections do not that way tend;
	Nor what he spake, though it lack'd form a little,
	Was not like madness. There's something in his soul
	O'er which his melancholy sits on brood;
	And, I do doubt, the hatch and the disclose
	Will be some danger; which for to prevent,
	I have in quick determination
	Thus set it down: he shall with speed to England,
	For the demand of our neglected tribute:
	Haply the seas and countries different
	With variable objects shall expel
	This something-settled matter in his heart,
	Whereon his brains still beating puts him thus
	From fashion of himself. What think you on't?
<SPEECH 26><ACT 3><SCENE 1><45%>
	It shall be so:
	Madness in great ones must not unwatch'd go.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 3><SCENE 2><48%>
	How fares our cousin Hamlet?
<SPEECH 28><ACT 3><SCENE 2><48%>
	I have nothing with this answer, Hamlet; these words are not mine.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 3><SCENE 2><52%>
	Have you heard the argument? Is there no offence in 't?
<SPEECH 30><ACT 3><SCENE 2><52%>
	What do you call the play?
<SPEECH 31><ACT 3><SCENE 2><53%>
	Give me some light: away!
<SPEECH 32><ACT 3><SCENE 3><56%>
	I like him not, nor stands it safe with us
	To let his madness range. Therefore prepare you;
	I your commission will forth with dispatch,
	And he to England shall along with you.
	The terms of our estate may not endure
	Hazard so dangerous as doth hourly grow
	Out of his lunacies.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 3><SCENE 3><57%>
	Arm you, I pray you, to this speedy voyage;
	For we will fetters put upon this fear,
	Which now goes too free-footed.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 3><SCENE 3><57%>
	Thanks, dear my lord.
	O! my offence is rank, it smells to heaven;
	It hath the primal eldest curse upon't;
	A brother's murder! Pray can I not,
	Though inclination be as sharp as will:
	My stronger guilt defeats my strong intent;
	And, like a man to double business bound,
	I stand in pause where I shall first begin,
	And both neglect. What if this cursed hand
	Were thicker than itself with brother's blood,
	Is there not rain enough in the sweet heavens
	To wash it white as snow? Whereto serves mercy
	But to confront the visage of offence?
	And what's in prayer but this two-fold force,
	To be forestalled, ere we come to fall,
	Or pardon'd, being down? Then, I'll look up;
	My fault is past. But, O! what form of prayer
	Can serve my turn? 'Forgive me my foul murder?'
	That cannot be; since I am still possess'd
	Of those effects for which I did the murder,
	My crown, mine own ambition, and my queen.
	May one be pardon'd and retain the offence?
	In the corrupted currents of this world
	Offence's gilded hand may shove by justice,
	And oft 'tis seen the wicked prise itself
	Buys out the law; but 'tis not so above;
	There is no shuffling, there the action lies
	In his true nature, and we ourselves compell'd
	Even to the teeth and forehead of our faults
	To give in evidence. What then? what rests?
	Try what repentance can: what can it not?
	Yet what can it, when one can not repent?
	O wretched state! O bosom black as death!
	O limed soul, that struggling to be free
	Art more engaged! Help, angels! make assay;
	Bow, stubborn knees; and heart with strings of steel
	Be soft as sinews of the new-born babe.
	All may be well.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 3><SCENE 3><58%>
	My words fly up, my thoughts remain below:
	Words without thoughts never to heaven go.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 4><SCENE 1><64%>
	There's matter in these sighs, these profound heaves:
	You must translate; 'tis fit we understand them.
	Where is your son?
<SPEECH 37><ACT 4><SCENE 1><64%>
	What, Gertrude? How does Hamlet?
<SPEECH 38><ACT 4><SCENE 1><65%>
	O heavy deed!
	It had been so with us had we been there.
	His liberty is full of threats to all;
	To you yourself, to us, to every one.
	Alas! how shall this bloody deed be answer'd?
	It will be laid to us, whose providence
	Should have kept short, restrain'd, and out of haunt,
	This mad young man: but so much was our love,
	We would not understand what was most fit,
	But, like the owner of a foul disease,
	To keep it from divulging, let it feed
	Even on the pith of life. Where is he gone?
<SPEECH 39><ACT 4><SCENE 1><65%>
	O Gertrude! come away.
	The sun no sooner shall the mountains touch
	But we will ship him hence; and this vile deed
	We must, with all our majesty and skill,
	Both countenance and excuse. Ho! Guildenstern!
	Friends both, go join you with some further aid:
	Hamlet in madness hath Polonius slain,
	And from his mother's closet hath he dragg'd him:
	Go seek him out; speak fair, and bring the body
	Into the chapel. I pray you, haste in this.
	Come, Gertrude, we'll call up our wisest friends;
	And let them know both what we mean to do,
	And what's untimely done: so, haply, slander,
	Whose whisper o'er the world's diameter,
	As level as the cannon to his blank
	Transports his poison'd shot, may miss our name,
	And hit the woundless air. O! come away;
	My soul is full of discord and dismay.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 4><SCENE 3><66%>
	I have sent to seek him, and to find the body.
	How dangerous is it that this man goes loose!
	Yet must not we put the strong law on him:
	He's lov'd of the distracted multitude,
	Who like not in their judgment, but their eyes;
	And where 'tis so, the offender's scourge is weigh'd,
	But never the offence. To bear all smooth and even,
	This sudden sending him away must seem
	Deliberate pause: diseases desperate grown
	By desperate appliance are reliev'd,
	Or not at all.
	How now! what hath befall'n?
<SPEECH 41><ACT 4><SCENE 3><67%>
	But where is he?
<SPEECH 42><ACT 4><SCENE 3><67%>
	Bring him before us.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 4><SCENE 3><67%>
	Now, Hamlet, where's Polonius?
<SPEECH 44><ACT 4><SCENE 3><67%>
	At supper! Where?
<SPEECH 45><ACT 4><SCENE 3><67%>
	Alas, alas!
<SPEECH 46><ACT 4><SCENE 3><67%>
	What dost thou mean by this?
<SPEECH 47><ACT 4><SCENE 3><67%>
	Where is Polonius?
<SPEECH 48><ACT 4><SCENE 3><67%>
	</STAGE DIR> Go seek him there.
<SPEECH 49><ACT 4><SCENE 3><68%>
	Hamlet, this deed, for thine especial safety,
	Which we do tender, as we dearly grieve
	For that which thou hast done, must send thee hence
	With fiery quickness: therefore prepare thyself;
	The bark is ready, and the wind at help,
	The associates tend, and every thing is bent
	For England.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 4><SCENE 3><68%>
	Ay, Hamlet.
<SPEECH 51><ACT 4><SCENE 3><68%>
	So is it, if thou knew'st our purposes.
<SPEECH 52><ACT 4><SCENE 3><68%>
	Thy loving father, Hamlet.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 4><SCENE 3><68%>
	Follow him at foot; tempt him with speed aboard:
	Delay it not, I'll have him hence to-night.
	Away! for every thing is seal'd and done
	That else leans on the affair: pray you, make haste.
	And, England, if my love thou hold'st at aught,—
	As my great power thereof may give thee sense,
	Since yet thy cicatrice looks raw and red
	After the Danish sword, and thy free awe
	Pays homage to us,—thou mayst not coldly set
	Our sovereign process, which imports at full,
	By letters conjuring to that effect,
	The present death of Hamlet. Do it, England;
	For like the hectic in my blood he rages,
	And thou must cure me. Till I know 'tis done,
	Howe'er my haps, my joys were ne'er begun.
<SPEECH 54><ACT 4><SCENE 5><71%>
	How do you, pretty lady?
<SPEECH 55><ACT 4><SCENE 5><71%>
	Conceit upon her father.
<SPEECH 56><ACT 4><SCENE 5><71%>
	Pretty Ophelia!
<SPEECH 57><ACT 4><SCENE 5><72%>
	How long hath she been thus?
<SPEECH 58><ACT 4><SCENE 5><72%>
	Follow her close; give her good watch, I pray you.
	O! this is the poison of deep grief; it springs
	All from her father's death. O Gertrude, Gertrude!
	When sorrows come, they come not single spies,
	But in battalions. First, her father slain;
	Next, your son gone; but he most violent author
	Of his own just remove: the people muddied,
	Thick and unwholesome in their thoughts and whispers,
	For good Polonius' death; and we have done but greenly,
	In hugger-mugger to inter him: poor Ophelia
	Divided from herself and her fair judgment,
	Without the which we are pictures, or mere beasts:
	Last, and as much containing as all these,
	Her brother is in secret come from France,
	Feeds on his wonder, keeps himself in clouds,
	And wants not buzzers to infect his ear
	With pestilent speeches of his father's death;
	Wherein necessity, of matter beggar'd,
	Will nothing stick our person to arraign
	In ear and ear. O my dear Gertrude! this,
	Like to a murdering-piece, in many places
	Gives me superfluous death.
<SPEECH 59><ACT 4><SCENE 5><72%>
	Where are my Switzers? Let them guard the door.
	What is the matter?
<SPEECH 60><ACT 4><SCENE 5><73%>
	The doors are broke.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 4><SCENE 5><73%>
	What is the cause, Laertes,
	That thy rebellion looks so giant-like?
	Let him go, Gertrude; do not fear our person:
	There's such divinity doth hedge a king,
	That treason can but peep to what it would,
	Acts little of his will. Tell me, Laertes,
	Why thou art thus incens'd. Let him go, Gertrude.
	Speak, man.
<SPEECH 62><ACT 4><SCENE 5><73%>
	Dead.
<SPEECH 63><ACT 4><SCENE 5><73%>
	Let him demand his fill.
<SPEECH 64><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	Who shall stay you?
<SPEECH 65><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	Good Laertes,
	If you desire to know the certainty
	Of your dear father's death, is't writ in your revenge,
	That, swoopstake, you will draw both friend and foe,
	Winner and loser?
<SPEECH 66><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	Will you know them then?
<SPEECH 67><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	Why, now you speak
	Like a good child and a true gentleman.
	That I am guiltless of your father's death,
	And am most sensibly in grief for it,
	It shall as level to your judgment pierce
	As day does to your eye.
<SPEECH 68><ACT 4><SCENE 5><75%>
	Laertes, I must common with your grief,
	Or you deny me right. Go but apart,
	Make choice of whom your wisest friends you will,
	And they shall hear and judge 'twixt you and me.
	If by direct or by collateral hand
	They find us touch'd, we will our kingdom give,
	Our crown, our life, and all that we call ours,
	To you in satisfaction; but if not,
	Be you content to lend your patience to us,
	And we shall jointly labour with your soul
	To give it due content.
<SPEECH 69><ACT 4><SCENE 5><75%>
	So you shall;
	And where the offence is let the great axe fall.
	I pray you go with me.
<SPEECH 70><ACT 4><SCENE 7><77%>
	Now must your conscience my acquittance seal,
	And you must put me in your heart for friend,
	Sith you have heard, and with a knowing ear,
	That he which hath your noble father slain
	Pursu'd my life.
<SPEECH 71><ACT 4><SCENE 7><77%>
	O! for two special reasons;
	Which may to you, perhaps, seem much unsinew'd,
	But yet to me they are strong. The queen his mother
	Lives almost by his looks, and for myself,—
	My virtue or my plague, be it either which,—
	She's so conjunctive to my life and soul,
	That, as the star moves not but in his sphere,
	I could not but by her. The other motive,
	Why to a public count I might not go,
	Is the great love the general gender bear him;
	Who, dipping all his faults in their affection,
	Would, like the spring that turneth wood to stone,
	Convert his gyves to graces; so that my arrows,
	Too slightly timber'd for so loud a wind,
	Would have reverted to my bow again,
	And not where I had aim'd them.
<SPEECH 72><ACT 4><SCENE 7><77%>
	Break not your sleeps for that; you must not think
	That we are made of stuff so flat and dull
	That we can let our beard be shook with danger
	And think it pastime. You shortly shall hear more;
	I lov'd your father, and we love ourself,
	And that, I hope, will teach you to imagine,—
	How now! what news?
<SPEECH 73><ACT 4><SCENE 7><77%>
	From Hamlet! who brought them?
<SPEECH 74><ACT 4><SCENE 7><78%>
	Laertes, you shall hear them.
	Leave us.
	High and mighty, you shall know I am set naked on your kingdom. To-morrow shall I beg leave to see your kingly eyes; when I shall, first asking your pardon thereunto, recount the occasions of my sudden and more strange return
	<HAMLET.>What should this mean? Are all the rest come back?
	Or is it some abuse and no such thing?
<SPEECH 75><ACT 4><SCENE 7><78%>
	'Tis Hamlet's character. 'Naked,'
	And in a postscript here, he says, 'alone.'
	Can you advise me?
<SPEECH 76><ACT 4><SCENE 7><78%>
	If it be so, Laertes,
	As how should it be so? how otherwise?
	Will you be rul'd by me?
<SPEECH 77><ACT 4><SCENE 7><78%>
	To thine own peace. If he be now return'd,
	As checking at his voyage, and that he means
	No more to undertake it, I will work him
	To an exploit, now ripe in my device,
	Under the which he shall not choose but fall;
	And for his death no wind of blame shall breathe,
	But even his mother shall uncharge the practice
	And call it accident.
<SPEECH 78><ACT 4><SCENE 7><78%>
	It falls right.
	You have been talk'd of since your travel much,
	And that in Hamlet's hearing, for a quality
	Wherein, they say, you shine; your sum of parts
	Did not together pluck such envy from him
	As did that one, and that, in my regard,
	Of the unworthiest siege.
<SPEECH 79><ACT 4><SCENE 7><78%>
	A very riband in the cap of youth,
	Yet needful too; for youth no less becomes
	The light and careless livery that it wears
	Than settled age his sables and his weeds,
	Importing health and graveness. Two months since
	Here was a gentleman of Normandy:
	I've seen myself, and serv'd against, the French,
	And they can well on horseback; but this gallant
	Had witchcraft in 't, he grew unto his seat,
	And to such wondrous doing brought his horse,
	As he had been incorps'd and demi-natur'd
	With the brave beast; so far he topp'd my thought,
	That I, in forgery of shapes and tricks,
	Come short of what he did.
<SPEECH 80><ACT 4><SCENE 7><79%>
	A Norman.
<SPEECH 81><ACT 4><SCENE 7><79%>
	The very same.
<SPEECH 82><ACT 4><SCENE 7><79%>
	He made confession of you,
	And gave you such a masterly report
	For art and exercise in your defence,
	And for your rapier most especially,
	That he cried out, 'twould be a sight indeed
	If one could match you; the scrimers of their nation,
	He swore, had neither motion, guard, nor eye,
	If you oppos'd them. Sir, this report of his
	Did Hamlet so envenom with his envy
	That he could nothing do but wish and beg
	Your sudden coming o'er, to play with him.
	Now, out of this,—
<SPEECH 83><ACT 4><SCENE 7><79%>
	Laertes, was your father dear to you?
	Or are you like the painting of a sorrow,
	A face without a heart?
<SPEECH 84><ACT 4><SCENE 7><79%>
	Not that I think you did not love your father,
	But that I know love is begun by time,
	And that I see, in passages of proof,
	Time qualifies the spark and fire of it.
	There lives within the very flame of love
	A kind of wick or snuff that will abate it,
	And nothing is at a like goodness still,
	For goodness, growing to a plurisy,
	Dies in his own too-much. That we would do,
	We should do when we would, for this 'would' changes,
	And hath abatements and delays as many
	As there are tongues, are hands, are accidents;
	And then this 'should' is like a spendthrift sigh,
	That hurts by easing. But, to the quick o' the ulcer;
	Hamlet comes back; what would you undertake
	To show yourself your father's son in deed
	More than in words?
<SPEECH 85><ACT 4><SCENE 7><80%>
	No place, indeed, should murder sanctuarize;
	Revenge should have no bounds. But, good Laertes,
	Will you do this, keep close within your chamber.
	Hamlet return'd shall know you are come home;
	We'll put on those shall praise your excellence,
	And set a double varnish on the fame
	The Frenchman gave you, bring you, in fine, together,
	And wager on your heads: he, being remise,
	Most generous and free from all contriving,
	Will not peruse the foils; so that, with ease
	Or with a little shuffling, you may choose
	A sword unbated, and, in a pass of practice
	Requite him for your father.
<SPEECH 86><ACT 4><SCENE 7><80%>
	Let's further think of this;
	Weigh what convenience both of time and means
	May fit us to our shape. If this should fail,
	And that our drift look through our bad performance
	'Twere better not assay'd; therefore this project
	Should have a back or second, that might hold,
	If this should blast in proof. Soft! let me see;
	We'll make a solemn wager on your cunnings:
	I ha't:
	When in your motion you are hot and dry,—
	As make your bouts more violent to that end,—
	And that he calls for drink, I'll have prepar'd him
	A chalice for the nonce, whereon but sipping,
	If he by chance escape your venom'd stuck,
	Our purpose may hold there. But stay! what noise?
	How now, sweet queen!
<SPEECH 87><ACT 4><SCENE 7><81%>
	Let's follow, Gertrude.
	How much I had to do to calm his rage!
	Now fear I this will give it start again;
	Therefore let's follow.
<SPEECH 88><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	Pluck them asunder.
<SPEECH 89><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	O! he is mad, Laertes.
<SPEECH 90><ACT 5><SCENE 1><89%>
	I pray you, good Horatio, wait upon him.
	</STAGE DIR> Strengthen your patience in our last night's speech;
	We'll put the matter to the present push.
	Good Gertrude, set some watch over your son.
	This grave shall have a living monument:
	An hour of quiet shortly shall we see;
	Till then, in patience our proceeding be.
<SPEECH 91><ACT 5><SCENE 2><95%>
	Come, Hamlet, come, and take this hand from me.
<SPEECH 92><ACT 5><SCENE 2><96%>
	Give them the foils, young Osric. Cousin Hamlet,
	You know the wager?
<SPEECH 93><ACT 5><SCENE 2><96%>
	I do not fear it; I have seen you both;
	But since he is better'd, we have therefore odds.
<SPEECH 94><ACT 5><SCENE 2><96%>
	Set me the stoups of wine upon that table.
	If Hamlet give the first or second hit,
	Or quit in answer of the third exchange,
	Let all the battlements their ordnance fire;
	The king shall drink to Hamlet's better breath;
	And in the cup an union shall he throw,
	Richer than that which four successive kings
	In Denmark's crown have worn. Give me the cups;
	And let the kettle to the trumpet speak,
	The trumpet to the cannoneer without,
	The cannons to the heavens, the heavens to earth,
	'Now the king drinks to Hamlet!' Come, begin;
	And you, the judges, bear a wary eye.
<SPEECH 95><ACT 5><SCENE 2><96%>
	Stay; give me drink. Hamlet, this pearl is thine;
	Here's to thy health. Give him the cup.
<SPEECH 96><ACT 5><SCENE 2><97%>
	Our son shall win.
<SPEECH 97><ACT 5><SCENE 2><97%>
	Gertrude, do not drink.
<SPEECH 98><ACT 5><SCENE 2><97%>
	</STAGE DIR> It is the poison'd cup! it is too late.
<SPEECH 99><ACT 5><SCENE 2><97%>
	I do not think 't
<SPEECH 100><ACT 5><SCENE 2><97%>
	Part them! they are incens'd
<SPEECH 101><ACT 5><SCENE 2><97%>
	She swounds to see them bleed.
<SPEECH 102><ACT 5><SCENE 2><98%>
	O! yet defend me, friends; I am but hurt.
