<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 2><6%>
	Dread my lord,
	Your leave and favour to return to France;
	From whence though willingly I came to Denmark,
	To show my duty in your coronation,
	Yet now, I must confess, that duty done,
	My thoughts and wishes bend again toward France
	And bow them to your gracious leave and pardon.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 3><11%>
	My necessaries are embark'd; farewell:
	And, sister, as the winds give benefit
	And convoy is assistant, do not sleep,
	But let me hear from you.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 3><12%>
	For Hamlet, and the trifling of his favour,
	Hold it a fashion and a toy in blood,
	A violet in the youth of primy nature,
	Forward, not permanent, sweet, not lasting,
	The perfume and suppliance of a minute;
	No more.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 3><12%>
	Think it no more:
	For nature, crescent, does not grow alone
	In thews and bulk; but, as this temple waxes,
	The inward service of the mind and soul
	Grows wide withal. Perhaps he loves you now,
	And now no soil nor cautel doth besmirch
	The virtue of his will; but you must fear,
	His greatness weigh'd, his will is not his own,
	For he himself is subject to his birth;
	He may not, as unvalu'd persons do,
	Carve for himself, for on his choice depends
	The safety and the health of the whole state;
	And therefore must his choice be circumscrib'd
	Unto the voice and yielding of that body
	Whereof he is the head. Then if he says he loves you,
	It fits your wisdom so far to believe it
	As he in his particular act and place
	May give his saying deed; which is no further
	Than the main voice of Denmark goes withal.
	Then weigh what loss your honour may sustain,
	If with too credent ear you list his songs,
	Or lose your heart, or your chaste treasure open
	To his unmaster'd importunity.
	Fear it, Ophelia, fear it, my dear sister;
	And keep you in the rear of your affection,
	Out of the shot and danger of desire.
	The chariest maid is prodigal enough
	If she unmask her beauty to the moon;
	Virtue herself 'scapes not calumnious strokes;
	The canker galls the infants of the spring
	Too oft before their buttons be disclos'd,
	And in the morn and liquid dew of youth
	Contagious blastments are most imminent.
	Be wary then; best safety lies in fear:
	Youth to itself rebels, though none else near.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 3><13%>
	O! fear me not.
	I stay too long; but here my father comes.
	A double blessing is a double grace;
	Occasion smiles upon a second leave.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 3><13%>
	Most humbly do I take my leave, my lord.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 3><13%>
	Farewell, Ophelia; and remember well
	What I have said to you.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 3><14%>
	Farewell.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 4><SCENE 5><73%>
	Where is the king? Sirs, stand you all without.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 4><SCENE 5><73%>
	I pray you, give me leave.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 4><SCENE 5><73%>
	I thank you: keep the door. O thou vile king!
	Give me my father.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 4><SCENE 5><73%>
	That drop of blood that's calm proclaims me bastard,
	Cries cuckold to my father, brands the harlot
	Even here, between the chaste unsmirched brow
	Of my true mother.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 4><SCENE 5><73%>
	Where is my father?
<SPEECH 14><ACT 4><SCENE 5><73%>
	How came he dead? I'll not be juggled with.
	To hell, allegiance! vows, to the blackest devil!
	Conscience and grace, to the profoundest pit!
	I dare damnation. To this point I stand,
	That both the worlds I give to negligence,
	Let come what comes; only I'll be reveng'd
	Most throughly for my father.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	My will, not all the world:
	And, for my means, I'll husband them so well,
	They shall go far with little.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	None but his enemies.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	To his good friends thus wide I'll ope my arms;
	And like the kind life-rendering pelican,
	Repast them with my blood.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	How now! what noise is that?
	O heat, dry up my brains! tears seven times salt,
	Burn out the sense and virtue of mine eye;
	By heaven, thy madness shall be paid by weight,
	Till our scale turn the beam. O rose of May!
	Dear maid, kind sister, sweet Ophelia!
	O heavens! is't possible a young maid's wits
	Should be as mortal as an old man's life?
	Nature is fine in love, and where 'tis fine
	It sends some precious instance of itself
	After the thing it loves.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	Hadst thou thy wits, and didst persuade revenge,
	It could not move thus.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	This nothing's more than matter.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 4><SCENE 5><75%>
	A document in madness, thoughts and remembrance fitted.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 4><SCENE 5><75%>
	Thought and affliction, passion, hell itself,
	She turns to favour and to prettiness.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 4><SCENE 5><75%>
	Do you see this, O God?
<SPEECH 24><ACT 4><SCENE 5><75%>
	Let this be so:
	His means of death, his obscure burial,
	No trophy, sword, nor hatchment o'er his bones,
	No noble rite nor formal ostentation,
	Cry to be heard, as 'twere from heaven to earth,
	That I must call 't in question.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 4><SCENE 7><77%>
	It well appears: but tell me
	Why you proceeded not against these feats,
	So crimeful and so capital in nature,
	As by your safety, wisdom, all things else,
	You mainly were stirr'd up.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 4><SCENE 7><77%>
	And so have I a noble father lost;
	A sister driven into desperate terms,
	Whose worth, if praises may go back again,
	Stood challenger on mount of all the age
	For her perfections. But my revenge will come.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 4><SCENE 7><78%>
	Know you the hand?
<SPEECH 28><ACT 4><SCENE 7><78%>
	I'm lost in it, my lord. But let him come:
	It warms the very sickness in my heart,
	That I shall live and tell him to his teeth,
	'Thus diddest thou.'
<SPEECH 29><ACT 4><SCENE 7><78%>
	Ay, my lord;
	So you will not o'er-rule me to a peace.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 4><SCENE 7><78%>
	My lord, I will be rul'd;
	The rather, if you could devise it so
	That I might be the organ.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 4><SCENE 7><78%>
	What part is that, my lord?
<SPEECH 32><ACT 4><SCENE 7><79%>
	A Norman was 't?
<SPEECH 33><ACT 4><SCENE 7><79%>
	Upon my life, Lamord.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 4><SCENE 7><79%>
	I know him well; he is the brooch indeed
	And gem of all the nation.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 4><SCENE 7><79%>
	What out of this, my lord?
<SPEECH 36><ACT 4><SCENE 7><79%>
	Why ask you this?
<SPEECH 37><ACT 4><SCENE 7><80%>
	To cut his throat i' the church.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 4><SCENE 7><80%>
	I will do 't;
	And, for that purpose, I'll anoint my sword.
	I bought an unction of a mountebank,
	So mortal that, but dip a knife in it,
	Where it draws blood no cataplasm so rare,
	Collected from all simples that have virtue
	Under the moon, can save the thing from death
	That is but scratch'd withal; I'll touch my point
	With this contagion, that, if I gall him slightly,
	It may be death.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 4><SCENE 7><81%>
	Drown'd! O, where?
<SPEECH 40><ACT 4><SCENE 7><81%>
	Alas! then, she is drown'd?
<SPEECH 41><ACT 4><SCENE 7><81%>
	Too much of water hast thou, poor Ophelis,
	And therefore I forbid my tears; but yet
	It is our trick, nature her custom holds,
	Let shame say what it will; when these are gone
	The woman will be out. Adieu, my lord!
	I have a speech of fire, that fain would blaze,
	But that this folly douts it.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	What ceremony else?
<SPEECH 43><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	What ceremony else?
<SPEECH 44><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Must there no more be done?
<SPEECH 45><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Lay her i' the earth;
	And from her fair and unpolluted flesh
	May violets spring! I tell thee, churlish priest,
	A ministering angel shall my sister be,
	When thou liest howling.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	O! treble woe
	Fall ten times treble on that cursed head
	Whose wicked deed thy most ingenious sense
	Depriv'd thee of. Hold off the earth awhile,
	Till I have caught her once more in mine arms.
	Now pile your dust upon the quick and dead,
	Till of this flat a mountain you have made,
	To o'er-top old Pelion or the skyish head
	Of blue Olympus.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	The devil take thy soul!
<SPEECH 48><ACT 5><SCENE 2><95%>
	I am satisfied in nature,
	Whose motive, in this case, should stir me most
	To my revenge; but in my terms of honour
	I stand aloof, and will no reconcilement,
	Till by some elder masters, of known honour,
	I have a voice and precedent of peace,
	To keep my name ungor'd. But till that time,
	I do receive your offer'd love like love,
	And will not wrong it.
<SPEECH 49><ACT 5><SCENE 2><96%>
	Come, one for me.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 5><SCENE 2><96%>
	You mock me, sir.
<SPEECH 51><ACT 5><SCENE 2><96%>
	This is too heavy; let me see another.
<SPEECH 52><ACT 5><SCENE 2><96%>
	Come, my lord.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 5><SCENE 2><96%>
	No.
<SPEECH 54><ACT 5><SCENE 2><96%>
	Well; again.
<SPEECH 55><ACT 5><SCENE 2><97%>
	A touch, a touch, I do confess.
<SPEECH 56><ACT 5><SCENE 2><97%>
	My lord, I'll hit him now.
<SPEECH 57><ACT 5><SCENE 2><97%>
	</STAGE DIR> And yet 'tis almost 'gainst my conscience.
<SPEECH 58><ACT 5><SCENE 2><97%>
	Say you so? come on.
<SPEECH 59><ACT 5><SCENE 2><97%>
	Have at you now.
<SPEECH 60><ACT 5><SCENE 2><97%>
	Why, as a woodcock to mine own springe, Osric;
	I am justly kill'd with mine own treachery.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 5><SCENE 2><98%>
	It is here, Hamlet. Hamlet, thou art slain;
	No medicine in the world can do thee good;
	In thee there is not half an hour of life;
	The treacherous instrument is in thy hand,
	Unbated and envenom'd. The foul practice
	Hath turn'd itself on me; lo! here I lie,
	Never to rise again. Thy mother's poison'd.
	I can no more. The king, the king's to blame.
<SPEECH 62><ACT 5><SCENE 2><98%>
	He is justly serv'd;
	It is a poison temper'd by himself.
	Exchange forgiveness with me, noble Hamlet:
	Mine and my father's death come not upon thee,
	Nor thine on me!
