<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 3><5%>
	So foul and fair a day I have not seen.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 3><6%>
	Speak, if you can: what are you?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 3><7%>
	Stay, you imperfect speakers, tell me more:
	By Sinel's death I know I am Thane of Glamis;
	But how of Cawdor? the Thane of Cawdor lives,
	A prosperous gentleman; and to be king
	Stands not within the prospect of belief
	No more than to be Cawdor. Say, from whence
	You owe this strange intelligence? or why
	Upon this blasted heath you stop our way
	With such prophetic greeting? Speak, I charge you.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 3><7%>
	Into the air, and what seem'd corporal melted
	As breath into the wind. Would they had stay'd!
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 3><8%>
	Your children shall be kings.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 3><8%>
	And Thane of Cawdor too; went it not so?
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 3><9%>
	The Thane of Cawdor lives: why do you dress me
	In borrow'd robes?
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 3><9%>
	</STAGE DIR> Glamis, and Thane of Cawdor:
	The greatest is behind. <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> Thanks for your pains.
	</STAGE DIR> Do you not hope your children shall be kings,
	When those that gave the Thane of Cawdor to me
	Promis'd no less to them?
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 3><9%>
	</STAGE DIR> Two truths are told,
	As happy prologues to the swelling act
	Of the imperial theme. I thank you, gentlemen.
	</STAGE DIR> This supernatural soliciting
	Cannot be ill, cannot be good; if ill,
	Why hath it given me earnest of success,
	Commencing in a truth? I am Thane of Cawdor:
	If good, why do I yield to that suggestion
	Whose horrid image doth unfix my hair
	And make my seated heart knock at my ribs,
	Against the use of nature? Present fears
	Are less than horrible imaginings;
	My thought, whose murder yet is but fantastical,
	Shakes so my single state of man that function
	Is smother'd in surmise, and nothing is
	But what is not.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 3><10%>
	</STAGE DIR> If chance will have me king, why, chance may crown me,
	Without my stir.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 3><10%>
	</STAGE DIR> Come what come may,
	Time and the hour runs through the roughest day.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 3><11%>
	Give me your favour: my dull brain was wrought
	With things forgotten. Kind gentlemen, your pains
	Are register'd where every day I turn
	The leaf to read them. Let us toward the king.
	Think upon what hath chanc'd; and, at more time,
	The interim having weigh'd it, let us speak
	Our free hearts each to other.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 1><SCENE 3><11%>
	Till then, enough. Come, friends.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 1><SCENE 4><12%>
	The service and the loyalty I owe,
	In doing it, pays itself. Your highness' part
	Is to receive our duties: and our duties
	Are to your throne and state, children and servants;
	Which do but what they should, by doing everything
	Safe toward your love and honour.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 1><SCENE 4><13%>
	The rest is labour, which is not us'd for you:
	I'll be myself the harbinger, and make joyful
	The hearing of my wife with your approach;
	So, humbly take my leave.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 1><SCENE 4><13%>
	</STAGE DIR> The Prince of Cumberland! that is a step
	On which I must fall down, or else o'er-leap,
	For in my way it lies. Stars, hide your fires!
	Let not light see my black and deep desires;
	The eye wink at the hand; yet let that be
	Which the eye fears, when it is done, to see.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 1><SCENE 5><16%>
	My dearest love,
	Duncan comes here to-night.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 1><SCENE 5><16%>
	To-morrow, as he purposes.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 1><SCENE 5><17%>
	We will speak further.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 1><SCENE 7><19%>
	If it were done when 'tis done, then 'twere well
	It were done quickly; if the assassination
	Could trammel up the consequence, and catch
	With his surcease success; that but this blow
	Might be the be-all and the end-all here,
	But here, upon this bank and shoal of time,
	We'd jump the life to come. But in these cases
	We still have judgment here; that we but teach
	Bloody instructions, which, being taught, return
	To plague the inventor; this even-handed justice
	Commends the ingredients of our poison'd chalice
	To our own lips. He's here in double trust:
	First, as I am his kinsman and his subject,
	Strong both against the deed; then, as his host,
	Who should against his murderer shut the door,
	Not bear the knife myself. Besides, this Duncan
	Hath borne his faculties so meek, hath been
	So clear in his great office, that his virtues
	Will plead like angels trumpet-tongu'd against
	The deep damnation of his taking-off;
	And pity, like a naked new-born babe,
	Striding the blast, or heaven's cherubin, hors'd
	Upon the sightless couriers of the air,
	Shall blow the horrid deed in every eye,
	That tears shall drown the wind. I have no spur
	To prick the sides of my intent, but only
	Vaulting ambition, which o'er-leaps itself
	And falls on the other.—
	How now! what news?
<SPEECH 21><ACT 1><SCENE 7><20%>
	Hath he ask'd for me?
<SPEECH 22><ACT 1><SCENE 7><20%>
	We will proceed no further in this business:
	He hath honour'd me of late; and I have bought
	Golden opinions from all sorts of people,
	Which would be worn now in their newest gloss,
	Not cast aside so soon.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 1><SCENE 7><21%>
	Prithee, peace.
	I dare do all that may become a man;
	Who dares do more is none.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 1><SCENE 7><21%>
	If we should fail,—
<SPEECH 25><ACT 1><SCENE 7><22%>
	Bring forth men-children only;
	For thy undaunted mettle should compose
	Nothing but males. Will it not be receiv'd,
	When we have mark'd with blood those sleepy two
	Of his own chamber and us'd their very daggers,
	That they have done't?
<SPEECH 26><ACT 1><SCENE 7><22%>
	I am settled, and bend up
	Each corporal agent to this terrible feat.
	Away, and mock the time with fairest show:
	False face must hide what the false heart doth know.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	A friend.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	Being unprepar'd,
	Our will became the servant to defect,
	Which else should free have wrought.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	I think not of them:
	Yet, when we can entreat an hour to serve,
	We would spend it in some words upon that business,
	If you would grant the time.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	If you shall cleave to my consent, when 'tis,
	It shall make honour for you.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	Good repose the while!
<SPEECH 32><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	Go bid thy mistress, when my drink is ready
	She strike upon the bell. Get thee to bed.
	Is this a dagger which I see before me,
	The handle toward my hand? Come, let me clutch thee:
	I have thee not, and yet I see thee still.
	Art thou not, fatal vision, sensible
	To feeling as to sight? or art thou but
	A dagger of the mind, a false creation,
	Proceeding from the heat-oppressed brain?
	I see thee yet, in form as palpable
	As this which now I draw.
	Thou marshall'st me the way that I was going;
	And such an instrument I was to use.
	Mine eyes are made the fools o' the other senses,
	Or else worth all the rest: I see thee still;
	And on thy blade and dudgeon gouts of blood,
	Which was not so before. There's no such thing:
	It is the bloody business which informs
	Thus to mine eyes. Now o'er the one half-world
	Nature seems dead, and wicked dreams abuse
	The curtain'd sleep; witchcraft celebrates
	Pale Hecate's offerings; and wither'd murder,
	Alarum'd by his sentinel, the wolf,
	Whose howl's his watch, thus with his stealthy pace,
	With Tarquin's ravishing strides, toward his design
	Moves like a ghost. Thou sure and firm-set earth,
	Hear not my steps, which way they walk, for fear
	Thy very stones prate of my whereabout,
	And take the present horror from the time,
	Which now suits with it. Whiles I threat he lives:
	Words to the heat of deeds too cold breath gives.
	I go, and it is done; the bell invites me.
	Hear it not, Duncan; for it is a knell
	That summons thee to heaven or to hell.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 2><SCENE 2><26%>
	</STAGE DIR> Who's there? what, ho!
<SPEECH 34><ACT 2><SCENE 2><26%>
	I have done the deed. Didst thou not hear a noise?
<SPEECH 35><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	When?
<SPEECH 36><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	As I descended?
<SPEECH 37><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	Hark!
	Who lies i' the second chamber?
<SPEECH 38><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	</STAGE DIR> This is a sorry sight.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	There's one did laugh in 's sleep, and one cried 'Murder!'
	That they did wake each other: I stood and heard them;
	But they did say their prayers, and address'd them
	Again to sleep.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	One cried 'God bless us!' and 'Amen' the other:
	As they had seen me with these hangman's hands.
	Listening their fear, I could not say 'Amen,'
	When they did say 'God bless us!'
<SPEECH 41><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	But wherefore could not I pronounce 'Amen?'
	I had most need of blessing, and 'Amen'
	Stuck in my throat.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	Methought I heard a voice cry 'Sleep no more!
	Macbeth does murder sleep,' the innocent sleep,
	Sleep that knits up the ravell'd sleave of care,
	The death of each day's life, sore labour's bath,
	Balm of hurt minds, great nature's second course,
	Chief nourisher in life's feast,—
<SPEECH 43><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	Still it cried, 'Sleep no more!' to all the house:
	'Glamis hath murder'd sleep, and therefore Cawdor
	Shall sleep no more, Macbeth shall sleep no more!'
<SPEECH 44><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	I'll go no more:
	I am afraid to think what I have done;
	Look on 't again I dare not.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	Whence is that knocking?
	How is't with me, when every noise appals me?
	What hands are here! Ha! they pluck out mine eyes.
	Will all great Neptune's ocean wash this blood
	Clean from my hand? No, this my hand will rather
	The multitudinous seas incarnadine,
	Making the green one red.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	To know my deed 'twere best not know myself.
	Wake Duncan with thy knocking! I would thou couldst!
<SPEECH 47><ACT 2><SCENE 3><32%>
	Good morrow, both.
<SPEECH 48><ACT 2><SCENE 3><32%>
	Not yet.
<SPEECH 49><ACT 2><SCENE 3><32%>
	I'll bring you to him.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 2><SCENE 3><32%>
	The labour we delight in physics pain.
	This is the door.
<SPEECH 51><ACT 2><SCENE 3><32%>
	He does: he did appoint so.
<SPEECH 52><ACT 2><SCENE 3><33%>
	'Twas a rough night.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 2><SCENE 3><33%>
	What's the matter?
<SPEECH 54><ACT 2><SCENE 3><33%>
	What is 't you say? the life?
<SPEECH 55><ACT 2><SCENE 3><34%>
	Had I but died an hour before this chance
	I had liv'd a blessed time; for, from this instant,
	There's nothing serious in mortality,
	All is but toys; renown and grace is dead,
	The wine of life is drawn, and the mere lees
	Is left this vault to brag of.
<SPEECH 56><ACT 2><SCENE 3><34%>
	You are, and do not know 't:
	The spring, the head, the fountain of your blood
	Is stopp'd; the very source of it is stopp'd.
<SPEECH 57><ACT 2><SCENE 3><35%>
	O! yet I do repent me of my fury,
	That I did kill them.
<SPEECH 58><ACT 2><SCENE 3><35%>
	Who can be wise, amaz'd, temperate and furious,
	Loyal and neutral, in a moment? No man:
	The expedition of my violent love
	Outran the pauser, reason. Here lay Duncan,
	His silver skin lac'd with his golden blood;
	And his gash'd stabs look'd like a breach in nature
	For ruin's wasteful entrance: there, the murderers,
	Steep'd in the colours of their trade, their daggers
	Unmannerly breech'd with gore: who could refrain,
	That had a heart to love, and in that heart
	Courage to make 's love known?
<SPEECH 59><ACT 2><SCENE 3><36%>
	Let's briefly put on manly readiness,
	And meet i' the hall together.
<SPEECH 60><ACT 3><SCENE 1><40%>
	Here's our chief guest.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 3><SCENE 1><40%>
	To-night we hold a solemn supper, sir,
	And I'll request your presence.
<SPEECH 62><ACT 3><SCENE 1><40%>
	Ride you this afternoon?
<SPEECH 63><ACT 3><SCENE 1><40%>
	We should have else desir'd your good advice—
	Which still hath been both grave and prosperous—
	In this day's council; but we'll take to-morrow.
	Is 't far you ride?
<SPEECH 64><ACT 3><SCENE 1><40%>
	Fail not our feast.
<SPEECH 65><ACT 3><SCENE 1><40%>
	We hear our bloody cousins are bestow'd
	In England and in Ireland, not confessing
	Their cruel parricide, filling their hearers
	With strange invention; but of that to-morrow,
	When therewithal we shall have cause of state
	Craving us jointly. Hie you to horse; adieu
	Till you return at night. Goes Fleance with you?
<SPEECH 66><ACT 3><SCENE 1><41%>
	I wish your horses swift and sure of foot;
	And so I do commend you to their backs.
	Farewell.
	Let every man be master of his time
	Till seven at night; to make society
	The sweeter welcome, we will keep ourself
	Till supper-time alone; while then, God be with you!
	Sirrah, a word with you. Attend those men
	Our pleasure?
<SPEECH 67><ACT 3><SCENE 1><41%>
	Bring them before us. <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> To be thus is nothing;
	But to be safely thus. Our fears in Banquo
	Stick deep, and in his royalty of nature
	Reigns that which would be fear'd: 'tis much he dares,
	And, to that dauntless temper of his mind,
	He hath a wisdom that doth guide his valour
	To act in safety. There is none but he
	Whose being I do fear; and under him
	My genius is rebuk'd, as it is said
	Mark Antony's was by Cæsar. He chid the sisters
	When first they put the name of king upon me,
	And bade them speak to him; then, prophet-like,
	They hail'd him father to a line of kings.
	Upon my head they plac'd a fruitless crown,
	And put a barren sceptre in my gripe,
	Thence to be wrench'd with an unlineal hand,
	No son of mine succeeding. If 't be so,
	For Banquo's issue have I fil'd my mind;
	For them the gracious Duncan have I murder'd;
	Put rancours in the vessel of my peace
	Only for them; and mine eternal jewel
	Given to the common enemy of man,
	To make them kings, the seed of Banquo kings!
	Rather than so, come fate into the list,
	And champion me to the utterance! Who's there?
	Now go to the door, and stay there till we call.
	Was it not yesterday we spoke together?
<SPEECH 68><ACT 3><SCENE 1><43%>
	Well then, now
	Have you consider'd of my speeches? Know
	That it was he in the times past which held you
	So under fortune, which you thought had been
	Our innocent self. This I made good to you
	In our last conference, pass'd in probation with you,
	How you were borne in hand, how cross'd, the instruments,
	Who wrought with them, and all things else that might
	To half a soul and to a notion craz'd
	Say, 'Thus did Banquo.'
<SPEECH 69><ACT 3><SCENE 1><43%>
	I did so; and went further, which is now
	Our point of second meeting. Do you find
	Your patience so predominant in your nature
	That you can let this go? Are you so gospell'd
	To pray for this good man and for his issue,
	Whose heavy hand hath bow'd you to the grave
	And beggar'd yours for ever?
<SPEECH 70><ACT 3><SCENE 1><43%>
	Ay, in the catalogue ye go for men;
	As hounds and greyhounds, mongrels, spaniels, curs,
	Shoughs, water-rugs, and demi-wolves, are clept
	All by the name of dogs: the valu'd file
	Distinguishes the swift, the slow, the subtle,
	The housekeeper, the hunter, every one
	According to the gift which bounteous nature
	Hath in him clos'd; whereby he does receive
	Particular addition, from the bill
	That writes them all alike: and so of men.
	Now, if you have a station in the file,
	Not i' the worst rank of manhood, say it;
	And I will put that business in your bosoms,
	Whose execution takes your enemy off,
	Grapples you to the heart and love of us,
	Who wear our health but sickly in his life,
	Which in his death were perfect.
<SPEECH 71><ACT 3><SCENE 1><44%>
	Both of you
	Know Banquo was your enemy.
<SPEECH 72><ACT 3><SCENE 1><44%>
	So is he mine; and in such bloody distance
	That every minute of his being thrusts
	Against my near'st of life: and though I could
	With bare-fac'd power sweep him from my sight
	And bid my will avouch it, yet I must not,
	For certain friends that are both his and mine,
	Whose loves I may not drop, but wail his fall
	Whom I myself struck down; and thence it is
	That I to your assistance do make love,
	Masking the business from the common eye
	For sundry weighty reasons.
<SPEECH 73><ACT 3><SCENE 1><45%>
	Your spirits shine through you. Within this hour at most
	I will advise you where to plant yourselves,
	Acquaint you with the perfect spy o' the time,
	The moment on 't; for 't must be done to-night,
	And something from the palace; always thought
	That I require a clearness: and with him—
	To leave no rubs nor botches in the work—
	Fleance his son, that keeps him company,
	Whose absence is no less material to me
	Than is his father's, must embrace the fate
	Of that dark hour. Resolve yourselves apart;
	I'll come to you anon.
<SPEECH 74><ACT 3><SCENE 1><45%>
	I'll call upon you straight: abide within.
	It is concluded: Banquo, thy soul's flight,
	If it find heaven, must find it out to-night.
<SPEECH 75><ACT 3><SCENE 2><46%>
	We have scotch'd the snake, not kill'd it:
	She'll close and be herself, whilst our poor malice
	Remains in danger of her former tooth.
	But let the frame of things disjoint, both the worlds suffer,
	Ere we will eat our meal in fear, and sleep
	In the affliction of these terrible dreams
	That shake us nightly. Better be with the dead,
	Whom we, to gain our peace, have sent to peace,
	Than on the torture of the mind to lie
	In restless ecstasy. Duncan is in his grave;
	After life's fitful fever he sleeps well;
	Treason has done his worst: nor steel, nor poison,
	Malice domestic, foreign levy, nothing
	Can touch him further.
<SPEECH 76><ACT 3><SCENE 2><47%>
	So shall I, love; and so, I pray, be you.
	Let your remembrance apply to Banquo;
	Present him eminence, both with eye and tongue:
	Unsafe the while, that we
	Must lave our honours in these flattering streams,
	And make our faces vizards to our hearts,
	Disguising what they are.
<SPEECH 77><ACT 3><SCENE 2><47%>
	O! full of scorpions is my mind, dear wife;
	Thou know'st that Banquo and his Fleance lives.
<SPEECH 78><ACT 3><SCENE 2><47%>
	There's comfort yet; they are assailable;
	Then be thou jocund. Ere the bat hath flown
	His cloister'd flight, ere, to black Hecate's summons
	The shard-borne beetle with his drowsy hums
	Hath rung night's yawning peal, there shall be done
	A deed of dreadful note.
<SPEECH 79><ACT 3><SCENE 2><48%>
	Be innocent of the knowledge, dearest chuck,
	Till thou applaud the deed. Come, seeling night,
	Scarf up the tender eye of pitiful day,
	And with thy bloody and invisible hand
	Cancel and tear to pieces that great bond
	Which keeps me pale! Light thickens, and the crow
	Makes wing to the rooky wood;
	Good things of day begin to droop and drowse,
	Whiles night's black agents to their preys do rouse.
	Thou marvell'st at my words: but hold thee still;
	Things bad begun make strong themselves by ill:
	So, prithee, go with me.
<SPEECH 80><ACT 3><SCENE 4><50%>
	You know your own degrees; sit down: at first and last,
	The hearty welcome.
<SPEECH 81><ACT 3><SCENE 4><50%>
	Ourself will mingle with society
	And play the humble host.
	Our hostess keeps her state, but in best time
	We will require her welcome.
<SPEECH 82><ACT 3><SCENE 4><50%>
	See, they encounter thee with their hearts' thanks;
	Both sides are even: here I'll sit i' the midst:
	Be large in mirth; anon, we'll drink a measure
	The table round. <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> There's blood upon thy face.
<SPEECH 83><ACT 3><SCENE 4><51%>
	'Tis better thee without than he within.
	Is he dispatch'd?
<SPEECH 84><ACT 3><SCENE 4><51%>
	Thou art the best o' the cut-throats; yet he's good
	That did the like for Fleance: if thou didst it,
	Thou art the nonpareil.
<SPEECH 85><ACT 3><SCENE 4><51%>
	Then comes my fit again: I had else been perfect;
	Whole as the marble, founded as the rock,
	As broad and general as the casing air:
	But now I am cabin'd, cribb'd, confin'd, bound in
	To saucy doubts and fears. But Banquo's safe?
<SPEECH 86><ACT 3><SCENE 4><51%>
	Thanks for that.
	There the grown serpent lies: the worm that's fled
	Hath nature that in time will venom breed,
	No teeth for the present. Get thee gone; to-morrow
	We'll hear ourselves again.
<SPEECH 87><ACT 3><SCENE 4><52%>
	Sweet remembrancer!
	Now good digestion wait on appetite,
	And health on both!
<SPEECH 88><ACT 3><SCENE 4><52%>
	Here had we now our country's honour roof'd,
	Were the grac'd person of our Banquo present;
	Who may I rather challenge for unkindness
	Than pity for mischance!
<SPEECH 89><ACT 3><SCENE 4><52%>
	The table's full.
<SPEECH 90><ACT 3><SCENE 4><52%>
	Where?
<SPEECH 91><ACT 3><SCENE 4><52%>
	Which of you have done this?
<SPEECH 92><ACT 3><SCENE 4><52%>
	Thou canst not say I did it: never shake
	Thy gory locks at me.
<SPEECH 93><ACT 3><SCENE 4><53%>
	Ay, and a bold one, that dare look on that
	Which might appal the devil.
<SPEECH 94><ACT 3><SCENE 4><53%>
	Prithee, see there! behold! look! lo! how say you?
	Why, what care I? If thou canst nod, speak too.
	If charnel-houses and our graves must send
	Those that we bury back, our monuments
	Shall be the maws of kites.
<SPEECH 95><ACT 3><SCENE 4><53%>
	If I stand here, I saw him.
<SPEECH 96><ACT 3><SCENE 4><53%>
	Blood hath been shed ere now, i' the olden time,
	Ere human statute purg'd the gentle weal;
	Ay, and since too, murders have been perform'd
	Too terrible for the ear: the times have been,
	That, when the brains were out, the man would die,
	And there an end; but now they rise again,
	With twenty mortal murders on their crowns,
	And push us from our stools: this is more strange
	Than such a murder is.
<SPEECH 97><ACT 3><SCENE 4><54%>
	I do forget.
	Do not muse at me, my most worthy friends;
	I have a strange infirmity, which is nothing
	To those that know me. Come, love and health to all;
	Then, I'll sit down. Give me some wine; fill full.
	I drink to the general joy of the whole table,
	And to our dear friend Banquo, whom we miss;
	Would he were here! to all, and him, we thirst,
	And all to all.
<SPEECH 98><ACT 3><SCENE 4><54%>
	Avaunt! and quit my sight! Let the earth hide thee!
	Thy bones are marrowless, thy blood is cold;
	Thou hast no speculation in those eyes
	Which thou dost glare with.
<SPEECH 99><ACT 3><SCENE 4><55%>
	What man dare, I dare:
	Approach thou like the rugged Russian bear,
	The arm'd rhinoceros, or the Hyrcan tiger;
	Take any shape but that, and my firm nerves
	Shall never tremble: or be alive again,
	And dare me to the desart with thy sword;
	If trembling I inhabit then, protest me
	The baby of a girl. Hence, horrible shadow!
	Unreal mockery, hence!
	Why, so; being gone,
	I am a man again. Pray you, sit still.
<SPEECH 100><ACT 3><SCENE 4><55%>
	Can such things be
	And overcome us like a summer's cloud,
	Without our special wonder? You make me strange
	Even to the disposition that I owe,
	When now I think you can behold such sights,
	And keep the natural ruby of your cheeks,
	When mine are blanch'd with fear.
<SPEECH 101><ACT 3><SCENE 4><56%>
	It will have blood, they say; blood will have blood:
	Stones have been known to move and trees to speak;
	Augurs and understood relations have
	By maggot-pies and choughs and rooks brought forth
	The secret'st man of blood. What is the night?
<SPEECH 102><ACT 3><SCENE 4><56%>
	How sayst thou, that Macduff denies his person
	At our great bidding?
<SPEECH 103><ACT 3><SCENE 4><56%>
	I hear it by the way; but I will send.
	There's not a one of them but in his house
	I keep a servant fee'd. I will to-morrow—
	And betimes I will—to the weird sisters:
	More shall they speak; for now I am bent to know,
	By the worst means, the worst. For mine own good
	All causes shall give way: I am in blood
	Stepp'd in so far, that, should I wade no more,
	Returning were as tedious as go o'er.
	Strange things I have in head that will to hand,
	Which must be acted ere they may be scann'd.
<SPEECH 104><ACT 3><SCENE 4><57%>
	Come, we'll to sleep. My strange and self-abuse
	Is the initiate fear that wants hard use:
	We are yet but young in deed.
<SPEECH 105><ACT 4><SCENE 1><62%>
	How now, you secret, black, and mid-night hags!
	What is 't you do?
<SPEECH 106><ACT 4><SCENE 1><62%>
	I conjure you, by that which you profess,—
	Howe'er you come to know it,—answer me:
	Though you untie the winds and let them fight
	Against the churches; though the yesty waves
	Confound and swallow navigation up;
	Though bladed corn be lodg'd and trees blown down;
	Though castles topple on their warders' heads;
	Though palaces and pyramids do slope
	Their heads to their foundations; though the treasure
	Of Nature's germens tumble all together,
	Even till destruction sicken; answer me
	To what I ask you.
<SPEECH 107><ACT 4><SCENE 1><63%>
	Call 'em: let me see 'em.
<SPEECH 108><ACT 4><SCENE 1><63%>
	Tell me, thou unknown power,—
<SPEECH 109><ACT 4><SCENE 1><64%>
	Whate'er thou art, for thy good caution thanks;
	Thou hast harp'd my fear aright. But one word more,—
<SPEECH 110><ACT 4><SCENE 1><64%>
	Had I three ears, I'd hear thee.
<SPEECH 111><ACT 4><SCENE 1><64%>
	Then live, Macduff: what need I fear of thee?
	But yet I'll make assurance double sure,
	And take a bond of fate: thou shalt not live;
	That I may tell pale-hearted fear it lies,
	And sleep in spite of thunder.
	What is this,
	That rises like the issue of a king,
	And wears upon his baby brow the round
	And top of sovereignty?
<SPEECH 112><ACT 4><SCENE 1><65%>
	That will never be:
	Who can impress the forest, bid the tree
	Unfix his earth-bound root? Sweet bodements! good!
	Rebellion's head, rise never till the wood
	Of Birnam rise, and our high-plac'd Macbeth
	Shall live the lease of nature, pay his breath
	To time and mortal custom. Yet my heart
	Throbs to know one thing: tell me—if your art
	Can tell so much,—shall Banquo's issue ever
	Reign in this kingdom?
<SPEECH 113><ACT 4><SCENE 1><65%>
	I will be satisfied: deny me this,
	And an eternal curse fall on you! Let me know.
	Why sinks that cauldron? and what noise is this?
<SPEECH 114><ACT 4><SCENE 1><66%>
	Thou art too like the spirit of Banquo; down!
	Thy crown does sear mine eyeballs: and thy hair,
	Thou other gold-bound brow, is like the first:
	A third is like the former. Filthy hags!
	Why do you show me this? A fourth! Start, eyes!
	What! will the line stretch out to the crack of doom?
	Another yet? A seventh! I'll see no more:
	And yet the eighth appears, who bears a glass
	Which shows me many more; and some I see
	That two-fold balls and treble sceptres carry.
	Horrible sight! Now, I see, 'tis true;
	For the blood-bolter'd Banquo smiles upon me,
	And points at them for his.
	What! is this so?
<SPEECH 115><ACT 4><SCENE 1><66%>
	Where are they? Gone? Let this pernicious hour
	Stand aye accursed in the calendar!
	Come in, without there!
<SPEECH 116><ACT 4><SCENE 1><67%>
	Saw you the weird sisters?
<SPEECH 117><ACT 4><SCENE 1><67%>
	Came they not by you?
<SPEECH 118><ACT 4><SCENE 1><67%>
	Infected be the air whereon they ride,
	And damn'd all those that trust them! I did hear
	The galloping of horse: who was 't came by?
<SPEECH 119><ACT 4><SCENE 1><67%>
	Fled to England!
<SPEECH 120><ACT 4><SCENE 1><67%>
	Time, thou anticipat'st my dread exploits;
	The flighty purpose never is o'ertook
	Unless the deed go with it; from this moment
	The very firstlings of my heart shall be
	The firstlings of my hand. And even now,
	To crown my thoughts with acts, be it thought and done:
	The castle of Macduff I will surprise;
	Seize upon Fife; give to the edge of the sword
	His wife, his babes, and all unfortunate souls
	That trace him in his line. No boasting like a fool;
	This deed I'll do, before this purpose cool:
	But no moresights! Where are these gentlemen?
	Come, bring me where they are.
<SPEECH 121><ACT 5><SCENE 3><87%>
	Bring me no more reports; let them fly all:
	Till Birnam wood remove to Dunsinane
	I cannot taint with fear. What's the boy Malcolm?
	Was he not born of woman? The spirits that know
	All mortal consequences have pronounc'd me thus:
	'Fear not, Macbeth; no man that's born of woman
	Shall e'er have power upon thee.' Then fly, false thanes,
	And mingle with the English epicures:
	The mind I sway by and the heart I bear
	Shall never sag with doubt nor shake with fear.
	The devil damn thee black, thou cream-fac'd loon!
	Where gott'st thou that goose look?
<SPEECH 122><ACT 5><SCENE 3><88%>
	Geese, villain?
<SPEECH 123><ACT 5><SCENE 3><88%>
	Go, prick thy face, and over-red thy fear,
	Thou lily-liver'd boy. What soldiers, patch?
	Death of thy soul! those linen cheeks of thine
	Are counsellors to fear. What soldiers, wheyface?
<SPEECH 124><ACT 5><SCENE 3><88%>
	Take thy face hence. <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> Seyton!—I am sick at heart
	When I behold—Seyton, I say!—This push
	Will cheer me ever or disseat me now.
	I have liv'd long enough: my way of life
	Is fall'n into the sear, the yellow leaf;
	And that which should accompany old age,
	As honour, love, obedience, troops of friends,
	I must not look to have; but, in their stead,
	Curses, not loud but deep, mouth-honour, breath,
	Which the poor heart would fain deny, and dare not.
	Seyton!
<SPEECH 125><ACT 5><SCENE 3><89%>
	What news more?
<SPEECH 126><ACT 5><SCENE 3><89%>
	I'll fight till from my bones my flesh be hack'd.
	Give me my armour.
<SPEECH 127><ACT 5><SCENE 3><89%>
	I'll put it on.
	Send out more horses, skirr the country round;
	Hang those that talk of fear. Give me mine armour.
	How does your patient, doctor?
<SPEECH 128><ACT 5><SCENE 3><89%>
	Cure her of that:
	Canst thou not minister to a mind diseas'd,
	Pluck from the memory a rooted sorrow,
	Raze out the written troubles of the brain,
	And with some sweet oblivious antidote
	Cleanse the stuff'd bosom of that perilous stuff
	Which weighs upon the heart?
<SPEECH 129><ACT 5><SCENE 3><89%>
	Throw physic to the dogs; I'll none of it.
	Come, put mine armour on; give me my staff.
	Seyton, send out.—Doctor, the thanes fly from me.—
	Come, sir, dispatch.—If thou couldst, doctor, cast
	The water of my land, find her disease,
	And purge it to a sound and pristine health,
	I would applaud thee to the very echo,
	That should applaud again.—Pull 't off, I say.—
	What rhubarb, senna, or what purgative drug
	Would scour these English hence? Hear'st thou of them?
<SPEECH 130><ACT 5><SCENE 3><90%>
	Bring it after me.
	I will not be afraid of death and bane
	Till Birnam forest come to Dunsinane.
<SPEECH 131><ACT 5><SCENE 5><92%>
	Hang out our banners on the outward walls;
	The cry is still, 'They come;' our castle's strength
	Will laugh a siege to scorn; here let them lie
	Till famine and the ague eat them up;
	Were they not forc'd with those that should be ours,
	We might have met them dareful, beard to beard,
	And beat them backward home.
	What is that noise?
<SPEECH 132><ACT 5><SCENE 5><92%>
	I have almost forgot the taste of fears.
	The time has been my senses would have cool'd
	To hear a night-shriek, and my fell of hair
	Would at a dismal treatise rouse and stir
	As life were in 't. I have supp'd full with horrors;
	Direness, familiar to my slaughterous thoughts,
	Cannot once start me.
	Wherefore was that cry?
<SPEECH 133><ACT 5><SCENE 5><92%>
	She should have died hereafter;
	There would have been a time for such a word.
	To-morrow, and to-morrow, and to-morrow,
	Creeps in this petty pace from day to day,
	To the last syllable of recorded time;
	And all our yesterdays have lighted fools
	The way to dusty death. Out, out, brief candle!
	Life's but a walking shadow, a poor player
	That struts and frets his hour upon the stage,
	And then is heard no more; it is a tale
	Told by an idiot, full of sound and fury,
	Signifying nothing.
	Thou com'st to use thy tongue; thy story quickly.
<SPEECH 134><ACT 5><SCENE 5><93%>
	Well, say, sir.
<SPEECH 135><ACT 5><SCENE 5><93%>
	Liar and slave!
<SPEECH 136><ACT 5><SCENE 5><93%>
	If thou speak'st false,
	Upon the next tree shalt thou hang alive,
	Till famine cling thee; if thy speech be sooth,
	I care not if thou dost for me as much.
	I pull in resolution and begin
	To doubt the equivocation of the fiend
	That lies like truth; 'Fear not, till Birnam wood
	Do come to Dunsinane;' and now a wood
	Comes toward Dunsinane. Arm, arm, and out!
	If this which he avouches does appear,
	There is nor flying hence, nor tarrying here.
	I 'gin to be aweary of the sun,
	And wish the estate o' the world were now undone.
	Ring the alarum-bell! Blow, wind! come, wrack!
	At least we'll die with harness on our back.
<SPEECH 137><ACT 5><SCENE 7><95%>
	They have tied me to a stake; I cannot fly,
	But bear-like I must fight the course. What's he
	That was not born of woman? Such a one
	Am I to fear, or none.
<SPEECH 138><ACT 5><SCENE 7><95%>
	Thou'lt be afraid to hear it.
<SPEECH 139><ACT 5><SCENE 7><95%>
	My name's Macbeth.
<SPEECH 140><ACT 5><SCENE 7><95%>
	No, nor more fearful.
<SPEECH 141><ACT 5><SCENE 7><95%>
	Thou wast born of woman:
	But swords I smile at, weapons laugh to scorn,
	Brandish'd by man that's of a woman born.
<SPEECH 142><ACT 5><SCENE 7><96%>
	Why should I play the Roman fool, and die
	On mine own sword? whiles I see lives, the gashes
	Do better upon them.
<SPEECH 143><ACT 5><SCENE 7><97%>
	Of all men else I have avoided thee:
	But get thee back, my soul is too much charg'd
	With blood of thine already.
<SPEECH 144><ACT 5><SCENE 7><97%>
	Thou losest labour:
	As easy mayst thou the intrenchant air
	With thy keen sword impress as make me bleed:
	Let fall thy blade on vulnerable crests;
	I bear a charmed life, which must not yield
	To one of woman born.
<SPEECH 145><ACT 5><SCENE 7><97%>
	Accursed be that tongue that tells me so,
	For it hath cow'd my better part of man:
	And be these juggling fiends no more believ'd,
	That palter with us in a double sense;
	That keep the word of promise to our ear,
	And break it to our hope. I'll not fight with thee.
<SPEECH 146><ACT 5><SCENE 7><98%>
	I will not yield,
	To kiss the ground before young Malcolm's feet,
	And to be baited with the rabble's curse.
	Though Birnam wood be come to Dunsinane,
	And thou oppos'd, being of no woman born,
	Yet I will try the last: before my body
	I throw my war-like shield. Lay on, Macduff,
	And damn'd be him that first cries, 'Hold, enough!'
