<SPEECH 1><ACT 2><SCENE 3><31%>
	Was it so late, friend, ere you went to bed,
	That you do lie so late?
<SPEECH 2><ACT 2><SCENE 3><31%>
	What three things does drink especially provoke?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 2><SCENE 3><31%>
	I believe drink gave thee the lie last night.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 2><SCENE 3><32%>
	Is thy master stirring?
	Our knocking has awak'd him; here he comes.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 2><SCENE 3><32%>
	Is the king stirring, worthy thane?
<SPEECH 6><ACT 2><SCENE 3><32%>
	He did command me to call timely on him:
	I have almost slipp'd the hour.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 2><SCENE 3><32%>
	I know this is a joyful trouble to you;
	But yet 'tis one.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 3><32%>
	I'll make so bold to call,
	For 'tis my limited service.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 2><SCENE 3><33%>
	O horror! horror! horror! Tongue nor heart
	Cannot conceive nor name thee!
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 3><33%>
	Confusion now hath made his masterpiece!
	Most sacrilegious murder hath broke ope
	The Lord's anointed temple, and stole thence
	The life o' the building!
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 3><33%>
	Approach the chamber, and destroy your sight
	With a new Gorgon: do not bid me speak;
	See, and then speak yourselves.
	Awake! awake!
	Ring the alarum-bell. Murder and treason!
	Banquo and Donalbain! Malcolm! awake!
	Shake off this downy sleep, death's counterfeit,
	And look on death itself! up, up, and see
	The great doom's image! Malcolm! Banquo!
	As from your graves rise up, and walk like sprites,
	To countenance this horror! Ring the bell.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 3><34%>
	O gentle lady!
	'Tis not for you to hear what I can speak;
	The repetition in a woman's ear
	Would murder as it fell.
	O Banquo! Banquo!
	Our royal master's murder'd!
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 3><35%>
	Your royal father's murder'd.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 3><35%>
	Wherefore did you so?
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 3><35%>
	Look to the lady.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 3><36%>
	And so do I.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	Why, see you not?
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	Those that Macbeth hath slain.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	They were suborn'd.
	Malcolm and Donalbain, the king's two sons,
	Are stol'n away and fled, which puts upon them
	Suspicion of the deed.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	He is already nam'd, and gone to Scone
	To be invested.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	Carried to Colmekill;
	The sacred storehouse of his predecessors
	And guardian of their bones.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	No, cousin, I'll to Fife.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	Well, may you see things well done there: adieu!
	Lest our old robes sit easier than our new!
<SPEECH 24><ACT 4><SCENE 3><72%>
	Let us rather
	Hold fast the mortal sword, and like good men
	Bestride our down-fall'n birthdom; each new morn
	New widowshowl, new orphans cry, new sorrows
	Strike heaven on the face, that it resounds
	As if it felt with Scotland and yell'd out
	Like syllable of dolour.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 4><SCENE 3><72%>
	I am not treacherous.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	I have lost my hopes.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	Bleed, bleed, poor country!
	Great tyranny, lay thou thy basis sure,
	For goodness dares not check thee! wear thou thy wrongs;
	The title is affeer'd! Fare thee well, lord:
	I would not be the villain that thou think'st
	For the whole space that's in the tyrant's grasp,
	And the rich East to boot.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 4><SCENE 3><74%>
	What should he be?
<SPEECH 29><ACT 4><SCENE 3><74%>
	Not in the legions
	Of horrid hell can come a devil more damn'd
	In evils to top Macbeth.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 4><SCENE 3><75%>
	Boundless intemperance
	In nature is a tyranny; it hath been
	Th' untimely emptying of the happy throne,
	And fall of many kings. But fear not yet
	To take upon you what is yours; you may
	Convey your pleasures in a spacious plenty,
	And yet seem cold, the time you may so hoodwink.
	We have willing dames enough; there cannot be
	That vulture in you, to devour so many
	As will to greatness dedicate themselves,
	Finding it so inclin'd.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 4><SCENE 3><75%>
	This avarice
	Sticks deeper, grows with more pernicious root
	Than summer-seeming lust, and it hath been
	The sword of our slain kings: yet do not fear;
	Scotland hath foisons to fill up your will,
	Of your mere own; all these are portable,
	With other graces weigh'd.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 4><SCENE 3><76%>
	O Scotland, Scotland!
<SPEECH 33><ACT 4><SCENE 3><76%>
	Fit to govern!
	No, not to live. O nation miserable,
	With an untitled tyrant bloody-scepter'd,
	When shalt thou see thy wholesome days again,
	Since that the truest issue of thy throne
	By his own interdiction stands accurs'd,
	And does blaspheme his breed? Thy royal father
	Was a most sainted king; the queen that bore thee,
	Oft'ner upon her knees than on her feet,
	Died every day she liv'd. Fare thee well!
	These evils thou repeat'st upon thyself
	Have banish'd me from Scotland. O my breast,
	Thy hope ends here!
<SPEECH 34><ACT 4><SCENE 3><77%>
	Such welcome and unwelcome things at once
	'Tis hard to reconcile.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	What's the disease he means?
<SPEECH 36><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	See, who comes here?
<SPEECH 37><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	My ever-gentle cousin, welcome hither.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	Stands Scotland where it did?
<SPEECH 39><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	O! relation
	Too nice, and yet too true!
<SPEECH 40><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	How does my wife?
<SPEECH 41><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	And all my children?
<SPEECH 42><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	The tyrant has not batter'd at their peace?
<SPEECH 43><ACT 4><SCENE 3><80%>
	Be not a niggard of your speech: how goes 't?
<SPEECH 44><ACT 4><SCENE 3><80%>
	What concern they?
	The general cause? or is it a fee-grief
	Due to some single breast?
<SPEECH 45><ACT 4><SCENE 3><80%>
	If it be mine
	Keep it not from me; quickly let me have it.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 4><SCENE 3><81%>
	Hum! I guess at it.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 4><SCENE 3><81%>
	My children too?
<SPEECH 48><ACT 4><SCENE 3><81%>
	And I must be from thence!
	My wife kill'd too?
<SPEECH 49><ACT 4><SCENE 3><81%>
	He has no children. All my pretty ones?
	Did you say all? O hell-kite! All?
	What! all my pretty chickens and their dam
	At one fell swoop?
<SPEECH 50><ACT 4><SCENE 3><81%>
	I shall do so;
	But I must also feel it as a man:
	I cannot but remember such things were,
	That were most precious to me. Did heaven look on,
	And would not take their part? Sinful Macduff!
	They were all struck for thee. Naught that I am,
	Not for their own demerits, but for mine,
	Fell slaughter on their souls. Heaven rest them now!
<SPEECH 51><ACT 4><SCENE 3><82%>
	O! I could play the woman with mine eyes,
	And braggart with my tongue. But, gentle heavens,
	Cut short all intermission; front to front
	Bring thou this fiend of Scotland and myself;
	Within my sword's length set him; if he 'scape,
	Heaven forgive him too!
<SPEECH 52><ACT 5><SCENE 4><91%>
	Let our just censures
	Attend the true event, and put we on
	Industrious soldiership.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 5><SCENE 6><94%>
	Make all our trumpets speak; give them all breath,
	Those clamorous harbingers of blood and death.
<SPEECH 54><ACT 5><SCENE 7><95%>
	That way the noise is. Tyrant, show thy face:
	If thou be'st slain and with no stroke of mine,
	My wife and children's ghosts will haunt me still.
	I cannot strike at wretched kerns, whose arms
	Are hir'd to bear their staves: either thou, Macbeth,
	Or else my sword with an unbatter'd edge
	I sheathe again undeeded. There thou shouldst be;
	By this great clatter, one of greatest note
	Seems bruited. Let me find him, fortune!
	And more I beg not.
<SPEECH 55><ACT 5><SCENE 7><96%>
	Turn, hell-hound, turn!
<SPEECH 56><ACT 5><SCENE 7><97%>
	I have no words;
	My voice is in my sword, thou bloodier villain
	Than terms can give thee out!
<SPEECH 57><ACT 5><SCENE 7><97%>
	Despair thy charm;
	And let the angel whom thou still hast serv'd
	Tell thee, Macduff was from his mother's womb
	Untimely ripp'd.
<SPEECH 58><ACT 5><SCENE 7><97%>
	Then yield thee, coward,
	And live to be the show and gaze o' the time:
	We'll have thee, as our rarer monsters are,
	Painted upon a pole, and underwrit,
	'Here may you see the tyrant.'
<SPEECH 59><ACT 5><SCENE 7><99%>
	Hail, king! for so thou art. Behold, where stands
	The usurper's cursed head: the time is free:
	I see thee compass'd with thy kingdom's pearl,
	That speak my salutation in their minds;
	Whose voices I desire aloud with mine;
	Hail, King of Scotland!
