<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 2><1%>
	This is the sergeant
	Who, like a good and hardy soldier fought
	'Gainst my captivity. Hail, brave friend!
	Say to the king the knowledge of the broil
	As thou didst leave it.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 2><3%>
	The worthy Thane of Ross.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 4><11%>
	My liege,
	They are not yet come back; but I have spoke
	With one that saw him die; who did report
	That very frankly he confess'd his treasons,
	Implor'd your highness' pardon and set forth
	A deep repentance. Nothing in his life
	Became him like the leaving it; he died
	As one that had been studied in his death
	To throw away the dearest thing he ow'd,
	As 'twere a careless trifle.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 2><SCENE 3><35%>
	O! by whom?
<SPEECH 5><ACT 2><SCENE 3><35%>
	</STAGE DIR> Why do we hold our tongues,
	That most may claim this argument for ours:
<SPEECH 6><ACT 2><SCENE 3><36%>
	</STAGE DIR> Nor our strong sorrow
	Upon the foot of motion.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 2><SCENE 3><36%>
	What will you do? Let's not consort with them:
	To show an unfelt sorrow is an office
	Which the false man does easy. I'll to England.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 3><37%>
	This murderous shaft that's shot
	Hath not yet lighted, and our safest way
	Is to avoid the aim: therefore, to horse;
	And let us not be dainty of leave-taking,
	But shift away: there's warrant in that theft
	Which steals itself when there's no mercy left.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 4><SCENE 3><72%>
	Let us seek out some desolate shade, and there
	Weep our sad bosoms empty.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 4><SCENE 3><72%>
	What I believe I'll wail,
	What know believe, and what I can redress,
	As I shall find the time to friend, I will.
	What you have spoke, it may be so perchance.
	This tyrant, whosesole name blisters our tongues,
	Was once thought honest: you have lov'd him well;
	He hath not touch'd you yet. I am young; but something
	You may deserve of him through me, and wisdom
	To offer up a weak, poor, innocent lamb
	To appease an angry god.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 4><SCENE 3><72%>
	But Macbeth is.
	A good and virtuous nature may recoil
	In an imperial charge. But I shall crave your pardon;
	That which you are my thoughts cannot transpose;
	Angels are bright still, though the brightest fell;
	Though all things foul would wear the brows of grace,
	Yet grace must still look so.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	Perchance even there where I did find my doubts.
	Why in that rawness left you wife and child—
	Those precious motives, those strong knots of love—
	Without leave-taking? I pray you,
	Let not my jealousies be your dishonours,
	But mine own safeties: you may be rightly just,
	Whatever I shall think.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	Be not offended:
	I speak not as in absolute fear of you.
	I think our country sinks beneath the yoke;
	It weeps, it bleeds, and each new day a gash
	Is added to her wounds: I think withal,
	There would be hands uplifted in my right;
	And here from gracious England have I offer
	Of goodly thousands: but, for all this,
	When I shall tread upon the tyrant's head,
	Or wear it on my sword, yet my poor country
	Shall have more vices than it had before,
	More suffer, and more sundry ways than ever,
	By him that shall succeed.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 4><SCENE 3><74%>
	It is myself I mean; in whom I know
	All the particulars of vice so grafted,
	That, when they shall be open'd, black Macbeth
	Will seem as pure as snow, and the poor state
	Esteem him as a lamb, being compar'd
	With my confineless harms.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 4><SCENE 3><74%>
	I grant him bloody,
	Luxurious, avaricious, false, deceitful,
	Sudden, malicious, smacking of every sin
	That has a name; but there's no bottom, none,
	In my voluptuousness: your wives, your daughters,
	Your matrons, and your maids, could not fill up
	The cistern of my lust; and my desire
	All continent impediments would o'erbear
	That did oppose my will; better Macbeth
	Than such an one to reign.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 4><SCENE 3><75%>
	With this there grows
	In my most ill-compos'd affection such
	A stanchless avarice that, were I king,
	I should cut off the nobles for their lands,
	Desire his jewels and this other's house;
	And my more-having would be as a sauce
	To make me hunger more, that I should forge
	Quarrels unjust against the good and loyal,
	Destroying them for wealth.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 4><SCENE 3><76%>
	But I have none: the king-becoming graces,
	As justice, verity, temperance, stableness,
	Bounty, perseverance, mercy, lowliness,
	Devotion, patience, courage, fortitude,
	I have no relish of them, but abound
	In the division of each several crime,
	Acting it many ways. Nay, had I power, I should
	Pour the sweet milk of concord into hell,
	Uproar the universal peace, confound
	All unity on earth.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 4><SCENE 3><76%>
	If such a one be fit to govern, speak:
	I am as I have spoken.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 4><SCENE 3><77%>
	Macduff, this noble passion,
	Child of integrity, hath from my soul
	Wip'd the black scruples, reconcil'd my thoughts
	To thy good truth and honour. Devilish Macbeth
	By many of these trains hath sought to win me
	Into his power, and modest wisdom plucks me
	From over-credulous haste; but God above
	Deal between thee and me! for even now
	I put myself to thy direction, and
	Unspeak mine own detraction, here abjure
	The taints and blames I laid upon myself,
	For strangers to my nature. I am yet
	Unknown to woman, never was forsworn,
	Scarcely have coveted what was mine own;
	At no time broke my faith, would not betray
	The devil to his fellow, and delight
	No less in truth than life; my first false speaking
	Was this upon myself. What I am truly,
	Is thine and my poor country's to command;
	Whither indeed, before thy here-approach,
	Old Siward, with ten thousand war-like men,
	Already at a point, was setting forth.
	Now we'll together, and the chance of goodness
	Be like our warranted quarrel. Why are you silent?
<SPEECH 20><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	Well; more anon. Comes the king forth, I pray you?
<SPEECH 21><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	I thank you, doctor.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	'Tis call'd the evil:
	A most miraculous work in this good king,
	Which often, since my here-remain in England,
	I have seen him do. How he solicits heaven,
	Himself best knows; but strangely-visited people,
	All swoln and ulcerous, pitiful to the eye,
	The mere despair of surgery, he cures;
	Hanging a golden stamp about their necks,
	Put on with holy prayers; and 'tis spoken
	To the succeeding royalty he leaves
	The healing benediction. With this strange virtue,
	He hath a heavenly gift of prophecy,
	And sundry blessings hang about his throne
	That speak him full of grace.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	My countryman; but yet I know him not.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	I know him now. Good God, betimes remove
	The means that make us strangers!
<SPEECH 25><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	What's the newest grief?
<SPEECH 26><ACT 4><SCENE 3><80%>
	Be 't their comfort,
	We are coming thither. Gracious England hath
	Lent us good Siward and ten thousand men;
	An older and a better soldier none
	That Christendom gives out.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 4><SCENE 3><81%>
	Merciful heaven!
	What! man; ne'er pull your hat upon your brows;
	Give sorrow words; the grief that does not speak
	Whispers the o'er-fraught heart and bids it break.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 4><SCENE 3><81%>
	Be comforted:
	Let's make us medicine of our great revenge,
	To cure this deadly grief.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 4><SCENE 3><81%>
	Dispute it like a man.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 4><SCENE 3><82%>
	Be this the whetstone of your sword: let grief
	Convert to anger; blunt not the heart, enrage it.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 4><SCENE 3><82%>
	This tune goes manly.
	Come, go we to the king; our power is ready;
	Our lack is nothing but our leave. Macbeth
	Is ripe for shaking, and the powers above
	Put on their instruments. Receive what cheer you may;
	The night is long that never finds the day.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 5><SCENE 4><90%>
	Cousins, I hope the days are near at hand
	That chambers will be safe.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 5><SCENE 4><91%>
	Let every soldier hew him down a bough
	And bear 't before him: thereby shall we shadow
	The numbers of our host, and make discovery
	Err in report of us.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 5><SCENE 4><91%>
	'Tis his main hope;
	For where there is advantage to be given,
	Both more and less have given him the revolt,
	And none serve with him but constrained things
	Whose hearts are absent too.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 5><SCENE 6><94%>
	Now near enough; your leavy screens throw down,
	And show like those you are. You, worthy uncle,
	Shall, with my cousin, your right-noble son,
	Lead our first battle; worthy Macduff and we
	Shall take upon 's what else remains to do,
	According to our order.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 5><SCENE 7><96%>
	We have met with foes
	That strike beside us.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 5><SCENE 7><98%>
	I would the friends we miss were safe arriv'd.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 5><SCENE 7><98%>
	Macduff is missing, and your noble son.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 5><SCENE 7><99%>
	He's worth more sorrow,
	And that I'll spend for him.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 5><SCENE 7><99%>
	We shall not spend a large expense of time
	Before we reckon with your several loves,
	And make us even with you. My thanes and kinsmen,
	Henceforth be earls, the first that ever Scotland
	In such an honour nam'd. What's more to do,
	Which would be planted newly with the time,
	As calling home our exil'd friends abroad
	That fled the snares of watchful tyranny;
	Producing forth the cruel ministers
	Of this dead butcher and his fiend-like queen,
	Who, as 'tis thought, by self and violent hands
	Took off her life; this, and what needful else
	That calls upon us, by the grace of Grace
	We will perform in measure, time, and place:
	So, thanks to all at once and to each one,
	Whom we invite to see us crown'd at Scone.
