<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 4><16%>
	Nay, gentle Romeo, we must have you dance.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 4><16%>
	You are a lover; borrow Cupid's wings,
	And soar with them above a common bound.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 4><16%>
	And, to sink in it, should you burden love;
	Too great oppression for a tender thing.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 4><16%>
	If love be rough with you, be rough with love;
	Prick love for pricking, and you beat love down.
	Give me a case to put my visage in:
	A visor for a visor! what care I,
	What curious eye doth quote deformities?
	Here are the beetle brows shall blush for me.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 4><17%>
	Tut! dun's the mouse, the constable's own word.
	If thou art Dun, we'll draw thee from the mire,
	Of—save your reverence—love, wherein thou stick'st
	Up to the ears. Come, we burn daylight, ho!
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 4><17%>
	I mean, sir, in delay
	We waste our lights in vain, like lamps by day.
	Take our good meaning, for our judgment sits
	Five times in that ere once in our five wits.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 4><17%>
	Why, may one ask?
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 4><17%>
	And so did I.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 4><17%>
	That dreamers often lie.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 4><17%>
	O! then, I see, Queen Mab hath been with you.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 4><17%>
	She is the fairies' midwife, and she comes
	In shape no bigger than an agate-stone
	On the fore-finger of an alderman,
	Drawn with a team of little atomies
	Athwart men's noses as they lie asleep:
	Her waggon-spokes made of long spinners' legs;
	The cover, of the wings of grasshoppers;
	The traces, of the smallest spider's web;
	The collars, of the moonshine's watery beams;
	Her whip, of cricket's bone; the lash, of film;
	Her waggoner, a small grey-coated gnat,
	Not half so big as a round little worm
	Prick'd from the lazy finger of a maid;
	Her chariot is an empty hazel-nut,
	Made by the joiner squirrel or old grub,
	Time out o' mind the fairies' coach-makers.
	And in this state she gallops night by night
	Through lovers' brains, and then they dream of love;
	O'er courtiers' knees, that dream on curtsies straight;
	O'er lawyers' fingers, who straight dream on fees;
	O'er ladies' lips, who straight on kisses dream;
	Which oft the angry Mab with blisters plagues,
	Because their breaths with sweetmeats tainted are.
	Sometimes she gallops o'er a courtier's nose,
	And then dreams he of smelling out a suit;
	And sometimes comes she with a tithe pig's tail,
	Tickling a parson's nose as a' lies asleep,
	Then dreams he of another benefice;
	Sometime she driveth o'er a soldier's neck,
	And then dreams he of cutting foreign throats,
	Of breaches, ambuscadoes, Spanish bladed,
	Of healths five fathom deep; and then anon
	Drums in his ear, at which he starts and wakes;
	And, being thus frighted, swears a prayer or two,
	And sleeps again. This is that very Mab
	That plats the manes of horses in the night;
	And bakes the elf-locks in foul sluttish hairs,
	Which once untangled much misfortune bodes;
	This is the hag, when maids lie on their backs,
	That presses them and learns them first to bear,
	Making them women of good carriage:
	This is she—
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 4><19%>
	True, I talk of dreams,
	Which are the children of an idle brain,
	Begot of nothing but vain fantasy;
	Which is as thin of substance as the air,
	And more inconstant than the wind, who woos
	Even now the frozen bosom of the north,
	And, being anger'd, puffs away from thence,
	Turning his face to the dew-dropping south.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	He is wise;
	And, on my life, hath stol'n him home to bed.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	Nay, I'll conjure too.
	Romeo! humours! madman! passion! lover!
	Appear thou in the likeness of a sigh:
	Speak but one rime and I am satisfied;
	Cry but 'Ay me!' couple but 'love' and 'dove;'
	Speak to my gossip Venus one fair word.
	One nickname for her purblind son and heir,
	Young Adam Cupid, he that shot so trim
	When King Cophetua lov'd the beggar-maid.
	He heareth not, he stirreth not, he moveth not;
	The ape is dead, and I must conjure him.
	I conjure thee by Rosaline's bright eyes,
	By her high forehead, and her scarlet lip,
	By her fine foot, straight leg, and quivering thigh,
	And the demesnes that there adjacent lie,
	That in thy likeness thou appear to us.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	This cannot anger him: 'twould anger him
	To raise a spirit in his mistress' circle
	Of some strange nature, letting it there stand
	Till she had laid it, and conjur'd it down;
	That were some spite: my invocation
	Is fair and honest, and in his mistress' name
	I conjure only but to raise up him.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	If love be blind, love cannot hit the mark.
	Now will he sit under a medlar tree,
	And wish his mistress were that kind of fruit
	As maids call medlars, when they laugh alone.
	O Romeo! that she were, O! that she were
	An open et cætera, thou a poperin pear.
	Romeo, good night: I'll to my truckle-bed;
	This field-bed is too cold for me to sleep:
	Come, shall we go?
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 4><35%>
	Where the devil should this Romeo be?
	Came he not home to-night?
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 4><36%>
	Why that same pale hard-hearted wench, that Rosaline,
	Torments him so, that he will sure run mad.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 4><36%>
	A challenge, on my life.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 4><36%>
	Any man that can write may answer a letter.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 4><36%>
	Alas! poor Romeo, he is already dead; stabbed with a white wench's black eye; shot through the ear with a love-song; the very pin of his heart cleft with the blind bow-boy's butt-shaft; and is he a man to encounter Tybalt?
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 4><36%>
	More than prince of cats, I can tell you. O! he is the courageous captain of compliments. He fights as you sing prick-song, keeps time, distance, and proportion; rests me his minim rest, one, two, and the third in your bosom; the very butcher of a silk button, a duellist, a duellist; a gentleman of the very first house, of the first and second cause. Ah! the immortal passado! the punto reverso! the hay!
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 4><36%>
	The pox of such antick, lisping, affecting fantasticoes, these new tuners of accents!—'By Jesu, a very good blade!—a very tall man! a very good whore.'—Why, is not this a lamentable thing, grandsire, that we should be thus afflicted with these strange flies, these fashion-mongers, these pardonnez-mois, who stand so much on the new form that they cannot sit at ease on the old bench? O, their bons, their bons!
<SPEECH 24><ACT 2><SCENE 4><37%>
	Without his roe, like a dried herring. O flesh, flesh, how art thou fishified! Now is he for the numbers that Petrarch flowed in: Laura to his lady was but a kitchen-wench; marry, she had a better love to be-rime her; Dido a dowdy; Cleopatra a gipsy; Helen and Hero hildings and harlots; Thisbe, a grey eye or so, but not to the purpose. Signior Romeo, bon jour! there's a French salutation to your French slop. You gave us the counterfeit fairly last night.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 2><SCENE 4><37%>
	The slip, sir, the slip; can you not conceive?
<SPEECH 26><ACT 2><SCENE 4><37%>
	That's as much as to say, such a case as yours constrains a man to bow in the hams.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 2><SCENE 4><37%>
	Thou hast most kindly hit it.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 2><SCENE 4><37%>
	Nay, I am the very pink of courtesy.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 2><SCENE 4><37%>
	Right.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 2><SCENE 4><37%>
	Well said; follow me this jest now till thou hast worn out the pump, that, when the single sole of it is worn, the jest may remain after the wearing sole singular.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	Come between us, good Benvolio; my wit faints.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	Nay, if thy wits run the wild-goose chase, I have done, for thou hast more of the wild-goose in one of thy wits than, I am sure, I have in my whole five. Was I with you there for the goose?
<SPEECH 33><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	I will bite thee by the ear for that jest.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	Thy wit is a very bitter sweeting; it is a most sharp sauce.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	O! here's a wit of cheveril, that stretches from an inch narrow to an ell broad.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	Why, is not this better now than groaning for love? now art thou sociable, now art thou Romeo; now art thou what thou art, by art as well as by nature: for this drivelling love is like a great natural, that runs lolling up and down to hide his bauble in a hole.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	Thou desirest me to stop in my tale against the hair.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	O! thou art deceived; I would have made it short; for I was come to the whole depth of my tale, and meant indeed to occupy the argument no longer.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	A sail, a sail!
<SPEECH 40><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	Good Peter, to hide her face; for her fan's the fairer face.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	God ye good den, fair gentlewoman.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	'Tis no less, I tell you; for the bawdy hand of the dial is now upon the prick of noon.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	Yea! is the worst well? very well took, i' faith; wisely, wisely.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	A bawd, a bawd, a bawd! So ho!
<SPEECH 45><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	No hare, sir; unless a hare, sir, in a lenten pie, that is something stale and hoar ere it be spent.
	An old hare hoar, and an old hare hoar,
	Is very good meat in Lent:
	But a hare that is hoar, is too much for a score,
	When it hoars ere it be spent.
	Romeo, will you come to your father's? we'll to dinner thither.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 2><SCENE 4><40%>
	Farewell, ancient lady; farewell, Lady, lady, lady.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 3><SCENE 1><46%>
	Thou art like one of those fellows that when he enters the confines of a tavern claps me his sword upon the table and says, 'God send me no need of thee!' and by the operation of the second cup draws him on the drawer, when, indeed, there is no need.
<SPEECH 48><ACT 3><SCENE 1><46%>
	Come, come, thou art as hot a Jack in thy mood as any in Italy; and as soon moved to be moody, and as soon moody to be moved.
<SPEECH 49><ACT 3><SCENE 1><46%>
	Nay, an there were two such, we should have none shortly, for one would kill the other. Thou! why, thou wilt quarrel with a man that hath a hair more or a hair less in his beard than thou hast. Thou wilt quarrel with a man for cracking nuts, having no other reason but because thou hast hazel eyes. What eye, but such an eye, would spy out such a quarrel? Thy head is as full of quarrels as an egg is full of meat, and yet thy head hath been beaten as addle as an egg for quarrelling. Thou hast quarrelled with a man for coughing in the street, because he hath wakened thy dog that hath lain asleep in the sun. Didst thou not fall out with a tailor for wearing his new doublet before Easter? with another, for tying his new shoes with old riband? and yet thou wilt tutor me from quarrelling!
<SPEECH 50><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	The fee-simple! O simple!
<SPEECH 51><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	By my heel, I care not.
<SPEECH 52><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	And but one word with one of us? Couple it with something; make it a word and a blow.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	Could you not take some occasion without giving?
<SPEECH 54><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	Consort! What! dost thou make us minstrels? an thou make minstrels of us, look to hear nothing but discords: here's my fiddlestick; here's that shall make you dance. 'Zounds! consort!
<SPEECH 55><ACT 3><SCENE 1><48%>
	Men's eyes were made to look, and let them gaze;
	I will not budge for no man's pleasure, I.
<SPEECH 56><ACT 3><SCENE 1><48%>
	But I'll be hang'd, sir, if he wear your livery:
	Marry, go before to field, he'll be your follower;
	Your worship in that sense may call him 'man.'
<SPEECH 57><ACT 3><SCENE 1><48%>
	O calm, dishonourable, vile submission!
	Alla stoccata carries it away.
	Tybalt, you rat-catcher, will you walk?
<SPEECH 58><ACT 3><SCENE 1><48%>
	Good king of cats, nothing but one of your nine lives, that I mean to make bold withal, and, as you shall use me hereafter, dry-beat the rest of the eight. Will you pluck your sword out of his pilcher by the ears? make haste, lest mine be about your ears ere it be out.
<SPEECH 59><ACT 3><SCENE 1><49%>
	Come, sir, your passado.
<SPEECH 60><ACT 3><SCENE 1><49%>
	I am hurt.
	A plague o' both your houses! I am sped.
	Is he gone, and hath nothing?
<SPEECH 61><ACT 3><SCENE 1><49%>
	Ay, ay, a scratch, a scratch; marry, 'tis enough.
	Where is my page? Go, villain, fetch a surgeon.
<SPEECH 62><ACT 3><SCENE 1><49%>
	No, 'tis not so deep as a well, nor so wide as a church door; but 'tis enough, 'twill serve: ask for me to-morrow, and you shall find me a grave man. I am peppered, I warrant, for this world. A plague o' both your houses! 'Zounds, a dog, a rat, a mouse, a cat, to scratch a man to death! a braggart, a rogue, a villain, that fights by the book of arithmetic! Why the devil came you between us? I was hurt under your arm.
<SPEECH 63><ACT 3><SCENE 1><49%>
	Help me into some house, Benvolio,
	Or I shall faint. A plague o' both your houses!
	They have made worms' meat of me: I have it,
	And soundly too:—your houses!
