<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 3><12%>
	Now, by my maidenhead, at twelve year old,—
	I bade her come. What, lamb! what, ladybird!
	God forbid! where's this girl? what, Juliet!
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 3><12%>
	Your mother.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 3><12%>
	Faith, I can tell her age unto an hour.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 3><12%>
	I'll lay fourteen of my teeth—
	And yet to my teen be it spoken I have but four—
	She is not fourteen. How long is it now
	To Lammas-tide?
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 3><13%>
	Even or odd, of all days in the year,
	Come Lammas-eve at night shall she be fourteen.
	Susan and she—God rest all Christian souls!—
	Were of an age. Well, Susan is with God;
	She was too good for me. But, as I said,
	On Lammas-eve at night shall she be fourteen;
	That shall she, marry; I remember it well.
	'Tis since the earthquake now eleven years;
	And she was wean'd, I never shall forget it,
	Of all the days of the year, upon that day;
	For I had then laid wormwood to my dug,
	Sitting in the sun under the dove-house wall;
	My lord and you were then at Mantua.
	Nay, I do bear a brain:—but, as I said,
	When it did taste the wormwood on the nipple
	Of my dug and felt it bitter, pretty fool!
	To see it tetchy and fall out with the dug.
	'Shake,' quoth the dove-house: 'twas no need, I trow,
	To bid me trudge:
	And since that time it is eleven years;
	For then she could stand high lone; nay, by the rood,
	She could have run and waddled all about;
	For even the day before she broke her brow:
	And then my husband—God be with his soul!
	A' was a merry man—took up the child:
	'Yea,' quoth he, 'dost thou fall upon thy face?
	Thou wilt fall backward when thou hast more wit;
	Wilt thou not, Jule?' and, by my halidom,
	The pretty wretch left crying, and said 'Ay.'
	To see now how a jest shall come about!
	I warrant, an I should live a thousand years,
	I never should forget it: 'Wilt thou not, Jule?' quoth he;
	And, pretty fool, it stinted and said 'Ay.'
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 3><14%>
	Yes, madam. Yet I cannot choose but laugh,
	To think it should leave crying, and say 'Ay.'
	And yet, I warrant, it had upon its brow
	A bump as big as a young cockerel's stone;
	A parlous knock; and it cried bitterly:
	'Yea,' quoth my husband, 'fall'st upon thy face?
	Thou wilt fall backward when thou com'st to age;
	Wilt thou not, Jule?' it stinted and said 'Ay.'
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 3><14%>
	Peace, I have done. God mark thee to his grace!
	Thou wast the prettiest babe that e'er I nursed:
	An I might live to see thee married once,
	I have my wish.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 3><14%>
	An honour! were not I thine only nurse,
	I would say thou hadst suck'd wisdom from thy teat.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 3><14%>
	A man, young lady! lady, such a man
	As all the world—why, he's a man of wax.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 3><14%>
	Nay, he's a flower; in faith, a very flower.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 3><15%>
	No less! nay, bigger; women grow by men.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 3><15%>
	Go, girl, seek happy nights to happy days.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 1><SCENE 5><23%>
	Madam, your mother craves a word with you.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 1><SCENE 5><23%>
	Marry, bachelor,
	Her mother is the lady of the house,
	And a good lady, and a wise, and virtuous:
	I nurs'd her daughter, that you talk'd withal;
	I tell you he that can lay hold of her
	Shall have the chinks.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 1><SCENE 5><24%>
	The son and heir of old Tiberio.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 1><SCENE 5><24%>
	Marry, that, I think, be young Petruchio.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 1><SCENE 5><24%>
	I know not.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 1><SCENE 5><24%>
	His name is Romeo, and a Montague;
	The only son of your great enemy.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 1><SCENE 5><24%>
	What's this, what's this?
<SPEECH 20><ACT 1><SCENE 5><24%>
	Anon, anon!—
	Come, let's away; the strangers are all gone.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	</STAGE DIR> Madam!
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	</STAGE DIR> Madam!
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	Peter!
<SPEECH 24><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	My fan, Peter.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	God ye good morrow, gentlemen.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	Is it good den?
<SPEECH 27><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	Out upon you! what a man are you!
<SPEECH 28><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	By my troth, it is well said; 'for himself to mar,' quoth a'?—Gentlemen, can any of you tell me where I may find the young Romeo?
<SPEECH 29><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	You say well.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	If you be he, sir, I desire some confidence with you.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 2><SCENE 4><40%>
	Marry, farewell! I pray you, sir, what saucy merchant was this, that was so full of his ropery?
<SPEECH 32><ACT 2><SCENE 4><40%>
	An a' speak anything against me, I'll take him down, an a' were lustier than he is, and twenty such Jacks; and if I cannot, I'll find those that shall. Scurvy knave! I am none of his flirt-gills; I am none of his skeins-mates. <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> And thou must stand by too, and suffer every knave to use me at his pleasure!
<SPEECH 33><ACT 2><SCENE 4><40%>
	Now, afore God, I am so vexed, that every part about me quivers. Scurvy knave! Pray you, sir, a word; and as I told you, my young lady bade me inquire you out; what she bid me say I will keep to myself; but first let me tell ye, if ye should lead her into a fool's paradise, as they say, it were a very gross kind of behaviour, as they say: for the gentlewoman is young; and, therefore, if you should deal double with her, truly it were an ill thing to be offered to any gentlewoman, and very weak dealing.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 2><SCENE 4><41%>
	Good heart! and i' faith, I will tell her as much. Lord, Lord! she will be a joyful woman.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 2><SCENE 4><41%>
	I will tell her, sir, that you do protest; which, as I take it, is a gentlemanlike offer.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 2><SCENE 4><41%>
	No, truly, sir; not a penny.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 2><SCENE 4><41%>
	This afternoon, sir? well, she shall be there.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 2><SCENE 4><41%>
	Now God in heaven bless thee! Hark you, sir.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 2><SCENE 4><41%>
	Is your man secret? Did you ne'er hear say,
	Two may keep counsel, putting one away?
<SPEECH 40><ACT 2><SCENE 4><41%>
	Well, sir; my mistress is the sweetest lady—Lord, Lord!—when 'twas a little prating thing,—O! there's a nobleman in town, one Paris, that would fain lay knife aboard; but she, good soul, had as lief see a toad, a very toad, as see him. I anger her sometimes and tell her that Paris is the properer man; but, I'll warrant you, when I say so, she looks as pale as any clout in the versal world. Doth not rosemary and Romeo begin both with a letter?
<SPEECH 41><ACT 2><SCENE 4><42%>
	Ah! mocker; that's the dog's name. R is for the—No; I know it begins with some other letter: and she had the prettiest sententious of it, of you and rosemary, that it would do you good to hear it.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 2><SCENE 4><42%>
	Ay, a thousand times. <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> Peter!
<SPEECH 43><ACT 2><SCENE 4><42%>
	Before, and apace.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 2><SCENE 5><43%>
	Peter, stay at the gate.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 2><SCENE 5><43%>
	I am aweary, give me leave awhile:
	Fie, how my bones ache! What a jaunce have I had!
<SPEECH 46><ACT 2><SCENE 5><43%>
	Jesu! what haste? can you not stay awhile?
	Do you not see that I am out of breath?
<SPEECH 47><ACT 2><SCENE 5><43%>
	Well, you have made a simple choice; you know not how to choose a man: Romeo! no, not he; though his face be better than any man's, yet his leg excels all men's; and for a hand, and a foot, and a body, though they be not to be talked on, yet they are past compare. He is not the flower of courtesy, but, I'll warrant him, as gentle as a lamb. Go thy ways, wench; serve God. What! have you dined at home?
<SPEECH 48><ACT 2><SCENE 5><44%>
	Lord! how my head aches; what a head have I!
	It beats as it would fall in twenty pieces.
	My back o' t'other side; O! my back, my back!
	Beshrew your heart for sending me about,
	To catch my death with jauncing up and down.
<SPEECH 49><ACT 2><SCENE 5><44%>
	Your love says, like an honest gentleman, and a courteous, and a kind, and a handsome, and, I warrant, a virtuous,—Where is your mother?
<SPEECH 50><ACT 2><SCENE 5><44%>
	O! God's lady dear,
	Are you so hot? Marry, come up, I trow;
	Is this the poultice for my aching bones?
	Henceforward do your messages yourself.
<SPEECH 51><ACT 2><SCENE 5><44%>
	Have you got leave to go to shrift to-day?
<SPEECH 52><ACT 2><SCENE 5><44%>
	Then hie you hence to Friar Laurence' cell,
	There stays a husband to make you a wife:
	Now comes the wanton blood up in your cheeks,
	They'll be in scarlet straight at any news.
	Hie you to church; I must another way,
	To fetch a ladder, by the which your love
	Must climb a bird's nest soon when it is dark;
	I am the drudge and toil in your delight,
	But you shall bear the burden soon at night.
	Go; I'll to dinner: hie you to the cell.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 3><SCENE 2><54%>
	Ay, ay, the cords.
<SPEECH 54><ACT 3><SCENE 2><54%>
	Ah well-a-day! he's dead, he's dead, he's dead!
	We are undone, lady, we are undone!
	Alack the day! he's gone, he's killed, he's dead!
<SPEECH 55><ACT 3><SCENE 2><54%>
	Romeo can,
	Though heaven cannot. O! Romeo, Romeo;
	Who ever would have thought it? Romeo!
<SPEECH 56><ACT 3><SCENE 2><54%>
	I saw the wound, I saw it with mine eyes,
	God save the mark! here on his manly breast:
	A piteous corse, a bloody piteous corse;
	Pale, pale as ashes, all bedaub'd in blood,
	All in gore blood; I swounded at the sight.
<SPEECH 57><ACT 3><SCENE 2><54%>
	O Tybalt, Tybalt! the best friend I had:
	O courteous Tybalt! honest gentleman!
	That ever I should live to see thee dead!
<SPEECH 58><ACT 3><SCENE 2><55%>
	Tybalt is gone, and Romeo banished;
	Romeo, that kill'd him, he is banished.
<SPEECH 59><ACT 3><SCENE 2><55%>
	It did, it did; alas the day! it did.
<SPEECH 60><ACT 3><SCENE 2><55%>
	There's no trust,
	No faith, no honesty in men; all naught,
	All perjur'd, all dissemblers, all forsworn.
	Ah! where's my man? give me some aqua vitæ:
	These griefs, these woes, these sorrows make me old.
	Shame come to Romeo!
<SPEECH 61><ACT 3><SCENE 2><55%>
	Will you speak well of him that kill'd your cousin?
<SPEECH 62><ACT 3><SCENE 2><56%>
	Weeping and wailing over Tybalt's corse:
	Will you go to them? I will bring you thither.
<SPEECH 63><ACT 3><SCENE 2><57%>
	Hie to your chamber; I'll find Romeo
	To comfort you: I wot well where he is.
	Hark ye, your Romeo will be here to-night:
	I'll to him; he is hid at Laurence' cell.
<SPEECH 64><ACT 3><SCENE 3><60%>
	</STAGE DIR> Let me come in, and you shall know my errand:
	I come from Lady Juliet.
<SPEECH 65><ACT 3><SCENE 3><60%>
	O holy friar! O! tell me, holy friar,
	Where is my lady's lord? where's Romeo?
<SPEECH 66><ACT 3><SCENE 3><60%>
	O! he is even in my mistress' case,
	Just in her case!
<SPEECH 67><ACT 3><SCENE 3><60%>
	Ah, sir! ah, sir! Well, death's the end of all.
<SPEECH 68><ACT 3><SCENE 3><60%>
	O! she says nothing, sir, but weeps and weeps;
	And now falls on her bed; and then starts up,
	And Tybalt calls, and then on Romeo cries,
	And then down falls again.
<SPEECH 69><ACT 3><SCENE 3><62%>
	O Lord! I could have stay'd here all the night
	To hear good counsel: O! what learning is.
	My lord, I'll tell my lady you will come.
<SPEECH 70><ACT 3><SCENE 3><62%>
	Here, sir, a ring she bid me give you, sir.
	Hie you, make haste, for it grows very late.
<SPEECH 71><ACT 3><SCENE 5><65%>
	Madam!
<SPEECH 72><ACT 3><SCENE 5><65%>
	Your lady mother is coming to your chamber:
	The day is broke; be wary, look about.
<SPEECH 73><ACT 3><SCENE 5><69%>
	God in heaven bless her!
	You are to blame, my lord, to rate her so.
<SPEECH 74><ACT 3><SCENE 5><70%>
	I speak no treason.
<SPEECH 75><ACT 3><SCENE 5><70%>
	May not one speak?
<SPEECH 76><ACT 3><SCENE 5><71%>
	Faith, here it is. Romeo
	Is banished; and all the world to nothing
	That he dares ne'er come back to challenge you;
	Or, if he do, it needs must be by stealth.
	Then, since the case so stands as now it doth,
	I think it best you married with the county.
	O! he's a lovely gentleman;
	Romeo's a dishclout to him: an eagle, madam,
	Hath not so green, so quick, so fair an eye
	As Paris hath. Beshrew my very heart,
	I think you are happy in this second match,
	For it excels your first: or if it did not,
	Your first is dead; or 'twere as good he were,
	As living here and you no use of him.
<SPEECH 77><ACT 3><SCENE 5><71%>
	And from my soul too;
	Or else beshrew them both.
<SPEECH 78><ACT 3><SCENE 5><71%>
	What!
<SPEECH 79><ACT 3><SCENE 5><71%>
	Marry, I will; and this is wisely done.
<SPEECH 80><ACT 4><SCENE 2><76%>
	Ay, forsooth.
<SPEECH 81><ACT 4><SCENE 2><76%>
	See where she comes from shrift with merry look.
<SPEECH 82><ACT 4><SCENE 4><80%>
	They call for dates and quinces in the pastry.
<SPEECH 83><ACT 4><SCENE 4><80%>
	Go, go, you cot-quean, go;
	Get you to bed; faith, you'll be sick to-morrow
	For this night's watching.
<SPEECH 84><ACT 4><SCENE 5><81%>
	Mistress! what, mistress! Juliet! fast, I warrant her, she:
	Why, lamb! why, lady! fie, you slug-a-bed!
	Why, love, I say! madam! sweet-heart! why, bride!
	What! not a word? you take your pennyworths now:
	Sleep for a week; for the next night, I warrant,
	The County Paris hath set up his rest,
	That you shall rest but little. God forgive me,
	Marry, and amen, how sound is she asleep!
	I needs must wake her. Madam, madam, madam!
	Ay, let the county take you in your bed;
	He'll fright you up, i' faith. Will it not be?
	What, dress'd! and in your clothes! and down again!
	I must needs wake you. Lady! lady! lady!
	Alas! alas! Help! help! my lady's dead!
	O! well-a-day, that ever I was born.
	Some aqua-vitæ, ho! My lord! my lady!
<SPEECH 85><ACT 4><SCENE 5><81%>
	O lamentable day!
<SPEECH 86><ACT 4><SCENE 5><81%>
	Look, look! O heavy day!
<SPEECH 87><ACT 4><SCENE 5><82%>
	She's dead, deceas'd, she's dead; alack the day!
<SPEECH 88><ACT 4><SCENE 5><82%>
	O lamentable day!
<SPEECH 89><ACT 4><SCENE 5><83%>
	O woe! O woeful, woeful, woeful day!
	Most lamentable day, most woeful day,
	That ever, ever, I did yet behold!
	O day! O day! O day! O hateful day!
	Never was seen so black a day as this:
	O woeful day, O woeful day!
<SPEECH 90><ACT 4><SCENE 5><84%>
	Honest good fellows, ah! put up, put up, for, well you know, this is a pitiful case.
