<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 3><12%>
	Do you doubt that?
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 3><12%>
	No more but so?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 3><13%>
	I shall th' effect of this good lesson keep,
	As watchman to my heart. But, good my brother,
	Do not, as some ungracious pastors do,
	Show me the steep and thorny way to heaven,
	Whiles, like a puff'd and reckless libertine,
	Himself the primrose path of dalliance treads,
	And recks not his own rede.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 3><14%>
	'Tis in my memory lock'd,
	And you yourself shall keep the key of it.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 3><14%>
	So please you, something touching the Lord Hamlet.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 3><14%>
	He hath, my lord, of late made many tenders
	Of his affection to me.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 3><14%>
	I do not know, my lord, what I should think.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 3><14%>
	My lord, he hath importun'd me with love
	In honourable fashion.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 3><14%>
	And hath given countenance to his speech, my lord,
	With almost all the holy vows of heaven.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 3><15%>
	I shall obey, my lord.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	Alas! my lord, I have been so affrighted.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	My lord, as I was sewing in my closet,
	Lord Hamlet, with his doublet all unbrac'd;
	No hat upon his head; his stockings foul'd,
	Ungarter'd, and down-gyved to his ancle;
	Pale as his shirt; his knees knocking each other;
	And with a look so piteous in purport
	As if he had been loosed out of hell
	To speak of horrors, he comes before me.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	My lord, I do not know;
	But truly I do fear it.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	He took me by the wrist and held me hard,
	Then goes he to the length of all his arm,
	And, with his other hand thus o'er his brow,
	He falls to such perusal of my face
	As he would draw it. Long stay'd he so;
	At last, a little shaking of mine arm,
	And thrice his head thus waving up and down,
	He rais'd a sigh so piteous and profound
	That it did seem to shatter all his bulk
	And end his being. That done, he lets me go,
	And, with his head over his shoulder turn'd,
	He seem'd to find his way without his eyes;
	For out o' doors he went without their help,
	And to the last bended their light on me.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	No, my good lord; but, as you did command,
	I did repel his letters and denied
	His access to me.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 3><SCENE 1><42%>
	Madam, I wish it may.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 3><SCENE 1><43%>
	Good my lord,
	How does your honour for this many a day?
<SPEECH 18><ACT 3><SCENE 1><43%>
	My lord, I have remembrances of yours,
	That I have longed long to re-deliver;
	I pray you, now receive them.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 3><SCENE 1><43%>
	My honour'd lord, you know right well you did;
	And, with them, words of so sweet breath compos'd
	As made the things more rich: their perfume lost,
	Take these again; for to the noble mind
	Rich gifts wax poor when givers prove unkind.
	There, my lord.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 3><SCENE 1><43%>
	My lord!
<SPEECH 21><ACT 3><SCENE 1><43%>
	What means your lordship?
<SPEECH 22><ACT 3><SCENE 1><43%>
	Could beauty, my lord, have better commerce than with honesty?
<SPEECH 23><ACT 3><SCENE 1><43%>
	Indeed, my lord, you made me believe so.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 3><SCENE 1><44%>
	I was the more deceived.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 3><SCENE 1><44%>
	At home, my lord.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 3><SCENE 1><44%>
	O! help him, you sweet heavens!
<SPEECH 27><ACT 3><SCENE 1><44%>
	O heavenly powers, restore him!
<SPEECH 28><ACT 3><SCENE 1><44%>
	O! what a noble mind is here o'erthrown:
	The courtier's, soldier's, scholar's, eye, tongue, sword;
	The expectancy and rose of the fair state,
	The glass of fashion and the mould of form,
	The observ'd of all observers, quite, quite down!
	And I, of ladies most deject and wretched,
	That suck'd the honey of his music vows,
	Now see that noble and most sovereign reason,
	Like sweet bells jangled, out of tune and harsh;
	That unmatch'd form and feature of blown youth
	Blasted with ecstasy: O! woe is me,
	To have seen what I have seen, see what I see!
<SPEECH 29><ACT 3><SCENE 2><49%>
	No, my lord.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 3><SCENE 2><49%>
	Ay, my lord.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 3><SCENE 2><49%>
	I think nothing, my lord.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 3><SCENE 2><49%>
	What is, my lord?
<SPEECH 33><ACT 3><SCENE 2><49%>
	You are merry, my lord.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 3><SCENE 2><49%>
	Ay, my lord.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 3><SCENE 2><49%>
	Nay, 'tis twice two months, my lord.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 3><SCENE 2><50%>
	What means this, my lord?
<SPEECH 37><ACT 3><SCENE 2><50%>
	Belike this show imports the argument of the play.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 3><SCENE 2><50%>
	Will he tell us what this show meant?
<SPEECH 39><ACT 3><SCENE 2><50%>
	You are naught, you are naught. I'll mark the play.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 3><SCENE 2><50%>
	'Tis brief, my lord.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 3><SCENE 2><52%>
	You are a good chorus, my lord.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 3><SCENE 2><52%>
	You are keen, my lord, you are keen.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 3><SCENE 2><52%>
	Still better, and worse.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 3><SCENE 2><53%>
	The king rises.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 4><SCENE 5><71%>
	Where is the beauteous majesty of Denmark?
<SPEECH 46><ACT 4><SCENE 5><71%>
	How should I your true love know
	From another one?
	By his cockle hat and staff,
	And his sandal shoon.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 4><SCENE 5><71%>
	Say you? nay, pray you, mark.
	He is dead and gone, lady,
	He is dead and gone;
	At his head a grass-green turf;
	At his heals a stone.
	O, ho!
<SPEECH 48><ACT 4><SCENE 5><71%>
	Pray you, mark.
	White his shroud as the mountain snow,—
<SPEECH 49><ACT 4><SCENE 5><71%>
	Larded with sweet flowers;
	Which bewept to the grave did go
	With true-love showers.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 4><SCENE 5><71%>
	Well, God 'ild you! They say the owl was a baker's daughter. Lord! we know what we are, but know not what we may be. God be at your table!
<SPEECH 51><ACT 4><SCENE 5><71%>
	Pray you, let's have no words of this; but when they ask you what it means, say you this:
	To-morrow is Saint Valentine's day,
	All in the morning betime,
	And I a maid at your window,
	To be your Valentine:
	Then up he rose, and donn'd his clothes,
	And dupp'd the chamber door;
	Let in the maid, that out a maid
	Never departed more.
<SPEECH 52><ACT 4><SCENE 5><71%>
	Indeed, la! without an oath, I'll make an end on 't:
	By Gis and by Saint Charity,
	Alack, and fie for shame!
	Young men will do't, if they come to't;
	By Cock they are to blame.
	Quoth she, before you tumbled me,
	You promis'd me to wed:
	So would I ha' done, by yonder sun,
	An thou hadst not come to my bed.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 4><SCENE 5><72%>
	I hope all will be well. We must be patient: but I cannot choose but weep, to think they should lay him i' the cold ground. My brother shall know of it: and so I thank you for your good counsel. Come, my coach! Good-night, ladies; good-night, sweet ladies; good-night, good-night.
<SPEECH 54><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	They bore him barefac'd on the bier;
	Hey non nonny, nonny, hey nonny;
	And in his grave rain'd many a tear;—
	Fare you well, my dove!
<SPEECH 55><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	You must sing, a-down a-down,
	And you call him a-down-a.
	O how the wheel becomes it! It is the false steward that stole his master's daughter.
<SPEECH 56><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	There's rosemary, that's for remembrance; brance; pray, love, remember: and there is pansies, that's for thoughts.
<SPEECH 57><ACT 4><SCENE 5><75%>
	There's fennel for you, and columbines; there's rue for you; and here's some for me; we may call it herb of grace o' Sundays. O! you must wear your rue with a difference. There's a daisy; I would give you some violets, but they withered all when my father died. They say he made a good end,—
	For bonny sweet Robin is all my joy.
<SPEECH 58><ACT 4><SCENE 5><75%>
	And will he not come again?
	And will he not come again?
	No, no, he is dead;
	Go to thy death-bed,
	He never will come again.
	His beard was as white as snow
	All fiaxen was his poll,
	He is gone, he is gone,
	And we cast away moan:
	God ha' mercy on his soul!
	And of all Christian souls! I pray God. God be wi' ye!
