<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 2><6%>
	He hath, my lord, wrung from me my slow leave
	By laboursome petition, and at last
	Upon his will I seal'd my hard consent:
	I do beseech you, give him leave to go.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 3><13%>
	Yet here, Laertes! aboard, aboard, for shame!
	The wind sits in the shoulder of your sail,
	And you are stay'd for. There, my blessing with thee!
	And these few precepts in thy memory
	Look thou character. Give thy thoughts no tongue,
	Nor any unproportion'd thought his act.
	Be thou familiar, but by no means vulgar;
	The friends thou hast, and their adoption tried,
	Grapple them to thy soul with hoops of steel;
	But do not dull thy palm with entertainment
	Of each new-hatch'd, unfledg'd comrade. Beware
	Of entrance to a quarrel, but, being in,
	Bear 't that th' opposed may beware of thee.
	Give every man thine ear, but few thy voice;
	Take each man's censure, but reserve thy judgment.
	Costly thy habit as thy purse can buy,
	But not express'd in fancy; rich, not gaudy;
	For the apparel oft proclaims the man,
	And they in France of the best rank and station
	Are most select and generous, chief in that.
	Neither a borrower, nor a lender be;
	For loan oft loses both itself and friend,
	And borrowing dulls the edge of husbandry.
	This above all: to thine own self be true,
	And it must follow, as the night the day,
	Thou canst not then be false to any man.
	Farewell; my blessing season this in thee!
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 3><13%>
	The time invites you; go, your servants tend.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 3><14%>
	What is 't, Ophelia, he hath said to you?
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 3><14%>
	Marry, well bethought:
	'Tis told me, he hath very oft of late
	Given private time to you; and you yourself
	Have of your audience been most free and bounteous.
	If it be so,—as so 'tis put on me,
	And that in way of caution,—I must tell you,
	You do not understand yourself so clearly
	As it behoves my daughter and your honour.
	What is between you? give me up the truth.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 3><14%>
	Affection! pooh! you speak like a green girl,
	Unsifted in such perilous circumstance.
	Do you believe his tenders, as you call them?
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 3><14%>
	Marry, I'll teach you: think yourself a baby,
	That you have ta'en these tenders for true pay,
	Which are not sterling. Tender yourself more dearly;
	Or,—not to crack the wind of the poor phrase,
	Running it thus,—you'll tender me a fool.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 3><14%>
	Ay, fashion you may call it: go to, go to.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 3><14%>
	Ay, springes to catch woodcocks. I do know,
	When the blood burns, how prodigal the soul
	Lends the tongue vows: these blazes, daughter,
	Giving more light than heat, extinct in both,
	Even in their promise, as it is a-making,
	You must not take for fire. From this time
	Be somewhat scanter of your maiden presence;
	Set your entreatments at a higher rate
	Than a command to parley. For Lord Hamlet,
	Believe so much in him, that he is young,
	And with a larger tether may he walk
	Than may be given you: in few, Ophelia,
	Do not believe his vows, for they are brokers,
	Not of that dye which their investments show,
	But mere implorators of unholy suits,
	Breathing like sanctified and pious bawds,
	The better to beguile. This is for all:
	I would not, in plain terms, from this time forth,
	Have you so slander any moment's leisure,
	As to give words or talk with the Lord Hamlet.
	Look to 't, I charge you; come your ways.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 1><22%>
	Give him this money and these notes, Reynaldo.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 1><22%>
	You shall do marvellous wisely, good Reynaldo,
	Before you visit him, to make inquiry
	Of his behaviour.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 1><22%>
	Marry, well said, very well said. Look you, sir,
	Inquire me first what Danskers are in Paris;
	And how, and who, what means, and where they keep,
	What company, at what expense; and finding
	By this encompassment and drift of question
	That they do know my son, come you more nearer
	Than your particular demands will touch it:
	Take you, as 'twere, some distant knowledge of him;
	As thus, 'I know his father, and his friends,
	And, in part, him;' do you mark this, Reynaldo?
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	'And, in part, him; but,' you may say, 'not well:
	But if't be he I mean, he's very wild,
	Addicted so and so;' and there put on him
	What forgeries you please; marry, none so rank
	As may dishonour him; take heed of that;
	But, sir, such wanton, wild, and usual slips
	As are companions noted and most known
	To youth and liberty.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	Ay, or drinking, fencing, swearing, quarrelling,
	Drabbing; you may go so far.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	Faith, no; as you may season it in the charge.
	You must not put another scandal on him,
	That he is open to incontinency;
	That's not my meaning; but breathe his faults so quaintly
	That they may seem the taints of liberty,
	The flash and outbreak of a fiery mind,
	A savageness in unreclaimed blood,
	Of general assault.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	Wherefore should you do this?
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	Marry, sir, here's my drift;
	And, I believe, it is a fetch of warrant:
	You laying these slight sullies on my son,
	As 'twere a thing a little soil'd i' the working,
	Mark you,
	Your party in converse, him you would sound,
	Having ever seen in the prenominate crimes
	The youth you breathe of guilty, be assur'd,
	He closes with you in this consequence;
	'Good sir,' or so; or 'friend,' or 'gentleman,'
	According to the phrase or the addition
	Of man and country.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	And then, sir, does he this,—he does,—what was I about to say? By the mass I was about to say something: where did I leave?
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	At 'closes in the consequence,' ay, marry;
	He closes with you thus: 'I know the gentleman;
	I saw him yesterday, or t' other day,
	Or then, or then; with such, or such; and, as you say,
	There was a' gaming; there o'ertook in 's rouse;
	There falling out at tennis;' or perchance,
	'I saw him enter such a house of sale,'
	Videlicet, a brothel, or so forth.
	See you now;
	Your bait of falsehood takes this carp of truth;
	And thus do we of wisdom and of reach,
	With windlasses, and with assays of bias,
	By indirections find directions out:
	So by my former lecture and advice
	Shall you my son. You have me, have you not?
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	God be wi' you; fare you well.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	Observe his inclination in yourself.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	And let him ply his music.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	Farewell!
	How now, Ophelia! what's the matter?
<SPEECH 24><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	With what, in the name of God?
<SPEECH 25><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	Mad for thy love?
<SPEECH 26><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	What said he?
<SPEECH 27><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	Come, go with me; I will go seek the king.
	This is the very ecstasy of love,
	Whose violent property fordoes itself
	And leads the will to desperate undertakings
	As oft as any passion under heaven
	That does afflict our natures. I am sorry.
	What! have you given him any hard words of late?
<SPEECH 28><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	That hath made him mad.
	I am sorry that with better heed and judgment
	I had not quoted him; I fear'd he did but trifle,
	And meant to wrack thee; but, beshrew my jealousy!
	By heaven, it is as proper to our age
	To cast beyond ourselves in our opinions
	As it is common for the younger sort
	To lack discretion. Come, go we to the king:
	This must be known; which, being kept close, might move
	More grief to hide than hate to utter love.
	Come.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 2><SCENE 2><26%>
	The ambassadors from Norway, my good lord,
	Are joyfully return'd.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 2><SCENE 2><26%>
	Have I, my lord? Assure you, my good liege,
	I hold my duty, as I hold my soul,
	Both to my God and to my gracious king;
	And I do think—or else this brain of mine
	Hunts not the trail of policy so sure
	As it hath us'd to do—that I have found
	The very cause of Hamlet's lunacy.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	Give first admittance to the ambassadors;
	My news shall be the fruit to that great feast.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	This business is well ended.
	My liege, and madam, to expostulate
	What majesty should be, what duty is,
	Why day is day, night night, and time is time,
	Were nothing but to waste night, day, and time.
	Therefore, since brevity is the soul of wit,
	And tediousness the limbs and outward flourishes,
	I will be brief. Your noble son is mad:
	Mad call I it; for, to define true madness,
	What is 't but to be nothing else but mad?
	But let that go.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	Madam, I swear I use no art at all.
	That he is mad, 'tis true; 'tis true 'tis pity;
	And pity 'tis 'tis true: a foolish figure;
	But farewell it, for I will use no art.
	Mad let us grant him, then; and now remains
	That we find out the cause of this effect,
	Or rather say, the cause of this defect,
	For this effect defective comes by cause;
	Thus it remains, and the remainder thus.
	Perpend.
	I have a daughter, have while she is mine;
	Who, in her duty and obedience, mark,
	Hath given me this: now, gather, and surmise.
	"To the celestial, and my soul's idol, the most beautified Ophelia.—"
	That's an ill phrase, a vile phrase; 'beautified'
	is a vile phrase; but you shall hear. Thus:
	In her excellent white bosom, these, &c.—
<SPEECH 34><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	Good madam, stay awhile; I will be faithful.
	"Doubt thou the stars are fire;
	Doubt that the sun doth move;
	Doubt truth to be a liar;
	But never doubt I love.
	O dear Ophelia! I am ill at these numbers: I have not art to reckon my groans; but that I love thee best, O most best! believe it. Adieu.
	Thine evermore, most dear lady, whilst this machine is to him,HAMLET."
	This in obedience hath my daughter shown me;
	And more above, hath his solicitings,
	As they fell out by time, by means, and place,
	All given to mine ear.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	What do you think of me?
<SPEECH 36><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	I would fain prove so. But what might you think,
	When I had seen this hot love on the wing,—
	As I perceiv'd it, I must tell you that,
	Before my daughter told me,—what might you,
	Or my dear majesty, your queen here, think,
	If I had play'd the desk or table-book,
	Or given my heart a winking, mute and dumb,
	Or look'd upon this love with idle sight;
	What might you think? No, I went round to work,
	And my young mistress thus I did bespeak:
	'Lord Hamlet is a prince, out of thy star;
	This must not be:' and then I precepts gave her,
	That she should lock herself from his resort,
	Admit no messengers, receive no tokens.
	Which done, she took the fruits of my advice;
	And he, repulsed,—a short tale to make,—
	Fell into a sadness, then into a fast,
	Thence to a watch, thence into a weakness,
	Thence to a lightness; and by this declension
	Into the madness wherein now he raves,
	And all we wail for.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	Hath there been such a time,—I'd fain know that,—
	That I have positively said, ''Tis so,'
	When it prov'd otherwise?
<SPEECH 38><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	Take this from this, if this be otherwise:
	If circumstances lead me, I will find
	Where truth is hid, though it were hid indeed
	Within the centre.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	You know sometimes he walks four hours together
	Here in the lobby.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	At such a time I'll loose my daughter to him;
	Be you and I behind an arras then;
	Mark the encounter; if he love her not,
	And be not from his reason fallen thereon,
	Let me be no assistant for a state,
	But keep a farm, and carters.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	Away! I do beseech you, both away.
	I'll board him presently.
	O! give me leave.
	How does my good Lord Hamlet?
<SPEECH 42><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	Do you know me, my lord?
<SPEECH 43><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	Not I, my lord.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	Honest, my lord!
<SPEECH 45><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	That's very true, my lord.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	I have, my lord.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	</STAGE DIR> How say you by that? Still harping on my daughter: yet he knew me not at first; he said I was a fishmonger: he is far gone, far gone: and truly in my youth I suffered much extremity for love; very near this. I'll speak to him again. What do you read, my lord?
<SPEECH 48><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	What is the matter, my lord?
<SPEECH 49><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	I mean the matter that you read, my lord.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	</STAGE DIR> Though this be madness, yet there is method in 't. Will you walk out of the air, my lord?
<SPEECH 51><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	Indeed, that is out o' the air. <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> How pregnant sometimes his replies are! a happiness that often madness hits on, which reason and sanity could not so prosperously be delivered of. I will leave him, and suddenly contrive the means of meeting between him and my daughter. My honourable lord, I will most humbly take my leave of you.
<SPEECH 52><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	Fare you well, my lord.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	You go to seek the Lord Hamlet; there he is.
<SPEECH 54><ACT 2><SCENE 2><35%>
	Well be with you, gentlemen!
<SPEECH 55><ACT 2><SCENE 2><35%>
	My lord, I have news to tell you.
<SPEECH 56><ACT 2><SCENE 2><35%>
	The actors are come hither, my lord.
<SPEECH 57><ACT 2><SCENE 2><35%>
	Upon my honour,—
<SPEECH 58><ACT 2><SCENE 2><35%>
	The best actors in the world, either for tragedy, comedy, history, pastoral, pastoral-comical, historical-pastoral, tragical-historical, tragical-comical-historical-pastoral, scene individable, or poem unlimited: Seneca cannot be too heavy, nor Plautus too light. For the law of writ and the liberty, these are the only men.
<SPEECH 59><ACT 2><SCENE 2><36%>
	What a treasure had he, my lord?
<SPEECH 60><ACT 2><SCENE 2><36%>
	</STAGE DIR> Still on my daughter.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 2><SCENE 2><36%>
	If you call me Jephthah, my lord, I have a daughter that I love passing well.
<SPEECH 62><ACT 2><SCENE 2><36%>
	What follows, then, my lord?
<SPEECH 63><ACT 2><SCENE 2><37%>
	'Fore God, my lord, well spoken; with good accent and good discretion.
<SPEECH 64><ACT 2><SCENE 2><38%>
	This is too long.
<SPEECH 65><ACT 2><SCENE 2><38%>
	That's good; 'mobled queen' is good.
<SPEECH 66><ACT 2><SCENE 2><38%>
	Look! wh'er he has not turned his colour and has tears in's eyes. Prithee, no more.
<SPEECH 67><ACT 2><SCENE 2><39%>
	My lord, I will use them according to their desert.
<SPEECH 68><ACT 2><SCENE 2><39%>
	Come, sirs.
<SPEECH 69><ACT 3><SCENE 1><41%>
	'Tis most true;
	And he beseech'd me to entreat your majesties
	To hear and see the matter.
<SPEECH 70><ACT 3><SCENE 1><42%>
	Ophelia, walk you here. Gracious, so please you,
	We will bestow ourselves. <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> Read on this book;
	That show of such an exercise may colour
	Your loneliness. We are oft to blame in this,
	'Tis too much prov'd, that with devotion's visage
	And pious action we do sugar o'er
	The devil himself.
<SPEECH 71><ACT 3><SCENE 1><42%>
	I hear him coming; let's withdraw, my lord.
<SPEECH 72><ACT 3><SCENE 1><45%>
	It shall do well: but yet do I believe
	The origin and commencement of his grief
	Sprung from neglected love. How now, Ophelia!
	You need not tell us what Lord Hamlet said;
	We heard it all. My lord, do as you please;
	But, if you hold it fit, after the play,
	Let his queen mother all alone entreat him
	To show his griefs: let her be round with him;
	And I'll be plac'd, so please you, in the ear
	Of all their conference. If she find him not,
	To England send him, or confine him where
	Your wisdom best shall think.
<SPEECH 73><ACT 3><SCENE 2><47%>
	And the queen too, and that presently.
<SPEECH 74><ACT 3><SCENE 2><48%>
	That did I, my lord, and was accounted a good actor.
<SPEECH 75><ACT 3><SCENE 2><48%>
	I did enact Julius Cæsar: I was killed i' the Capitol; Brutus killed me.
<SPEECH 76><ACT 3><SCENE 2><48%>
	</STAGE DIR> O ho! do you mark that?
<SPEECH 77><ACT 3><SCENE 2><53%>
	Give o'er the play.
<SPEECH 78><ACT 3><SCENE 2><55%>
	My lord, the queen would speak with you, and presently.
<SPEECH 79><ACT 3><SCENE 2><55%>
	By the mass, and 'tis like a camel, indeed.
<SPEECH 80><ACT 3><SCENE 2><55%>
	It is backed like a weasel.
<SPEECH 81><ACT 3><SCENE 2><55%>
	Very like a whale.
<SPEECH 82><ACT 3><SCENE 2><55%>
	I will say so.
<SPEECH 83><ACT 3><SCENE 3><57%>
	My lord, he's going to his mother's closet:
	Behind the arras I'll convey myself
	To hear the process; I'll warrant she'll tax him home;
	And, as you said, and wisely was it said,
	'Tis meet that some more audience than a mother,
	Since nature makes them partial, should o'erhear
	The speech, of vantage. Fare you well, my liege:
	I'll call upon you ere you go to bed
	And tell you what I know.
<SPEECH 84><ACT 3><SCENE 4><59%>
	He will come straight. Look you lay home to him;
	Tell him his pranks have been too broad to bear with,
	And that your Grace hath screen'd and stood between
	Much heat and him. I'll silence me e'en here.
	Pray you, be round with him.
<SPEECH 85><ACT 3><SCENE 4><59%>
	</STAGE DIR> What, ho! help! help! help!
<SPEECH 86><ACT 3><SCENE 4><59%>
	</STAGE DIR> O! I am slain.
