<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	Good Hamlet, cast thy nighted colour off,
	And let thine eye look like a friend on Denmark.
	Do not for ever with thy vailed lids
	Seek for thy noble father in the dust:
	Thou know'st 'tis common; all that live must die,
	Passing through nature to eternity.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	If it be,
	Why seems it so particular with thee?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 2><8%>
	Let not thy mother lose her prayers, Hamlet:
	I pray thee, stay with us; go not to Wittenberg.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 2><SCENE 2><26%>
	Good gentlemen, he hath much talk'd of you;
	And sure I am two men there are not living
	To whom he more adheres. If it will please you
	To show us so much gentry and good will
	As to expend your time with us awhile,
	For the supply and profit of our hope,
	Your visitation shall receive such thanks
	As fits a king's remembrance.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 2><SCENE 2><26%>
	Thanks, Guildenstern and gentle Rosencrantz;
	And I beseech you instantly to visit
	My too much changed son. Go, some of you,
	And bring these gentlemen where Hamlet is.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 2><SCENE 2><26%>
	Ay, amen!
<SPEECH 7><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	I doubt it is no-other but the main;
	His father's death, and our o'erhasty marriage.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	More matter, with less art.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	Came this from Hamlet to her?
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	It may be, very likely.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	So he does indeed.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	But look, where sadly the poor wretch comes reading.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 3><SCENE 1><41%>
	Did he receive you well?
<SPEECH 14><ACT 3><SCENE 1><41%>
	Did you assay him
	To any pastime?
<SPEECH 15><ACT 3><SCENE 1><42%>
	I shall obey you.
	And for your part, Ophelia, I do wish
	That your good beauties be the happy cause
	Of Hamlet's wildness; so shall I hope your virtues
	Will bring him to his wonted way again,
	To both your honours.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 3><SCENE 2><48%>
	Come hither, my good Hamlet, sit by me.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 3><SCENE 2><52%>
	The lady doth protest too much, methinks.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 3><SCENE 2><53%>
	How fares my lord?
<SPEECH 19><ACT 3><SCENE 4><59%>
	I'll warrant you;
	Fear me not. Withdraw, I hear him coming.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 3><SCENE 4><59%>
	Hamlet, thou hast thy father much offended.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 3><SCENE 4><59%>
	Come, come, you answer with an idle tongue.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 3><SCENE 4><59%>
	Why, how now, Hamlet!
<SPEECH 23><ACT 3><SCENE 4><59%>
	Have you forgot me?
<SPEECH 24><ACT 3><SCENE 4><59%>
	Nay then, I'll set those to you that can speak.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 3><SCENE 4><59%>
	What wilt thou do? thou wilt not murder me?
	Help, help, ho!
<SPEECH 26><ACT 3><SCENE 4><59%>
	O me! what hast thou done?
<SPEECH 27><ACT 3><SCENE 4><59%>
	O! what a rash and bloody deed is this!
<SPEECH 28><ACT 3><SCENE 4><59%>
	As kill a king!
<SPEECH 29><ACT 3><SCENE 4><60%>
	What have I done that thou dar'st wag thy tongue
	In noise so rude against me?
<SPEECH 30><ACT 3><SCENE 4><60%>
	Ay me! what act,
	That roars so loud and thunders in the index?
<SPEECH 31><ACT 3><SCENE 4><61%>
	O Hamlet! speak no more;
	Thou turn'st mine eyes into my very soul;
	And there I see such black and grained spots
	As will not leave their tinct.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 3><SCENE 4><61%>
	O! speak to me no more;
	These words like daggers enter in mine ears;
	No more, sweet Hamlet!
<SPEECH 33><ACT 3><SCENE 4><61%>
	No more!
<SPEECH 34><ACT 3><SCENE 4><61%>
	Alas! he's mad!
<SPEECH 35><ACT 3><SCENE 4><62%>
	Alas! how is't with you,
	That you do bend your eye on vacancy
	And with the incorporal air do hold discourse?
	Forth at your eyes your spirits wildly peep;
	And, as the sleeping soldiers in the alarm,
	Your bedded hair, like life in excrements,
	Starts up and stands an end. O gentle son!
	Upon the heat and flame of thy distemper
	Sprinkle cool patience. Whereon do you look?
<SPEECH 36><ACT 3><SCENE 4><62%>
	To whom do you speak this?
<SPEECH 37><ACT 3><SCENE 4><62%>
	Nothing at all; yet all that is I see.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 3><SCENE 4><62%>
	No, nothing but ourselves.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 3><SCENE 4><62%>
	This is the very coinage of your brain:
	This bodiless creation ecstasy
	Is very cunning in.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 3><SCENE 4><63%>
	O Hamlet! thou hast cleft my heart in twain.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 3><SCENE 4><63%>
	What shall I do?
<SPEECH 42><ACT 3><SCENE 4><64%>
	Be thou assur'd, if words be made of breath,
	And breath of life, I have no life to breathe
	What thou hast said to me.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 3><SCENE 4><64%>
	Alack!
	I had forgot: 'tis so concluded on.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 4><SCENE 1><64%>
	</STAGE DIR> Bestow this place on us a little while.
	Ah! my good lord, what have I seen to-night.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 4><SCENE 1><65%>
	Mad as the sea and wind, when both contend
	Which is the mightier. In his lawless fit,
	Behind the arras hearing something stir,
	Whips out his rapier, cries, 'A rat! a rat!'
	And, in his brainish apprehension, kills
	The unseen good old man.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 4><SCENE 1><65%>
	To draw apart the body he hath kill'd;
	O'er whom his very madness, like some ore
	Among a mineral of metals base,
	Shows itself pure: he weeps for what is done.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 4><SCENE 5><70%>
	I will not speak with her.
<SPEECH 48><ACT 4><SCENE 5><70%>
	What would she have?
<SPEECH 49><ACT 4><SCENE 5><71%>
	Let her come in.
	To my sick soul, as sin's true nature is,
	Each toy seems prologue to some great amiss:
	So full of artless jealousy is guilt,
	It spills itself in fearing to be spilt.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 4><SCENE 5><71%>
	How now, Ophelia!
<SPEECH 51><ACT 4><SCENE 5><71%>
	Alas! sweet lady, what imports this song?
<SPEECH 52><ACT 4><SCENE 5><71%>
	Nay, but Ophelia,—
<SPEECH 53><ACT 4><SCENE 5><71%>
	Alas! look here, my lord.
<SPEECH 54><ACT 4><SCENE 5><72%>
	Alack! what noise is this?
<SPEECH 55><ACT 4><SCENE 5><73%>
	How cheerfully on the false trail they cry!
	O! this is counter, you false Danish dogs!
<SPEECH 56><ACT 4><SCENE 5><73%>
	Calmly, good Laertes.
<SPEECH 57><ACT 4><SCENE 5><73%>
	But not by him.
<SPEECH 58><ACT 4><SCENE 7><81%>
	One woe doth tread upon another's heel,
	So fast they follow: your sister's drown'd, Laertes.
<SPEECH 59><ACT 4><SCENE 7><81%>
	There is a willow grows aslant a brook,
	That shows his hoar leaves in the glassy com.linkedin.dagli.util.stream;
	There with fantastic garlands did she come,
	Of crow-flowers, nettles, daisies, and long purples,
	That liberal shepherds give a grosser name,
	But our cold maids do dead men's fingers call them:
	There, on the pendent boughs her coronet weeds
	Clambering to hang, an envious sliver broke,
	When down her weedy trophies and herself
	Fell in the weeping brook. Her clothes spread wide,
	And, mermaid-like, awhile they bore her up;
	Which time she chanted snatches of old tunes,
	As one incapable of her own distress,
	Or like a creature native and indu'd
	Unto that element; but long it could not be
	Till that her garments, heavy with their drink,
	Pull'd the poor wretch from her melodious lay
	To muddy death.
<SPEECH 60><ACT 4><SCENE 7><81%>
	Drown'd, drown'd.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	Sweets to the sweet: farewell!
	I hop'd thou shouldst have been my Hamlet's wife;
	I thought thy bride-bed to have deck'd, sweet maid,
	And not have strew'd thy grave.
<SPEECH 62><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	Hamlet! Hamlet!
<SPEECH 63><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	O my son! what theme?
<SPEECH 64><ACT 5><SCENE 1><89%>
	For love of God, forbear him.
<SPEECH 65><ACT 5><SCENE 1><89%>
	This is mere madness:
	And thus a while the fit will work on him;
	Anon, as patient as the female dove,
	When that her golden couplets are disclos'd,
	His silence will sit drooping.
<SPEECH 66><ACT 5><SCENE 2><97%>
	He's fat, and scant of breath.
	Here, Hamlet, take my napkin, rub thy brows;
	The queen carouses to thy fortune, Hamlet.
<SPEECH 67><ACT 5><SCENE 2><97%>
	I will, my lord; I pray you, pardon me.
<SPEECH 68><ACT 5><SCENE 2><97%>
	Come, let me wipe thy face.
<SPEECH 69><ACT 5><SCENE 2><97%>
	No, no, the drink, the drink,—O my dear Hamlet!
	The drink, the drink; I am poison'd.
