<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><6%>
	Is the day so young?
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><6%>
	Ay me! sad hours seem long.
	Was that my father that went hence so fast?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 1><6%>
	Not having that, which having, makes them short.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 1><6%>
	Out—
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 1><6%>
	Out of her favour, where I am in love.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 1><6%>
	Alas! that love, whose view is muffled still,
	Should, without eyes, see pathways to his will.
	Where shall we dine? O me! What fray was here?
	Yet tell me not, for I have heard it all.
	Here's much to do with hate, but more with love:
	Why then, O brawling love! O loving hate!
	O any thing! of nothing first create.
	O heavy lightness! serious vanity!
	Mis-shapen chaos of well-seeming forms!
	Feather of lead, bright smoke, cold fire, sick health!
	Still-waking sleep, that is not what it is!
	This love feel I, that feel no love in this.
	Dost thou not laugh?
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	Good heart, at what?
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	Why, such is love's transgression.
	Griefs of mine own lie heavy in my breast,
	Which thou wilt propagate to have it press'd
	With more of thine: this love that thou hast shown
	Doth add more grief to too much of mine own.
	Love is a smoke rais'd with the fume of sighs;
	Being purg'd, a fire sparkling in lovers' eyes;
	Being vex'd, a sea nourish'd with lovers' tears:
	What is it else? a madness most discreet,
	A choking gall, and a preserving sweet.
	Farewell, my coz.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	Tut! I have lost myself; I am not here;
	This is not Romeo, he's some other where.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	What! shall I groan and tell thee?
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	Bid a sick man in sadness make his will;
	Ah! word ill urg'd to one that is so ill.
	In sadness, cousin, I do love a woman.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 1><8%>
	A right good mark-man! And she's fair I love.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 1><SCENE 1><8%>
	Well, in that hit you miss: she'll not be hit
	With Cupid's arrow; she hath Dian's wit;
	And, in strong proof of chastity well arm'd,
	From love's weak childish bow she lives unharm'd.
	She will not stay the siege of loving terms,
	Nor bide the encounter of assailing eyes,
	Nor ope her lap to saint-seducing gold:
	O! she is rich in beauty; only poor
	That, when she dies, with beauty dies her store.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 1><SCENE 1><8%>
	She hath, and in that sparing makes huge waste;
	For beauty, starv'd with her severity,
	Cuts beauty off from all posterity.
	She is too fair, too wise, wisely too fair,
	To merit bliss by making me despair:
	She hath forsworn to love, and in that vow
	Do I live dead that live to tell it now.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 1><SCENE 1><8%>
	O! teach me how I should forget to think.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 1><SCENE 1><8%>
	'Tis the way
	To call hers exquisite, in question more.
	These happy masks that kiss fair ladies' brows
	Being black put us in mind they hide the fair;
	He, that is strucken blind cannot forget
	The precious treasure of his eyesight lost:
	Show me a mistress that is passing fair,
	What doth her beauty serve but as a note
	Where I may read who pass'd that passing fair?
	Farewell: thou canst not teach me to forget.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 1><SCENE 2><10%>
	Your plantain leaf is excellent for that.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 1><SCENE 2><10%>
	For your broken shin.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 1><SCENE 2><10%>
	Not mad, but bound more than a madman is;
	Shut up in prison, kept without my food,
	Whipp'd and tormented, and—Good den, good fellow.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	Ay, mine own fortune in my misery.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	Ay, if I know the letters and the language.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	Stay, fellow; I can read.
	Signior Martino and his wife and daughters; County Anselme and his beauteous sisters; the lady widow of Vitruvio; Signior Placentio, and his lovely nieces; Mercutio and his brother Valentine; mine uncle Capulet, his wife and daughters; my fair niece Rosaline; Livia; Signior Valentio and his cousin Tybalt; Lucio and the lively Helena.
	A fair assembly: whither should they come?
<SPEECH 23><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	Whither?
<SPEECH 24><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	Whose house?
<SPEECH 25><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	Indeed, I should have asked you that before.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	When the devout religion of mine eye
	Maintains such falsehood, then turn tears to fires!
	And these, who often drown'd could never die,
	Transparent heretics, be burnt for liars!
	One fairer than my love! the all-seeing sun
	Ne'er saw her match since first the world begun.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 1><SCENE 2><12%>
	I'll go along, no such sight to be shown,
	But to rejoice in splendour of mine own.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 1><SCENE 4><16%>
	What! shall this speech be spoke for our excuse,
	Or shall we on without apology?
<SPEECH 29><ACT 1><SCENE 4><16%>
	Give me a torch: I am not for this ambling;
	Being but heavy, I will bear the light.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 1><SCENE 4><16%>
	Not I, believe me: you have dancing shoes
	With nimble soles; I have a soul of lead
	So stakes me to the ground I cannot move.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 1><SCENE 4><16%>
	I am too sore enpierced with his shaft
	To soar with his light feathers; and so bound
	I cannot bound a pitch above dull woe:
	Under love's heavy burden do I sink.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 1><SCENE 4><16%>
	Is love a tender thing? it is too rough,
	Too rude, too boisterous; and it pricks like thorn.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 1><SCENE 4><17%>
	A torch for me; let wantons, light of heart,
	Tickle the senseless rushes with their heels,
	For I am proverb'd with a grandsire phrase;
	I'll be a candle holder, and look on.
	The game was ne'er so fair, and I am done.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 1><SCENE 4><17%>
	Nay, that's not so.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 1><SCENE 4><17%>
	And we mean well in going to this masque;
	But 'tis no wit to go.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 1><SCENE 4><17%>
	I dream'd a dream to-night.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 1><SCENE 4><17%>
	Well, what was yours?
<SPEECH 38><ACT 1><SCENE 4><17%>
	In bed asleep, while they do dream things true.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 1><SCENE 4><19%>
	Peace, peace! Mercutio, peace!
	Thou talk'st of nothing.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 1><SCENE 4><19%>
	I fear too early; for my mind misgives
	Some consequence yet hanging in the stars
	Shall bitterly begin his fearful date
	With this night's revels, and expire the term
	Of a despised life clos'd in my breast
	By some vile forfeit of untimely death.
	But he, that hath the steerage of my course,
	Direct my sail!, On, lusty gentlemen.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 1><SCENE 5><21%>
	What lady is that which doth enrich the hand
	Of yonder knight?
<SPEECH 42><ACT 1><SCENE 5><21%>
	O! she doth teach the torches to burn bright.
	It seems she hangs upon the cheek of night
	Like a rich jewel in an Ethiop's ear;
	Beauty too rich for use, for earth too dear!
	So shows a snowy dove trooping with crows,
	As yonder lady o'er her fellows shows.
	The measure done, I'll watch her place of stand,
	And, touching hers, make blessed my rude hand.
	Did my heart love till now? forswear it, sight!
	For I ne'er saw true beauty till this night.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 1><SCENE 5><22%>
	</STAGE DIR> If I profane with my unworthiest hand
	This holy shrine, the gentle sin is this;
	My lips, two blushing pilgrims, ready stand
	To smooth that rough touch with a tenderkiss.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 1><SCENE 5><23%>
	Have not saints lips, and holy palmers too?
<SPEECH 45><ACT 1><SCENE 5><23%>
	O! then, dear saint, let lips do what hands do;
	They pray, grant thou, lest faith turn to despair.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 1><SCENE 5><23%>
	Then move not, while my prayers' effect I take.
	Thus from my lips, by thine, my sin is purg'd.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 1><SCENE 5><23%>
	Sin from my lips? O trespass sweetly urg'd!
	Give me my sin again.
<SPEECH 48><ACT 1><SCENE 5><23%>
	What is her mother?
<SPEECH 49><ACT 1><SCENE 5><23%>
	Is she a Capulet?
	O dear account! my life is my foe's debt.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 1><SCENE 5><23%>
	Ay, so I fear; the more is my unrest.
<SPEECH 51><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	Can I go forward when my heart is here?
	Turn back, dull earth, and find thy centre out.
<SPEECH 52><ACT 2><SCENE 2><26%>
	He jests at scars, that never felt a wound.
	But, soft! what light through yonder window breaks?
	It is the east, and Juliet is the sun!
	Arise, fair sun, and kill the envious moon,
	Who is already sick and pale with grief,
	That thou her maid art far more fair than she:
	Be not her maid, since she is envious;
	Her vestal livery is but sick and green,
	And none but fools do wear it; cast it off.
	It is my lady; O! it is my love:
	O! that she knew she were.
	She speaks, yet she says nothing: what of that?
	Her eye discourses; I will answer it.
	I am too bold, 'tis not to me she speaks:
	Two of the fairest stars in all the heaven,
	Having some business, do entreat her eyes
	To twinkle in their spheres till they return.
	What if her eyes were there, they in her head?
	The brightness of her cheek would shame those stars
	As daylight doth a lamp; her eyes in heaven
	Would through the airy region com.linkedin.dagli.util.stream so bright
	That birds would sing and think it were not night.
	See! how she leans her cheek upon her hand:
	O! that I were a glove upon that hand,
	That I might touch that cheek.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	She speaks:
	O! speak again, bright angel; for thou art
	As glorious to this night, being o'er my head,
	As is a winged messenger of heaven
	Unto the white-upturned wond'ring eyes
	Of mortals, that fall back to gaze on him
	When he bestrides the lazy-pacing clouds,
	And sails upon the bosom of the air.
<SPEECH 54><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	</STAGE DIR> Shall I hear more, or shall I speak at this?
<SPEECH 55><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	I take thee at thy word.
	Call me but love, and I'll be new baptiz'd;
	Henceforth I never will be Romeo.
<SPEECH 56><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	By a name
	I know not how to tall thee who I am:
	My name, dear saint, is hateful to myself,
	Because it is an enemy to thee:
	Had I it written, I would tear the word.
<SPEECH 57><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	Neither, fair maid, if either thee dislike.
<SPEECH 58><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	With love's light wings did I o'erperch these walls;
	For stony limits cannot hold love out,
	And what love can do that dares love attempt;
	Therefore thy kinsmen are no stop to me.
<SPEECH 59><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	Alack! there lies more peril in thine eye
	Than twenty of their swords: look thou but sweet,
	And I am proof against their enmity.
<SPEECH 60><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	I have night's cloak to hide me from their eyes;
	And but thou love me, let them find me here;
	My life were better ended by their hate,
	Than death prorogued, wanting of thy love.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	By Love, that first did prompt me to inquire;
	He lent me counsel, and I lent him eyes.
	I am no pilot; yet, wert thou as far
	As that vast shore wash'd with the furthest sea,
	I would adventure for such merchandise.
<SPEECH 62><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	Lady, by yonder blessed moon I swear
	That tips with silver all these fruit-tree tops,—
<SPEECH 63><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	What shall I swear by?
<SPEECH 64><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	If my heart's dear love—
<SPEECH 65><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	O! wilt thou leave me so unsatisfied?
<SPEECH 66><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	The exchange of thy love's faithful vow for mine.
<SPEECH 67><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	Wouldst thou withdraw it? for what purpose, love?
<SPEECH 68><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	O blessed, blessed night! I am afeard,
	Being in night, all this is but a dream,
	Too flattering-sweet to be substantial.
<SPEECH 69><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	So thrive my soul,—
<SPEECH 70><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	A thousand times the worse, to want thy light.
	Love goes toward love, as schoolboys from their books;
	But love from love, toward school with heavy looks.
<SPEECH 71><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	It is my soul that calls upon my name:
	How silver-sweet sound lovers' tongues by night,
	Like softest music to attending ears!
<SPEECH 72><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	My dear!
<SPEECH 73><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	At the hour of nine.
<SPEECH 74><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	Let me stand here till thou remember it.
<SPEECH 75><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	And I'll still stay, to have thee still forget,
	Forgetting any other home but this.
<SPEECH 76><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	I would I were thy bird.
<SPEECH 77><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	Sleep dwell upon thine eyes, peace in thy breast!
	Would I were sleep and peace, so sweet to rest!
	Hence will I to my ghostly father's cell,
	His help to crave, and my dear hap to tell.
<SPEECH 78><ACT 2><SCENE 3><33%>
	Good morrow, father!
<SPEECH 79><ACT 2><SCENE 3><34%>
	That last is true; the sweeter rest was mine.
<SPEECH 80><ACT 2><SCENE 3><34%>
	With Rosaline, my ghostly father? no;
	I have forgot that name, and that name's woe.
<SPEECH 81><ACT 2><SCENE 3><34%>
	I'll tell thee, ere thou ask it me again.
	I have been feasting with mine enemy,
	Where on a sudden one hath wounded me,
	That's by me wounded: both our remedies
	Within thy help and holy physic lies:
	I bear no hatred, blessed man; for, lo!
	My intercession likewise steads my foe.
<SPEECH 82><ACT 2><SCENE 3><34%>
	Then plainly know my heart's dear love is set
	On the fair daughter of rich Capulet:
	As mine on hers, so hers is set on mine;
	And all combin'd, save what thou must combine
	By holy marriage: when and where and how
	We met we woo'd and made exchange of vow,
	I'll tell thee as we pass; but this I pray,
	That thou consent to marry us to-day.
<SPEECH 83><ACT 2><SCENE 3><35%>
	Thou chidd'st me oft for loving Rosaline.
<SPEECH 84><ACT 2><SCENE 3><35%>
	And bad'st me bury love.
<SPEECH 85><ACT 2><SCENE 3><35%>
	I pray thee, chide not; she, whom I love now
	Doth grace for grace and love for love allow;
	The other did not so.
<SPEECH 86><ACT 2><SCENE 3><35%>
	O! let us hence; I stand on sudden haste.
<SPEECH 87><ACT 2><SCENE 4><37%>
	Good morrow to you both. What counterfeit did I give you?
<SPEECH 88><ACT 2><SCENE 4><37%>
	Pardon, good Mercutio, my business was great; and in such a case as mine a man may strain courtesy.
<SPEECH 89><ACT 2><SCENE 4><37%>
	Meaning—to curtsy.
<SPEECH 90><ACT 2><SCENE 4><37%>
	A most courteous exposition.
<SPEECH 91><ACT 2><SCENE 4><37%>
	Pink for flower.
<SPEECH 92><ACT 2><SCENE 4><37%>
	Why, then, is my pump well flowered.
<SPEECH 93><ACT 2><SCENE 4><37%>
	O single-soled jest! solely singular for the singleness.
<SPEECH 94><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	Switch and spurs, switch and spurs; or I'll cry a match.
<SPEECH 95><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	Thou wast never with me for anything when thou wast not here for the goose.
<SPEECH 96><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	Nay, good goose, bite not.
<SPEECH 97><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	And is it not then well served in to a sweet goose?
<SPEECH 98><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	I stretch it out for that word 'broad;' which added to the goose, proves thee far and wide a broad goose.
<SPEECH 99><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	Here's goodly gear!
<SPEECH 100><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	One, gentlewoman, that God hath made for himself to mar.
<SPEECH 101><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	I can tell you; but young Romeo will be older when you have found him than he was when you sought him: I am the youngest of that name, for fault of a worse.
<SPEECH 102><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	What hast thou found?
<SPEECH 103><ACT 2><SCENE 4><40%>
	I will follow you.
<SPEECH 104><ACT 2><SCENE 4><40%>
	A gentleman, nurse, that loves to hear himself talk, and will speak more in a minute than he will stand to in a month.
<SPEECH 105><ACT 2><SCENE 4><40%>
	Nurse, commend me to thy lady and mistress. I protest unto thee,—
<SPEECH 106><ACT 2><SCENE 4><41%>
	What wilt thou tell her, nurse? thou dost not mark me.
<SPEECH 107><ACT 2><SCENE 4><41%>
	Bid her devise
	Some means to come to shrift this afternoon;
	And there she shall at Friar Laurence' cell,
	Be shriv'd and married. Here is for thy pains.
<SPEECH 108><ACT 2><SCENE 4><41%>
	Go to; I say, you shall.
<SPEECH 109><ACT 2><SCENE 4><41%>
	And stay, good nurse; behind the abbey wall:
	Within this hour my man shall be with thee,
	And bring thee cords made like a tackled stair;
	Which to the high top-gallant of my joy
	Must be my convoy in the secret night.
	Farewell! Be trusty, and I'll quit thy pains.
	Farewell! Commend me to thy mistress.
<SPEECH 110><ACT 2><SCENE 4><41%>
	What sayst thou, my dear nurse?
<SPEECH 111><ACT 2><SCENE 4><41%>
	I warrant thee my man's as true as steel.
<SPEECH 112><ACT 2><SCENE 4><42%>
	Ay, nurse: what of that? both with an R.
<SPEECH 113><ACT 2><SCENE 4><42%>
	Commend me to thy lady.
<SPEECH 114><ACT 2><SCENE 6><45%>
	Amen, amen! but come what sorrow can,
	It cannot countervail the exchange of joy
	That one short minute gives me in her sight:
	Do thou but close our hands with holy words,
	Then love-devouring death do what he dare;
	It is enough I may but call her mine.
<SPEECH 115><ACT 2><SCENE 6><45%>
	Ah! Juliet, if the measure of thy joy
	Be heap'd like mine, and that thy skill be more
	To blazon it, then sweeten with thy breath
	This neighbour air, and let rich music's tongue
	Unfold the imagin'd happiness that both
	Receive in either by this dear encounter.
<SPEECH 116><ACT 3><SCENE 1><48%>
	Tybalt, the reason that I have to love thee
	Doth much excuse the appertaining rage
	To such a greeting; villain am I none,
	Therefore farewell; I see thou know'st me not.
<SPEECH 117><ACT 3><SCENE 1><48%>
	I do protest I never injur'd thee,
	But love thee better than thou canst devise,
	Till thou shalt know the reason of my love:
	And so, good Capulet, which name I tender
	As dearly as my own, be satisfied.
<SPEECH 118><ACT 3><SCENE 1><49%>
	Gentle Mercutio, put thy rapier up.
<SPEECH 119><ACT 3><SCENE 1><49%>
	Draw, Benvolio; beat down their weapons.
	Gentlemen, for shame, forbear this outrage!
	Tybalt, Mercutio, the prince expressly hath
	Forbidden bandying in Verona streets.
	Hold, Tybalt! good Mercutio!
<SPEECH 120><ACT 3><SCENE 1><49%>
	Courage, man; the hurt cannot be much.
<SPEECH 121><ACT 3><SCENE 1><49%>
	I thought all for the best.
<SPEECH 122><ACT 3><SCENE 1><49%>
	This gentleman, the prince's near ally,
	My very friend, hath got his mortal hurt
	In my behalf; my reputation stain'd
	With Tybalt's slander, Tybalt, that an hour
	Hath been my kinsman. O sweet Juliet!
	Thy beauty hath made me effeminate,
	And in my temper soften'd valour's steel!
<SPEECH 123><ACT 3><SCENE 1><50%>
	This day's black fate on more days doth depend;
	This but begins the woe others must end.
<SPEECH 124><ACT 3><SCENE 1><50%>
	Alive! in triumph! and Mercutio slain!
	Away to heaven, respective lenity,
	And fire-ey'd fury be my conduct now!
	Now, Tybalt, take the villain back again
	That late thou gav'st me; for Mercutio's soul
	Is but a little way above our heads,
	Staying for thine to keep him company:
	Either thou, or I, or both, must go with him.
<SPEECH 125><ACT 3><SCENE 1><50%>
	This shall determine that.
<SPEECH 126><ACT 3><SCENE 1><50%>
	O! I am Fortune's fool.
<SPEECH 127><ACT 3><SCENE 3><57%>
	Father, what news? what is the prince's doom?
	What sorrow craves acquaintance at my hand,
	That I yet know not?
<SPEECH 128><ACT 3><SCENE 3><57%>
	What less than doomsday is the prince's doom?
<SPEECH 129><ACT 3><SCENE 3><57%>
	Ha! banishment! be merciful, say 'death;'
	For exile hath more terror in his look,
	Much more than death: do not say 'banishment.'
<SPEECH 130><ACT 3><SCENE 3><58%>
	There is no world without Verona walls,
	But purgatory, torture, hell itself.
	Hence banished is banish'd from the world,
	And world's exile is death; then 'banished,'
	Is death mis-term'd. Calling death 'banished,'
	Thou cutt'st my head off with a golden axe,
	And smil'st upon the stroke that murders me.
<SPEECH 131><ACT 3><SCENE 3><58%>
	'Tis torture, and not mercy: heaven is here,
	Where Juliet lives; and every cat and dog
	And little mouse, every unworthy thing,
	Live here in heaven and may look on her;
	But Romeo may not: more validity,
	More honourable state, more courtship lives
	In carrion flies than Romeo: they may seize
	On the white wonder of dear Juliet's hand,
	And steal immortal blessing from her lips,
	Who, even in pure and vestal modesty,
	Still blush, as thinking their own kisses sin;
	Flies may do this, but I from this must fly:
	They are free men, but I am banished.
	And sayst thou yet that exile is not death?
	Hadst thou no poison mix'd, no sharp-ground knife,
	No sudden mean of death, though ne'er so mean,
	But 'banished' to kill me? 'Banished!'
	O friar! the damned use that word in hell;
	Howlings attend it: how hast thou the heart,
	Being a divine, a ghostly confessor,
	A sin-absolver, and my friend profess'd,
	To mangle me with that word 'banished?'
<SPEECH 132><ACT 3><SCENE 3><59%>
	O! thou wilt speak again of banishment.
<SPEECH 133><ACT 3><SCENE 3><59%>
	Yet 'banished!' Hang up philosophy!
	Unless philosophy can make a Juliet,
	Displant a town, reverse a prince's doom,
	It helps not, it prevails not: talk no more.
<SPEECH 134><ACT 3><SCENE 3><59%>
	How should they, when that wise men have no eyes?
<SPEECH 135><ACT 3><SCENE 3><59%>
	Thou canst not speak of that thou dost not feel:
	Wert thou as young as I, Juliet thy love,
	An hour but married, Tybalt murdered,
	Doting like me, and like me banished,
	Then mightst thou speak, then mightst thou tear thy hair,
	And fall upon the ground, as I do now,
	Taking the measure of an unmade grave.
<SPEECH 136><ACT 3><SCENE 3><59%>
	Not I; unless the breath of heart-sick groans,
	Mist-like, infold me from the search of eyes.
<SPEECH 137><ACT 3><SCENE 3><60%>
	Nurse!
<SPEECH 138><ACT 3><SCENE 3><60%>
	Spak'st thou of Juliet? how is it with her?
	Doth she not think me an old murderer,
	Now I have stain'd the childhood of our joy.
	With blood remov'd but little from her own?
	Where is she? and how doth she? and what says
	My conceal'd lady to our cancell'd love?
<SPEECH 139><ACT 3><SCENE 3><60%>
	As if that name,
	Shot from the deadly level of a gun,
	Did murder her; as that name's cursed hand
	Murder'd her kinsman. O! tell me, friar, tell me,
	In what vile part of this anatomy
	Doth my name lodge? tell me, that I may sack
	The hateful mansion.
<SPEECH 140><ACT 3><SCENE 3><62%>
	Do so, and bid my sweet prepare to chide.
<SPEECH 141><ACT 3><SCENE 3><62%>
	How well my comfort is reviv'd by this!
<SPEECH 142><ACT 3><SCENE 3><63%>
	But that a joy past joy calls out on me,
	It were a grief so brief to part with thee:
	Farewell.
<SPEECH 143><ACT 3><SCENE 5><64%>
	It was the lark, the herald of the morn,
	No nightingale: look, love, what envious streaks
	Do lace the severing clouds in yonder east:
	Night's candles are burnt out, and jocund day
	Stands tiptoe on the misty mountain tops:
	I must be gone and live, or stay and die.
<SPEECH 144><ACT 3><SCENE 5><64%>
	Let me be ta'en, let me be put to death;
	I am content, so thou wilt have it so.
	I'll say yon grey is not the morning's eye,
	'Tis but the pale reflex of Cynthia's brow;
	Nor that is not the lark, whose notes do beat
	The vaulty heaven so high above our heads:
	I have more care to stay than will to go:
	Come, death, and welcome! Juliet wills it so.
	How is't, my soul? let's talk; it is not day.
<SPEECH 145><ACT 3><SCENE 5><65%>
	More light and light; more dark and dark our woes.
<SPEECH 146><ACT 3><SCENE 5><65%>
	Farewell, farewell! one kiss, and I'll descend.
<SPEECH 147><ACT 3><SCENE 5><65%>
	Farewell!
	I will omit no opportunity
	That may convey my greetings, love, to thee.
<SPEECH 148><ACT 3><SCENE 5><66%>
	I doubt it not; and all these woes shall serve
	For sweet discourses in our time to come.
<SPEECH 149><ACT 3><SCENE 5><66%>
	And trust me, love, in my eye so do you:
	Dry sorrow drinks our blood. Adieu! adieu!
<SPEECH 150><ACT 5><SCENE 1><85%>
	If I may trust the flattering truth of sleep,
	My dreams presage some joyful news at hand:
	My bosom's lord sits lightly in his throne;
	And all this day an unaccustom'd spirit
	Lifts me above the ground with cheerful thoughts.
	I dreamt my lady came and found me dead;—
	Strange dream, that gives a dead man leave to think,—
	And breath'd such life with kisses in my lips,
	That I reviv'd, and was an emperor.
	Ah me! how sweet is love itself possess'd,
	When but love's shadows are so rich in joy!
	News from Verona! How now, Balthasar?
	Dost thou not bring me letters from the friar?
	How doth my lady? Is my father well?
	How fares my Juliet? That I ask again;
	For nothing can be ill if she be well.
<SPEECH 151><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	Is it even so? then I defy you, stars!
	Thou know'st my lodging: get me ink and paper,
	And hire post-horses; I will hence to-night.
<SPEECH 152><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	Tush, thou art deceiv'd;
	Leave me, and do the thing I bid thee do.
	Hast thou no letters to me from the friar?
<SPEECH 153><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	No matter; get thee gone,
	And hire those horses: I'll be with thee straight.
	Well, Juliet, I will he with thee to-night.
	Let's see for means: O mischief! thou art swift
	To enter in the thoughts of desperate men.
	I do remember an apothecary,
	And hereabouts he dwells, which late I noted
	In tatter'd weeds, with overwhelming brows,
	Culling of simples; meagre were his looks,
	Sharp misery had worn him to the bones:
	And in his needy shop a tortoise hung,
	An alligator stuff'd, and other skins
	Of ill-shap'd fishes; and about his shelves
	A beggarly account of empty boxes,
	Green earthen pots, bladders, and musty seeds,
	Remnants of packthread, and old cakes of roses,
	Were thinly scatter'd, to make up a show.
	Noting this penury, to myself I said
	An if a man did need a poison now,
	Whose sale is present death in Mantua,
	Here lives a caitiff wretch would sell it him.
	O! this same thought did but fore-run my need,
	And this same needy man must sell it me.
	As I remember, this should be the house:
	Being holiday, the beggar's shop is shut.
	What, ho! apothecary!
<SPEECH 154><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Come hither, man. I see that thou art poor;
	Hold, there is forty ducats; let me have
	A dram of poison, such soon-speeding gear
	As will disperse itself through all the veins
	That the life-weary taker may fall dead,
	And that the trunk may be discharg'd of breath
	As violently as hasty powder fir'd
	Doth hurry from the fatal cannon's womb.
<SPEECH 155><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	Art thou so bare, and full of wretchedness,
	And fear'st to die? famine is in thy cheeks,
	Need and oppression starveth in thine eyes,
	Contempt and beggary hang upon thy back;
	The world is not thy friend nor the world's law:
	The world affords no law to make thee rich;
	Then be not poor, but break it, and take this.
<SPEECH 156><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	I pay thy poverty, and not thy will.
<SPEECH 157><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	There is thy gold, worse poison to men's souls,
	Doing more murders in this loathsome world
	Than these poor compounds that thou mayst not sell:
	I sell thee poison, thou hast sold me none.
	Farewell; buy food, and get thyself in flesh.
	Come, cordial and not poison, go with me
	To Juliet's grave, for there must I use thee.
<SPEECH 158><ACT 5><SCENE 3><90%>
	Give me that mattock, and the wrenching iron.
	Hold, take this letter; early in the morning
	See thou deliver it to my lord and father.
	Give me the light: upon thy life I charge thee,
	Whate'er thou hear'st or seest, stand all aloof,
	And do not interrupt me in my course.
	Why I descend into this bed of death,
	Is partly, to behold my lady's face;
	But chiefly to take thence from her dead finger
	A precious ring, a ring that I must use
	In dear employment: therefore hence, be gone:
	But, if thou, jealous, dost return to pry
	In what I further shall intend to do,
	By heaven, I will tear thee joint by joint,
	And strew this hungry churchyard with thy limbs.
	The time and my intents are savage-wild,
	More fierce and more inexorable far
	Than empty tigers or the roaring sea.
<SPEECH 159><ACT 5><SCENE 3><91%>
	So shalt thou show me friendship. Take thou that:
	Live, and be prosperous; and farewell, good fellow.
<SPEECH 160><ACT 5><SCENE 3><91%>
	Thou detestable maw, thou womb of death,
	Gorg'd with the dearest morsel of the earth,
	Thus I enforce thy rotten jaws to open,
	And, in despite, I'll cram thee with more food!
<SPEECH 161><ACT 5><SCENE 3><91%>
	I must, indeed; and therefore came I hither.
	Good gentle youth, tempt not a desperate man;
	Fly hence and leave me: think upon these gone;
	Let them affright thee. I beseech thee, youth,
	Put not another sin upon my head
	By urging me to fury: O! be gone:
	By heaven, I love thee better than myself.
	For I come hither arm'd against myself:
	Stay not, be gone; live, and hereafter say
	A madman's mercy bade thee run away.
<SPEECH 162><ACT 5><SCENE 3><92%>
	Wilt thou provoke me? then have at thee, boy!
<SPEECH 163><ACT 5><SCENE 3><92%>
	In faith, I will. Let me peruse this face:
	Mercutio's kinsman, noble County Paris!
	What said my man when my betossed soul
	Did not attend him as we rode? I think
	He told me Paris should have married Juliet:
	Said he not so? or did I dream it so?
	Or am I mad, hearing him talk of Juliet,
	To think it was so? O! give me thy hand,
	One writ with me in sour misfortune's book:
	I'll bury thee in a triumphant grave;
	A grave? O, no! a lanthorn, slaughter'd youth,
	For here lies Juliet, and her beauty makes
	This vault a feasting presence full of light.
	Death, lie thou there, by a dead man interr'd,
	How oft when men are at the point of death
	Have they been merry! which their keepers call
	A lightning before death: O! how may I
	Call this a lightning? O my love! my wife!
	Death, that hath suck'd the honey of thy breath,
	Hath had no power yet upon thy beauty:
	Thou art not conquer'd; beauty's ensign yet
	Is crimson in thy lips and in thy cheeks,
	And death's pale flag is not advanced there.
	Tybalt, liest thou there in thy bloody sheet?
	O! what more favour can I do to thee,
	Than with that hand that cut thy youth in twain
	To sunder his that was thine enemy?
	Forgive me, cousin! Ah! dear Juliet,
	Why art thou yet so fair? Shall I believe
	That unsubstantial Death is amorous,
	And that the lean abhorred monster keeps
	Thee here in dark to be his paramour?
	For fear of that I still will stay with thee,
	And never from this palace of dim night
	Depart again: here, here will I remain
	With worms that are thy chambermaids; O! here
	Will I set up my everlasting rest,
	And shake the yoke of inauspicious stars
	From this world-wearied flesh. Eyes, look your last!
	Arms, take your last embrace! and, lips, O you
	The doors of breath, seal with a righteous kiss
	A dateless bargain to engrossing death!
	Come, bitter conduct, come, unsavoury guide!
	Thou desperate pilot, now at once run on
	The dashing rocks thy sea-sick weary bark!
	Here's to my love! <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> O true apothecary!
	Thy drugs are quick. Thus with a kiss I die.
