<SPEECH 1><ACT 2><SCENE 2><26%>
	Both your majesties
	Might, by the sovereign power you have of us,
	Put your dread pleasures more into command
	Than to entreaty.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	</STAGE DIR> God save you, sir!
<SPEECH 3><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	My most dear lord!
<SPEECH 4><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	As the indifferent children of the earth.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	Neither, my lord.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	None, my lord, but that the world's grown honest.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	Then is the world one.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	We think not so, my lord.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	Why, then your ambition makes it one; 'tis too narrow for your mind.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	Truly, and I hold ambition of so airy and light a quality that it is but a shadow's shadow.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	We'll wait upon you.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	To visit you, my lord; no other occasion.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 2><33%>
	To what end, my lord?
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 2><33%>
	</STAGE DIR> What say you?
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 2><33%>
	My lord, there was no such stuff in my thoughts.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 2><33%>
	To think, my lord; if you delight not in man, what lenten entertainment the players shall receive from you: we coted them on the way; and hither are they coming, to offer you service.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 2><34%>
	Even those you were wont to take delight in, the tragedians of the city.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 2><34%>
	I think their inhibition comes by the means of the late innovation.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 2><34%>
	No, indeed they are not.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 2><34%>
	Nay, their endeavour keeps in the wonted pace: but there is, sir, an aery of children, little eyases, that cry out on the top of question, and are most tyrannically clapped for't: these are now the fashion, and so berattle the common stages,—so they call them,—that many wearing rapiers are afraid of goose-quills, and dare scarce come thither.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 2><34%>
	Faith, there has been much to-do on both sides: and the nation holds it no sin to tarre them to controversy: there was, for a while, no money bid for argument, unless the poet and the player went to cuffs in the question.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 2><35%>
	Ay, that they do, my lord; Hercules and his load too.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 2><35%>
	Happily he's the second time come to them; for they say an old man is twice a child.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 2><SCENE 2><39%>
	Good my lord!
<SPEECH 25><ACT 3><SCENE 1><41%>
	He does confess he feels himself distracted;
	But from what cause he will by no means speak.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 3><SCENE 1><41%>
	Most like a gentleman.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 3><SCENE 1><41%>
	Niggard of question, but of our demands
	Most free in his reply.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 3><SCENE 1><41%>
	Madam, it so fell out that certain players
	We o'er-raught on the way; of these we told him,
	And there did seem in him a kind of joy
	To hear of it: they are about the court,
	And, as I think, they have already order
	This night to play before him.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 3><SCENE 1><41%>
	We shall, my lord.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 3><SCENE 2><47%>
	We will, my lord.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 3><SCENE 2><48%>
	Ay, my lord; they stay upon your patience.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 3><SCENE 2><54%>
	Then, thus she says: your behaviour hath struck her into amasement and admiration.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 3><SCENE 2><54%>
	She desires to speak with you in her closet ere you go to bed.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 3><SCENE 2><54%>
	My lord, you once did love me.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 3><SCENE 2><54%>
	Good my lord, what is your cause of distemper? you do surely bar the door upon your own liberty, if you deny your griefs to your friend.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 3><SCENE 2><54%>
	How can that be when you have the voice of the king himself for your succession in Denmark?
<SPEECH 37><ACT 3><SCENE 3><56%>
	The single and peculiar life is bound
	With all the strength and armour of the mind
	To keep itself from noyance; but much more
	That spirit upon whose weal depend and rest
	The lives of many. The cease of majesty
	Dies not alone, but, like a gulf doth draw
	What's near it with it; it is a massy wheel,
	Fix'd on the summit of the highest mount,
	To whose huge spokes ten thousand lesser things
	Are mortis'd and adjoin'd; which, when it falls,
	Each small annexment, petty consequence,
	Attends the boisterous ruin. Never alone
	Did the king sigh, but with a general groan.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 3><SCENE 3><57%>
	We will haste us.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 4><SCENE 2><66%>
	</STAGE DIR> Hamlet! Lord Hamlet!
<SPEECH 40><ACT 4><SCENE 2><66%>
	What have you done, my lord, with the dead body?
<SPEECH 41><ACT 4><SCENE 2><66%>
	Tell us where 'tis, that we may take it thence
	And bear it to the chapel.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 4><SCENE 2><66%>
	Believe what?
<SPEECH 43><ACT 4><SCENE 2><66%>
	Take you me for a sponge, my lord?
<SPEECH 44><ACT 4><SCENE 2><66%>
	I understand you not, my lord.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 4><SCENE 2><66%>
	My lord, you must tell us where the body is, and go with us to the king.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 4><SCENE 3><67%>
	Where the dead body is bestow'd, my lord,
	We cannot get from him.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 4><SCENE 3><67%>
	Without, my lord; guarded, to know your pleasure.
<SPEECH 48><ACT 4><SCENE 3><67%>
	Ho, Guildenstern! bring in my lord.
<SPEECH 49><ACT 4><SCENE 4><69%>
	Will 't please you go, my lord?
