<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 2><3%>
	God save the king!
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 2><3%>
	From Fife, great king;
	Where the Norweyan banners flout the sky
	And fan our people cold. Norway himself,
	With terrible numbers,
	Assisted by that most disloyal traitor,
	The Thane of Cawdor, began a dismal conflict;
	Till that Bellona's bridegroom, lapp'd in proof,
	Confronted him with self-comparisons,
	Point against point, rebellious arm 'gainst arm,
	Curbing his lavish spirit: and, to conclude,
	The victory fell on us.—
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 2><4%>
	That now
	Sweno, the Norways' king, craves composition;
	Nor would we deign him burial of his men
	Till he disbursed, at Saint Colme's Inch,
	Ten thousand dollars to our general use.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 2><4%>
	I'll see it done.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 3><8%>
	The king hath happily receiv'd, Macbeth,
	The news of thy success; and when he reads
	Thy personal venture in the rebels' fight,
	His wonders and his praises do contend
	Which should be thine or his. Silenc'd with that,
	In viewing o'er the rest o' the self-same day,
	He finds thee in the stout Norweyan ranks,
	Nothing afeard of what thyself didst make,
	Strange images of death. As thick as hail
	Came post with post, and every one did bear
	Thy praises in his kingdom's great defence,
	And pour'd them down before him.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 3><8%>
	And, for an earnest of a greater honour,
	He bade me, from him, call thee Thane of Cawdor:
	In which addition, hail, most worthy thane!
	For it is thine.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 2><SCENE 4><37%>
	Ah! good father,
	Thou seest, the heavens, as troubled with man's act,
	Threaten his bloody stage: by the clock 'tis day,
	And yet dark night strangles the travelling lamp.
	Is 't night's predominance, or the day's shame,
	That darkness does the face of earth entomb,
	When living light should kiss it?
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	And Duncan's horses,—a thing most strange and certain,—
	Beauteous and swift, the minions of their race,
	Turn'd wild in nature, broke their stalls, flung out,
	Contending 'gainst obedience, as they would
	Make war with mankind.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	They did so; to the amazement of mine eyes,
	That look'd upon 't. Here comes the good Macduff.
	How goes the world, sir, now?
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	Is 't known who did this more than bloody deed?
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	Alas, the day!
	What good could they pretend?
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	'Gainst nature still!
	Thriftless ambition, that wilt ravin up
	Thine own life's means! Then 'tis most like
	The sovereignty will fall upon Macbeth.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	Where is Duncan's body?
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	Will you to Scone?
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	Well, I will thither.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	Farewell, father.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 3><SCENE 4><52%>
	His absence, sir,
	Lays blame upon his promise. Please 't your highness
	To grace us with your royal company.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 3><SCENE 4><52%>
	Gentlemen, rise; his highness is not well.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 3><SCENE 4><55%>
	What sights, my lord?
<SPEECH 20><ACT 4><SCENE 2><68%>
	You must have patience, madam.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 4><SCENE 2><68%>
	You know not
	Whether it was his wisdom or his fear.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 4><SCENE 2><68%>
	My dearest coz,
	I pray you, school yourself: but, for your husband,
	He is noble, wise, judicious, and best knows
	The fits o' the season. I dare not speak much further:
	But cruel are the times, when we are traitors
	And do not know ourselves, when we hold rumour
	From what we fear, yet know not what we fear,
	But float upon a wild and violent sea
	Each way and move. I take my leave of you:
	Shall not be long but I'll be here again.
	Things at the worst will cease, or else climb upward
	To what they were before. My pretty cousin,
	Blessing upon you!
<SPEECH 23><ACT 4><SCENE 2><69%>
	I am so much a fool, should I stay longer,
	It would be my disgrace, and your discomfort:
	I take my leave at once.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	Sir, amen.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	Alas! poor country;
	Almost afraid to know itself. It cannot
	Be call'd our mother, but our grave; where nothing,
	But who knows nothing, is once seen to smile;
	Where sighs and groans and shrieks that rent the air
	Are made, not mark'd; where violent sorrow seems
	A modern ecstasy; the dead man's knell
	Is there scarce ask'd for who; and good men's lives
	Expire before the flowers in their caps,
	Dying or ere they sicken.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	That of an hour's age doth hiss the speaker;
	Each minute teems a new one.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	Why, well.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	Well too.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	No; they were well at peace when I did leave 'em.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 4><SCENE 3><80%>
	When I came hither to transport the tidings,
	Which I have heavily borne, there ran a rumour
	Of many worthy fellows that were out;
	Which was to my belief witness'd the rather
	For that I saw the tyrant's power a-foot.
	Now is the time of help; your eye in Scotland
	Would create soldiers, make our women fight,
	To doff their dire distresses.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 4><SCENE 3><80%>
	Would I could answer
	This comfort with the like! But I have words
	That would be howl'd out in the desert air,
	Where hearing should not latch them.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 4><SCENE 3><80%>
	No mind that's honest
	But in it shares some woe, though the main part
	Pertains to you alone.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 4><SCENE 3><80%>
	Let not your ears despise my tongue for ever,
	Which shall possess them with the heaviest sound
	That ever yet they heard.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 4><SCENE 3><81%>
	Your castle is surpris'd; your wife and babes
	Savagely slaughter'd; to relate the manner,
	Were, on the quarry of these murder'd deer,
	To add the death of you.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 4><SCENE 3><81%>
	Wife, children, servants, all
	That could be found.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 4><SCENE 3><81%>
	I have said.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 5><SCENE 7><98%>
	Your son, my lord, has paid a soldier's debt:
	He only liv'd but till he was a man;
	The which no sooner had his prowess confirm'd
	In the unshrinking station where he fought,
	But like a man he died.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 5><SCENE 7><98%>
	Ay, and brought off the field. Your cause of sorrow
	Must not be measur'd by his worth, for then
	It hath no end.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 5><SCENE 7><99%>
	Ay, on the front.
